<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<search>
  
  
  
  <entry>
    <title>好的写作</title>
    <link href="/2025/07/14/good-wrting/"/>
    <url>/2025/07/14/good-wrting/</url>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="GOOD-WRITING"><a href="#GOOD-WRITING" class="headerlink" title="GOOD WRITING"></a>GOOD WRITING</h2><p>原文链接: <a href="https://paulgraham.com/goodwriting.html">https://paulgraham.com/goodwriting.html</a></p><h3 id="一、听起来好-与-观点正确"><a href="#一、听起来好-与-观点正确" class="headerlink" title="一、听起来好 与 观点正确"></a>一、听起来好 与 观点正确</h3><p>There are two senses in which writing can be good: it can sound good, and the ideas can be right. It can have nice, flowing sentences, and it can draw correct conclusions about important things. It might seem as if these two kinds of good would be unrelated, like the speed of a car and the color it’s painted. And yet I don’t think they are. I think writing that sounds good is more likely to be right. </p><p>好的写作可以体现在两个方面：一是<strong>听起来好</strong>，二是<strong>思想正确</strong>。它可以拥有流畅优美的句子，也可以对重要事物得出正确的结论。乍看之下，这两种“好”似乎毫无关联，就像汽车的速度和它的颜色一样互不相干。然而，我认为它们并非如此。<strong>我认为听起来好的文字，更可能是正确的。</strong></p><p>So here we have the most exciting kind of idea: one that seems both preposterous and true. Let’s examine it. How can this possibly be true? </p><p>于是，我们遇到了最令人兴奋的那种观点：一个看似荒谬却又真实的想法。让我们仔细审视它——这怎么可能成立？</p><p>I know it’s true from writing. You can’t simultaneously optimize two unrelated things; when you push one far enough, you always end up sacrificing the other. And yet no matter how hard I push, I never find myself having to choose between the sentence that sounds best and the one that expresses an idea best. If I did, it would be frivolous to care how sentences sound. But in practice it feels the opposite of frivolous. Fixing sentences that sound bad seems to help get the ideas right. [1] </p><p>我从写作中知道这是真的。你无法同时优化两件毫无关联的事情；当你把其中一件事推到极致时，总会牺牲另一件。然而，无论我如何努力，我从未发现自己必须在“听起来最好的句子”和“表达思想最准确的句子”之间做选择。如果真是这样，纠结句子的音律就显得轻浮了。但实践中，这种感觉恰恰相反——<strong>修改听起来别扭的句子，似乎能帮助理清思想</strong>[1]</p><p>By right I mean more than just true. Getting the ideas right means developing them well — drawing the conclusions that matter most, and exploring each one to the right level of detail. So getting the ideas right is not just a matter of saying true things, but saying the right true things. </p><p>这里的“正确”不仅仅是“真实”。思想正确意味着充分发展它们——得出最重要的结论，并以恰当的细节层次展开。因此，思想正确不只是说真话，而是说出<strong>该说的真话</strong>。</p><p>How could trying to make sentences sound good help you do that? The clue to the answer is something I noticed 30 years ago when I was doing the layout for my first book. Sometimes when you’re laying out text you have bad luck. For example, you get a section that runs one line longer than the page. I don’t know what ordinary typesetters do in this situation, but what I did was rewrite the section to make it a line shorter. You’d expect such an arbitrary constraint to make the writing worse. But I found, to my surprise, that it never did. I always ended up with something I liked better. </p><p>为什么追求句子的音律能帮助做到这一点？答案的线索来自30年前我为第一本书排版时的发现。排版时偶尔会遇到厄运：比如某个章节比页面多出一行。我不知道普通排版师会怎么做，但我的解决方法是重写那段，让它缩短一行。这种武断的限制本该让文字变得更糟，但出乎意料的是，结果总是更好。</p><h3 id="二、文章的重力定律"><a href="#二、文章的重力定律" class="headerlink" title="二、文章的重力定律"></a>二、文章的重力定律</h3><p>I don’t think this was because my writing was especially careless. I think if you pointed to a random paragraph in anything written by anyone and told them to make it slightly shorter (or longer), they’d probably be able to come up with something better.</p><p>The best analogy for this phenomenon is when you shake a bin full of different objects. The shakes are arbitrary motions. Or more precisely, they’re not calculated to make any two specific objects fit more closely together. And yet repeated shaking inevitably makes the objects discover brilliantly clever ways of packing themselves. Gravity won’t let them become less tightly packed, so any change has to be a change for the better. [2] </p><p>我不认为这是因为我的写作特别粗心。我相信，如果随机指一段别人的文字并要求稍作删减（或扩充），他们很可能改得更好。</p><p>这种现象的最佳类比是摇晃装满杂物的箱子。摇晃是随机的动作，或者说，它并非为了让某两件物品更紧密贴合。然而，反复摇晃最终会让物品找到绝妙的排列方式。重力不允许它们松散，所以任何变化都只能是优化[2]。</p><p>So it is with writing. If you have to rewrite an awkward passage, you’ll never do it in a way that makes it less true. You couldn’t bear it, any more than gravity could bear things floating upward. So any change in the ideas has to be a change for the better. </p><p>写作也是如此。如果你必须重写一段拗口的文字，绝不会以牺牲真实性为代价。你无法忍受这种妥协，就像重力无法接受物体向上飘浮。因此，思想上的任何调整都只能是改进。</p><p>It’s obvious once you think about it. Writing that sounds good is more likely to be right for the same reason that a well-shaken bin is more likely to be tightly packed. But there’s something else going on as well. Sounding good isn’t just a random external force that leaves the ideas in an essay better off. It actually helps you to get them right. </p><p>细想之下，这显而易见。<strong>听起来好的文字更可能是正确的，就像摇晃充分的箱子更可能紧凑</strong>。但还有另一层原因：音律并非只是随机外力，被动地优化文章思想——它<strong>主动</strong>帮助你理清思路。</p><h3 id="三、好的文章是易读的"><a href="#三、好的文章是易读的" class="headerlink" title="三、好的文章是易读的"></a>三、好的文章是易读的</h3><p>The reason is that it makes the essay easier to read. It’s less work to read writing that flows well. How does that help the writer? Because the writer is the first reader. When I’m working on an essay, I spend far more time reading than writing. I’ll reread some parts 50 or 100 times, replaying the thoughts in them and asking myself, like someone sanding a piece of wood, does anything catch? Does anything feel wrong? And the easier the essay is to read, the easier it is to notice if something catches. </p><p>因为音律让文章更易读。流畅的文字减轻了阅读负担。这对作者有何帮助？因为<strong>作者是第一位读者</strong>。写文章时，我花在阅读上的时间远多于写作。某些段落我会重读50甚至100遍，反复咀嚼其中的思想，像打磨木头一样自问：是否有阻滞？是否有不对劲？文章越易读，越容易发现这些问题。</p><p>So yes, the two senses of good writing are connected in at least two ways. Trying to make writing sound good makes you fix mistakes unconsciously, and also helps you fix them consciously; it shakes the bin of ideas, and also makes mistakes easier to see. But now that we’ve dissolved one layer of preposterousness, I can’t resist adding another. Does sounding good do more than just help you get the ideas right? Is writing that sounds good inherently more likely to be right? Crazy as it may seem, I think that’s true too. </p><p>因此，好的写作的两个维度至少通过两种方式关联：追求音律能让你无意识地修正错误，也有助于有意识地改进；它既“摇晃思想的箱子”，又让错误更易察觉。但既然我们已经揭开了一层荒谬，我不妨再添一层：**音律的作用是否不止于辅助思想正确？听起来好的文字是否天生更可能是正确的？**尽管看似疯狂，我认为确实如此。</p><p>Obviously there’s a connection at the level of individual words. There are lots of words in English that sound like what they mean, often in wonderfully subtle ways. Glitter. Round. Scrape. Prim. Cavalcade. But the sound of good writing depends even more on the way you put words together, and there’s a connection at that level too. </p><p>显然，单个词汇层面就存在关联。英语中许多词的发音暗示其含义，且方式精妙至极。比如“glitter”（闪烁）、“round”（圆润）、“scrape”（刮擦）、“prim”（刻板）、“cavalcade”（队列）。但好文章的音律更多取决于词语组合方式，而这一层面同样存在联系。</p><h3 id="四、好的节奏产生好的文章"><a href="#四、好的节奏产生好的文章" class="headerlink" title="四、好的节奏产生好的文章"></a>四、好的节奏产生好的文章</h3><p>When writing sounds good, it’s mostly because it has good rhythm. But the rhythm of good writing is not the rhythm of music, or the meter of verse. It’s not so regular. If it were, it wouldn’t be good, because the rhythm of good writing has to match the ideas in it, and ideas have all kinds of different shapes. Sometimes they’re simple and you just state them. But other times they’re more subtle, and you need longer, more complicated sentences to tease out all the implications. </p><p>文章听起来好，主要因其节奏得当。但优秀写作的节奏并非音乐的韵律或诗歌的格律，它没那么规整。如果规整，反而不好，因为好文章的节奏必须匹配其中的思想，而思想的形态千差万别。有时它们简单直接，只需陈述；有时则微妙复杂，需要更长的句子梳理全部内涵。</p><p>An essay is a cleaned up train of thought, in the same way dialogue is cleaned up conversation, and a train of thought has a natural rhythm. So when an essay sounds good, it’s not merely because it has a pleasing rhythm, but because it has its natural one. Which means you can use getting the rhythm right as a heuristic for getting the ideas right. And not just in principle: good writers do both simultaneously as a matter of course. Often I don’t even distinguish between the two problems. I just think Ugh, this doesn’t sound right; what do I mean to say here? [3] </p><p>文章是整理过的思路轨迹，如同对白是加工过的对话，而思路自有其自然节奏。因此，文章音律好不仅因为节奏悦耳，更因为节奏<strong>自然</strong>。这意味着你可以把节奏正确作为思想正确的启发式标准。而且不仅是理论上的——优秀作者在实践中会同步解决这两个问题。我常甚至不区分它们，只是觉得“呃，这里听起来不对——我到底想说什么？”[3]</p><p>The sound of writing turns out to be more like the shape of a plane than the color of a car. If it looks good, as Kelly Johnson used to say, it will fly well. </p><p>最终，文字的音律更像飞机的气动外形，而非汽车的颜色。正如凯利·约翰逊所言：“如果它看起来对，飞起来就不会差。”</p><p>This is only true of writing that’s used to develop ideas, though. It doesn’t apply when you have ideas in some other way and then write about them afterward — for example, if you build something, or conduct an experiment, and then write a paper about it. In such cases the ideas often live more in the work than the writing, so the writing can be bad even though the ideas are good. The writing in textbooks and popular surveys can be bad for the same reason: the author isn’t developing the ideas, merely describing other people’s. It’s only when you’re writing to develop ideas that there’s such a close connection between the two senses of doing it well. </p><p>不过，这仅适用于<strong>用于发展思想的写作</strong>。如果你通过其他方式（比如建造某物或做实验）获得思想后再写成文章，音律与思想的关联就会减弱。这类情况下，思想更多存在于工作中而非文字里，因此文章可能糟糕但思想正确。教科书和科普读物的文字不佳也源于此——作者并非发展思想，只是转述他人。<strong>唯有当你通过写作探索思想时，两种“好”才会紧密相连。</strong></p><h3 id="内部一致与真实的重合"><a href="#内部一致与真实的重合" class="headerlink" title="内部一致与真实的重合"></a>内部一致与真实的重合</h3><p>Ok, many people will be thinking, this seems plausible so far, but what about liars? Is it not notoriously possible for a smooth-tongued liar to write something beautiful that’s completely false? </p><p>读到此处，许多人会想：目前为止还算合理，但骗子呢？巧舌如簧的骗子难道不能写出优美而完全虚假的文字吗？</p><p>It is, of course. But not without method acting. The way to write something beautiful and false is to begin by making yourself almost believe it. So just like someone writing something beautiful and true, you’re presenting a perfectly-formed train of thought. The difference is the point where it attaches to the world. You’re saying something that would be true if certain false premises were. If for some bizarre reason the number of jobs in a country were fixed, then immigrants really would be taking our jobs. </p><p>当然可以。但前提是<strong>方法派演技</strong>。写出美丽谎言的方法，是先让自己几乎相信它。因此，与写出美丽真理的人一样，你呈现的是一段完美成型的思路。区别在于它和现实的连接点——你描述的是一种在虚假前提下成立的真实。比如，如果某国工作岗位数量固定（尽管这荒诞），那么移民确实会“抢走我们的工作”。</p><p>So it’s not quite right to say that better sounding writing is more likely to be true. Better sounding writing is more likely to be internally consistent. If the writer is honest, internal consistency and truth converge. But while we can’t safely conclude that beautiful writing is true, it’s usually safe to conclude the converse: something that seems clumsily written will usually have gotten the ideas wrong too. </p><p>因此，“音律好的文字更可能真实”并不完全准确。更准确的说法是：<strong>音律好的文字更可能内部一致</strong>。如果作者诚实，内部一致与真实自会重合。</p><p>Indeed, the two senses of good writing are more like two ends of the same thing. The connection between them is not a rigid one; the goodness of good writing is not a rod but a rope, with multiple overlapping connections running through it. But it’s hard to move one end without moving the other. It’s hard to be right without sounding right.</p><p>虽然我们不能断言优美文字必然真实，但通常可以安全地反推：<strong>笨拙的文字往往思想也有问题</strong>。</p><p>事实上，好的写作的两个维度更像是同一事物的两端。它们的联系并非 rigid（僵硬的杆），而是 rope（柔韧的绳），内含多重交织的关联。但你很难只移动一端而不牵动另一端。<strong>很难正确而不听起来正确。</strong></p><p>Notes </p><p>[1] The closest thing to an exception is when you have to go back and insert a new point into the middle of something you’ve written. This often messes up the flow, sometimes in ways you can never quite repair. But I think the ultimate source of this problem is that ideas are tree-shaped and essays are linear. You inevitably run into difficulties when you try to cram the former into the latter. Frankly it’s surprising how much you can get away with. But even so you sometimes have to resort to an endnote. </p><p>[1] 最接近例外的情况是：当你需要在已写好的内容中插入新观点时，常会破坏行文流畅性，有时甚至无法完全修复。我认为根本原因在于思想是树状结构，而文章是线性的。将前者塞进后者时难免遇到困难。说实话，能勉强做到的程度已令人惊讶。但即便如此，有时你仍不得不借助尾注。</p><p>[2] Obviously if you shake the bin hard enough the objects in it can become less tightly packed. And similarly, if you imposed some huge external constraint on your writing, like using alternating one and two syllable words, the ideas would start to suffer. </p><p>[2] 显然，如果摇晃过于剧烈，箱内物品反而会变松散。同理，如果对写作施加某些极端限制（比如交替使用单双音节词），思想就会受损。</p><p>[3] Bizarrely enough, this happened in the writing of this very paragraph. An earlier version shared several phrases in common with the preceding paragraph, and the repetition bugged me each time I reread it. When I got annoyed enough to fix it, I discovered that the repetition reflected a problem in the underlying ideas, and I fixed both simultaneously.</p><p>[3] 诡异的是，这段文字的写作过程就印证了这一点。初稿与前一段有多个重复短语，每次重读都让我不适。当我终于忍无可忍去修改时，发现重复反映了底层思想的问题，于是同步修正了两者。</p>]]></content>
    
    
    <categories>
      
      <category>文章翻译</category>
      
    </categories>
    
    
    <tags>
      
      <tag>PAUL GRAHAM</tag>
      
    </tags>
    
  </entry>
  
  
  
  <entry>
    <title>Hello World</title>
    <link href="/2025/07/14/hello-world/"/>
    <url>/2025/07/14/hello-world/</url>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Welcome to <a href="https://hexo.io/">Hexo</a>! This is your very first post. Check <a href="https://hexo.io/docs/">documentation</a> for more info. If you get any problems when using Hexo, you can find the answer in <a href="https://hexo.io/docs/troubleshooting.html">troubleshooting</a> or you can ask me on <a href="https://github.com/hexojs/hexo/issues">GitHub</a>.</p><h2 id="Quick-Start"><a href="#Quick-Start" class="headerlink" title="Quick Start"></a>Quick Start</h2><h3 id="Create-a-new-post"><a href="#Create-a-new-post" class="headerlink" title="Create a new post"></a>Create a new post</h3><figure class="highlight bash"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre><span class="line">1</span><br></pre></td><td class="code"><pre><code class="hljs bash">$ hexo new <span class="hljs-string">&quot;My New Post&quot;</span><br></code></pre></td></tr></table></figure><p>More info: <a href="https://hexo.io/docs/writing.html">Writing</a></p><h3 id="Run-server"><a href="#Run-server" class="headerlink" title="Run server"></a>Run server</h3><figure class="highlight bash"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre><span class="line">1</span><br></pre></td><td class="code"><pre><code class="hljs bash">$ hexo server<br></code></pre></td></tr></table></figure><p>More info: <a href="https://hexo.io/docs/server.html">Server</a></p><h3 id="Generate-static-files"><a href="#Generate-static-files" class="headerlink" title="Generate static files"></a>Generate static files</h3><figure class="highlight bash"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre><span class="line">1</span><br></pre></td><td class="code"><pre><code class="hljs bash">$ hexo generate<br></code></pre></td></tr></table></figure><p>More info: <a href="https://hexo.io/docs/generating.html">Generating</a></p><h3 id="Deploy-to-remote-sites"><a href="#Deploy-to-remote-sites" class="headerlink" title="Deploy to remote sites"></a>Deploy to remote sites</h3><figure class="highlight bash"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre><span class="line">1</span><br></pre></td><td class="code"><pre><code class="hljs bash">$ hexo deploy<br></code></pre></td></tr></table></figure><p>More info: <a href="https://hexo.io/docs/one-command-deployment.html">Deployment</a></p>]]></content>
    
    
    
  </entry>
  
  
  
  
</search>
