<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<search>
  
  
  
  <entry>
    <title>平凡而惊奇</title>
    <link href="/2025/07/17/general-and-surprising/"/>
    <url>/2025/07/17/general-and-surprising/</url>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="GENERAL-AND-SURPRISING"><a href="#GENERAL-AND-SURPRISING" class="headerlink" title="GENERAL AND SURPRISING"></a>GENERAL AND SURPRISING</h2><p>原文链接: <a href="https://paulgraham.com/sun.html">https://paulgraham.com/sun.html</a></p><h3 id="一、最具价值的见解"><a href="#一、最具价值的见解" class="headerlink" title="一、最具价值的见解"></a>一、最具价值的见解</h3><p>The most valuable insights are both general and surprising. F &#x3D; ma for example. But general and surprising is a hard combination to achieve. That territory tends to be picked clean, precisely because those insights are so valuable. </p><p>最有价值的见解兼具普遍性和惊喜感。例如 F&#x3D;ma（牛顿第二运动定律）。但兼具普遍性和惊喜感是很难实现的，这类见解所在的领域往往已被挖掘殆尽，原因恰恰在于它们极具价值。</p><p>Ordinarily, the best that people can do is one without the other: either surprising without being general (e.g. gossip), or general without being surprising (e.g. platitudes). </p><p>通常情况下，鱼和熊掌不可兼得：要么有惊喜感却缺乏普遍性（比如八卦），要么有普遍性却毫无惊喜（比如陈词滥调）。</p><p>Where things get interesting is the moderately valuable insights. You get those from small additions of whichever quality was missing. The more common case is a small addition of generality: a piece of gossip that’s more than just gossip, because it teaches something interesting about the world. But another less common approach is to focus on the most general ideas and see if you can find something new to say about them. Because these start out so general, you only need a small delta of novelty to produce a useful insight. </p><p>真正有趣的是那些中等价值的见解。要获得这类见解，只需在缺失的特质上稍作补充。更常见的情况是补充少量普遍性：一条八卦之所以不只是八卦，是因为它能让人了解到关于世界的有趣之事。但另一种不太常见的方式是，聚焦于最具普遍性的观点，看看能否就它们说出些新东西。由于这些观点本身已经极具普遍性，因此只需一点新颖性的补充，就能产生有独到之处的见解。</p><h3 id="二、微小创意也能够带来巨大的不同"><a href="#二、微小创意也能够带来巨大的不同" class="headerlink" title="二、微小创意也能够带来巨大的不同"></a>二、微小创意也能够带来巨大的不同</h3><p>A small delta of novelty is all you’ll be able to get most of the time. Which means if you take this route, your ideas will seem a lot like ones that already exist. Sometimes you’ll find you’ve merely rediscovered an idea that did already exist. But don’t be discouraged. Remember the huge multiplier that kicks in when you do manage to think of something even a little new. </p><p>大多数时候，你能获得的只是少量的新颖性。这意味着如果你选择这条路径，你的观点看起来会和已有的观点十分相似。有时你会发现，自己只是重新发现了一个早已存在的观点。但不必气馁。记住，当你确实想到哪怕一点点新东西时，随之而来的乘法效应是巨大的。</p><p>Corollary: the more general the ideas you’re talking about, the less you should worry about repeating yourself. If you write enough, it’s inevitable you will. Your brain is much the same from year to year and so are the stimuli that hit it. I feel slightly bad when I find I’ve said something close to what I’ve said before, as if I were plagiarizing myself. But rationally one shouldn’t. You won’t say something exactly the same way the second time, and that variation increases the chance you’ll get that tiny but critical delta of novelty. </p><p>推论：你谈论的观点越具普遍性，就越不必担心重复自己。如果你写得足够多，重复是不可避免的。你的大脑年复一年变化不大，冲击它的刺激也大致相同。当我发现自己说的话和以前说过的很接近时，会略感不适，仿佛在抄袭自己。但理性而言，不必如此。你第二次不会用完全相同的方式表达，而这种差异会增加你获得那微小却关键的新颖性增量的机会。</p><h3 id="三、持续探索的勇气"><a href="#三、持续探索的勇气" class="headerlink" title="三、持续探索的勇气"></a>三、持续探索的勇气</h3><p>And of course, ideas beget ideas. (That sounds familiar.) An idea with a small amount of novelty could lead to one with more. But only if you keep going. So it’s doubly important not to let yourself be discouraged by people who say there’s not much new about something you’ve discovered. “Not much new” is a real achievement when you’re talking about the most general ideas. </p><p>当然，观点会催生新观点。（这话听着耳熟。）一个带有少量新颖性的观点可能会引出更具新颖性的观点，但前提是你要坚持下去。因此，当有人说你发现的东西没什么新意时，千万不要气馁，这一点尤为重要。当你谈论的是最具普遍性的观点时，“没太多新意” 其实是一项实实在在的成就。</p><p>It’s not true that there’s nothing new under the sun. There are some domains where there’s almost nothing new. But there’s a big difference between nothing and almost nothing, when it’s multiplied by the area under the sun.</p><p>“日光之下并无新事” 这句话并不正确。有些领域几乎没有新东西，但 “完全没有新东西” 和 “几乎没有新东西” 之间存在巨大差异，尤其是当它乘以 “日光之下的广阔领域” 时。</p>]]></content>
    
    
    <categories>
      
      <category>文章翻译</category>
      
    </categories>
    
    
    <tags>
      
      <tag>PAUL GRAHAM</tag>
      
    </tags>
    
  </entry>
  
  
  
  <entry>
    <title>何时去追寻你所热爱</title>
    <link href="/2025/07/16/follow-your-passion/"/>
    <url>/2025/07/16/follow-your-passion/</url>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="WHEN-TO-DO-WHAT-YOU-LOVE"><a href="#WHEN-TO-DO-WHAT-YOU-LOVE" class="headerlink" title="WHEN TO DO WHAT YOU LOVE"></a>WHEN TO DO WHAT YOU LOVE</h2><p>原文链接: <a href="https://paulgraham.com/when.html">https://paulgraham.com/when.html</a></p><h3 id="一、关于“追随热情”的争论"><a href="#一、关于“追随热情”的争论" class="headerlink" title="一、关于“追随热情”的争论"></a>一、关于“追随热情”的争论</h3><p>There’s some debate about whether it’s a good idea to “follow your passion.” In fact the question is impossible to answer with a simple yes or no. Sometimes you should and sometimes you shouldn’t, but the border between should and shouldn’t is very complicated. The only way to give a general answer is to trace it. </p><p>关于 “追随激情” 是否是个好主意，存在一些争议。事实上，这个问题无法用简单的 “是” 或 “否” 来回答。有时应该，有时不应该，但 “应该” 与 “不应该” 之间的界限非常复杂。给出一个一般性答案的唯一方法，是追溯其背后的逻辑。</p><p>When people talk about this question, there’s always an implicit “instead of.” All other things being equal, why wouldn’t you work on what interests you the most? So even raising the question implies that all other things aren’t equal, and that you have to choose between working on what interests you the most and something else, like what pays the best. </p><p>人们讨论这个问题时，总会隐含一个 “取而代之” 的前提。在其他条件相同的情况下，为什么不做自己最感兴趣的事呢？因此，即便提出这个问题，也意味着其他条件并不相同 —— 你必须在 “做最感兴趣的事” 和 “其他事”（比如薪资最高的事）之间做出选择。</p><p>And indeed if your main goal is to make money, you can’t usually afford to work on what interests you the most. People pay you for doing what they want, not what you want. But there’s an obvious exception: when you both want the same thing. For example, if you love football, and you’re good enough at it, you can get paid a lot to play it. </p><p>的确，若你的主要目标是赚钱，通常就没法只顾着做最感兴趣的事。人们付钱给你，是为了让你做他们想让你做的事，而非你自己想做的事。但有个明显的例外：当你和他们的需求一致时。比如，如果你热爱足球，且足够擅长，就能靠踢球赚很多钱。</p><p>Of course the odds are against you in a case like football, because so many other people like playing it too. This is not to say you shouldn’t try though. It depends how much ability you have and how hard you’re willing to work. </p><p>当然，在足球这类领域，成功的概率对你不利，因为太多人也喜欢踢球。但这并非说你不该尝试 —— 这取决于你的能力有多强，以及你愿意付出多少努力。</p><p>The odds are better when you have strange tastes: when you like something that pays well and that few other people like. For example, it’s clear that Bill Gates truly loved running a software company. He didn’t just love programming, which a lot of people do. He loved writing software for customers. That is a very strange taste indeed, but if you have it, you can make a lot by indulging it. </p><p>当你的喜好比较特别时，成功的概率会更高：比如你喜欢的事既能赚钱，又没多少人感兴趣。显然，比尔・盖茨是真的热爱经营软件公司。他不只是热爱编程（很多人都热爱编程），而是热爱为客户写软件。这确实是一种非常特别的喜好，但如果你有这种喜好，沉浸其中就能赚很多钱。</p><p>There are even some people who have a genuine intellectual interest in making money. This is distinct from mere greed. They just can’t help noticing when something is mispriced, and can’t help doing something about it. It’s like a puzzle for them. [1] </p><p>甚至有一些人，对赚钱有着真正的智力层面的兴趣。这和单纯的贪婪不同。他们总会不由自主地发现定价不合理的东西，也总会忍不住去做点什么。对他们来说，这就像一道谜题。[1]</p><h3 id="二、目标与兴趣的平衡"><a href="#二、目标与兴趣的平衡" class="headerlink" title="二、目标与兴趣的平衡"></a>二、目标与兴趣的平衡</h3><p>In fact there’s an edge case here so spectacular that it turns all the preceding advice on its head. If you want to make a really huge amount of money — hundreds of millions or even billions of dollars — it turns out to be very useful to work on what interests you the most. The reason is not the extra motivation you get from doing this, but that the way to make a really large amount of money is to start a startup, and working on what interests you is an excellent way to discover startup ideas. </p><p>事实上，这里有一个极端案例，它的影响之大，足以颠覆前面所有的建议。如果你想赚一大笔钱 —— 数亿甚至数十亿美元 —— 那么，做自己最感兴趣的事其实非常有用。原因并非做这些事能带来额外的动力，而是赚大钱的方式往往是创办初创公司，而做自己感兴趣的事，是发现初创公司创意的绝佳途径。</p><p>Many if not most of the biggest startups began as projects the founders were doing for fun. Apple, Google, and Facebook all began that way. Why is this pattern so common? Because the best ideas tend to be such outliers that you’d overlook them if you were consciously looking for ways to make money. Whereas if you’re young and good at technology, your unconscious instincts about what would be interesting to work on are very well aligned with what needs to be built. </p><p>即便不是大多数，也有很多顶尖的初创公司，最初都是创始人出于乐趣而做的项目。苹果、谷歌、脸书都是如此。为什么这种模式如此常见？因为最棒的创意往往太出格，如果你刻意追求赚钱，很可能会忽略它们。而如果你年轻且擅长技术，你对 “做什么事有趣” 的直觉，往往和 “该创造什么” 高度契合。</p><p>So there’s something like a midwit peak for making money. If you don’t need to make much, you can work on whatever you’re most interested in; if you want to become moderately rich, you can’t usually afford to; but if you want to become super rich, and you’re young and good at technology, working on what you’re most interested in becomes a good idea again. </p><p>所以，在赚钱这件事上，存在一种 “中等智慧峰值”：如果你不需要赚太多钱，就能做自己最感兴趣的事；如果你想变得小康，通常就不能只顾兴趣；但如果你想变得超级富有，且年轻又擅长技术，那么做自己最感兴趣的事又会成为一个好主意。</p><h3 id="三、何时做出抉择"><a href="#三、何时做出抉择" class="headerlink" title="三、何时做出抉择"></a>三、何时做出抉择</h3><p>What if you’re not sure what you want? What if you’re attracted to the idea of making money and more attracted to some kinds of work than others, but neither attraction predominates? How do you break ties? </p><p>如果你不确定自己想要什么呢？如果你既被赚钱的想法吸引，又对某些工作更感兴趣，但两者都没有绝对优势，该如何抉择？</p><p>The key here is to understand that such ties are only apparent. When you have trouble choosing between following your interests and making money, it’s never because you have complete knowledge of yourself and of the types of work you’re choosing between, and the options are perfectly balanced. When you can’t decide which path to take, it’s almost always due to ignorance. In fact you’re usually suffering from three kinds of ignorance simultaneously: you don’t know what makes you happy, what the various kinds of work are really like, or how well you could do them. [2] </p><p>关键在于，这种 “难以抉择” 往往只是表面现象。当你在 “追随兴趣” 和 “赚钱” 之间犹豫时，绝非因为你完全了解自己、了解可选的工作，且选项完美平衡。你无法决定，几乎总是因为信息不足 —— 你不知道什么能让自己快乐，不知道各种工作的真实情况，也不知道自己能把这些工作做得多好。[2]</p><p>In a way this ignorance is excusable. It’s often hard to predict these things, and no one even tells you that you need to. If you’re ambitious you’re told you should go to college, and this is good advice so far as it goes, but that’s where it usually ends. No one tells you how to figure out what to work on, or how hard this can be. </p><p>在某种程度上，这种信息不足是可以理解的。预测这些事往往很难，而且没人告诉你需要去弄清楚这些。如果你有野心，别人会告诉你应该上大学，这在某种程度上是个好建议，但通常也就到此为止了。没人告诉你该如何确定自己要做什么，也没人告诉你这件事有多难。</p><p>What do you do in the face of uncertainty? Get more certainty. And probably the best way to do that is to try working on things you’re interested in. That will get you more information about how interested you are in them, how good you are at them, and how much scope they offer for ambition. </p><p>面对不确定性该怎么办？去获取更多确定性。最好的方法可能就是尝试做自己感兴趣的事。这会让你更清楚自己对这件事的兴趣有多深、自己有多擅长，以及这件事能给你多大的发展空间。</p><p>Don’t wait. Don’t wait till the end of college to figure out what to work on. Don’t even wait for internships during college. You don’t necessarily need a job doing x in order to work on x; often you can just start doing it in some form yourself. And since figuring out what to work on is a problem that could take years to solve, the sooner you start, the better. </p><p>别等。别等到大学毕业才确定自己要做什么，甚至别等到大学期间的实习。你不一定非要找到一份做某件事的工作才能去做它 —— 通常你自己就能以某种形式开始。既然确定自己要做什么可能需要好几年，那么越早开始越好。</p><h3 id="四、时势造英雄"><a href="#四、时势造英雄" class="headerlink" title="四、时势造英雄"></a>四、时势造英雄</h3><p>One useful trick for judging different kinds of work is to look at who your colleagues will be. You’ll become like whoever you work with. Do you want to become like these people? </p><p>判断不同工作的一个有用技巧，是看看你未来的同事会是什么样的人。你会变得和他们越来越像。你想变成他们那样吗？</p><p>Indeed, the difference in character between different kinds of work is magnified by the fact that everyone else is facing the same decisions as you. If you choose a kind of work mainly for how well it pays, you’ll be surrounded by other people who chose it for the same reason, and that will make it even more soul-sucking than it seems from the outside. Whereas if you choose work you’re genuinely interested in, you’ll be surrounded mostly by other people who are genuinely interested in it, and that will make it extra inspiring. [3] </p><p>事实上，不同工作在 “人的特质” 上的差异，会因 “每个人都在做类似选择” 而被放大。如果你选一份工作主要是因为薪水高，身边就会围绕着同样为钱而来的人，这会让这份工作比表面看起来更让人身心俱疲。而如果你选择自己真正感兴趣的工作，身边大多会是同样感兴趣的人，这会让工作额外鼓舞人心。[3]</p><p>The other thing you do in the face of uncertainty is to make choices that are uncertainty-proof. The less sure you are about what to do, the more important it is to choose options that give you more options in the future. I call this “staying upwind.” If you’re unsure whether to major in math or economics, for example, choose math; math is upwind of economics in the sense that it will be easier to switch later from math to economics than from economics to math. </p><p>面对不确定性时，另一件要做的事是做 “抗不确定性” 的选择。你越不确定该做什么，就越要选那些能给未来留更多选项的事。我称之为 “保持在上风处”。比如，如果你不确定该选数学还是经济学专业，就选数学 —— 数学相对于经济学处于 “上风”，因为日后从数学转经济学比从经济学转数学更容易。</p><p>There’s one case, though, where it’s easy to say whether you should work on what interests you the most: if you want to do great work. This is not a sufficient condition for doing great work, but it is a necessary one. </p><p>不过，有一种情况，“是否该做自己最感兴趣的事” 的答案很明确：如果你想做出伟大的成就。这不是做出伟大成就的充分条件，但却是必要条件。</p><p>There’s a lot of selection bias in advice about whether to “follow your passion,” and this is the reason. Most such advice comes from people who are famously successful, and if you ask someone who’s famously successful how to do what they did, most will tell you that you have to work on what you’re most interested in. And this is in fact true. </p><p>关于 “是否该追随激情” 的建议，存在很强的选择性偏差，这就是原因所在。大多数这类建议来自那些非常成功的人，如果你问一个极其成功的人如何取得成就，大多数人会告诉你，必须做自己最感兴趣的事。而这其实是事实。</p><p>That doesn’t mean it’s the right advice for everyone. Not everyone can do great work, or wants to. But if you do want to, the complicated question of whether or not to work on what interests you the most becomes simple. The answer is yes. The root of great work is a sort of ambitious curiosity, and you can’t manufacture that.     </p><p>但这并不意味着这对每个人都是正确的建议。不是每个人都能或都想做出伟大的成就。但如果你想，那么 “是否该做自己最感兴趣的事” 这个复杂的问题就会变得简单 —— 答案是 “是”。伟大成就的根源，是一种充满野心的好奇心，而这种好奇心是无法刻意制造的。</p><p>Notes </p><p>[1] These examples show why it’s a mistake to assume that economic inequality must be evidence of some kind of brokenness or unfairness. It’s obvious that different people have different interests, and that some interests yield far more money than others, so how can it not be obvious that some people will end up much richer than others? In a world where some people like to write enterprise software and others like to make studio pottery, economic inequality is the natural outcome. </p><p>[1] 这些例子说明，认为 “经济不平等一定是某种缺陷或不公的证据” 是错误的。显然，不同的人有不同的兴趣，有些兴趣能带来多得多的钱，那么有些人比其他人富有得多，这不也是显而易见的吗？在一个有人喜欢写企业软件、有人喜欢做工作室陶艺的世界里，经济不平等是自然的结果。</p><p>[2] Difficulty choosing between interests is a different matter. That’s not always due to ignorance. It’s often intrinsically difficult. I still have trouble doing it. </p><p>[2] 在不同兴趣之间难以抉择则是另一回事。这并不总是因为信息不足，往往本质上就很难。我至今也很难做到。</p><p>[3] You can’t always take people at their word on this. Since it’s more prestigious to work on things you’re interested in than to be driven by money, people who are driven mainly by money will often claim to be more interested in their work than they actually are. One way to test such claims is by doing the following thought experiment: if their work didn’t pay well, would they take day jobs doing something else in order to do it in their spare time? Lots of mathematicians and scientists and engineers would. Historically lots have. But I don’t think as many investment bankers would.</p><p>[3] 在这一点上，你不能总是轻信别人的话。因为 “为兴趣工作” 比 “为钱工作” 更体面，所以那些主要为钱工作的人，往往会宣称自己对工作的兴趣比实际更深。检验这种说法的一个方法是做这样一个思想实验：如果他们的工作薪水不高，他们会做一份其他的日常工作，以便在业余时间继续做这份工作吗？很多数学家、科学家和工程师会这么做。历史上很多人都是如此。但我觉得，投资银行家里这么做的人不会太多。</p>]]></content>
    
    
    <categories>
      
      <category>文章翻译</category>
      
    </categories>
    
    
    <tags>
      
      <tag>PAUL GRAHAM</tag>
      
    </tags>
    
  </entry>
  
  
  
  <entry>
    <title>好的写作</title>
    <link href="/2025/07/14/good-wrting/"/>
    <url>/2025/07/14/good-wrting/</url>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="GOOD-WRITING"><a href="#GOOD-WRITING" class="headerlink" title="GOOD WRITING"></a>GOOD WRITING</h2><p>原文链接: <a href="https://paulgraham.com/goodwriting.html">https://paulgraham.com/goodwriting.html</a></p><h3 id="一、听起来好-与-观点正确"><a href="#一、听起来好-与-观点正确" class="headerlink" title="一、听起来好 与 观点正确"></a>一、听起来好 与 观点正确</h3><p>There are two senses in which writing can be good: it can sound good, and the ideas can be right. It can have nice, flowing sentences, and it can draw correct conclusions about important things. It might seem as if these two kinds of good would be unrelated, like the speed of a car and the color it’s painted. And yet I don’t think they are. I think writing that sounds good is more likely to be right. </p><p>好的写作可以体现在两个方面：一是<strong>听起来好</strong>，二是<strong>思想正确</strong>。它可以拥有流畅优美的句子，也可以对重要事物得出正确的结论。乍看之下，这两种“好”似乎毫无关联，就像汽车的速度和它的颜色一样互不相干。然而，我认为它们并非如此。<strong>我认为听起来好的文字，更可能是正确的。</strong></p><p>So here we have the most exciting kind of idea: one that seems both preposterous and true. Let’s examine it. How can this possibly be true? </p><p>于是，我们遇到了最令人兴奋的那种观点：一个看似荒谬却又真实的想法。让我们仔细审视它——这怎么可能成立？</p><p>I know it’s true from writing. You can’t simultaneously optimize two unrelated things; when you push one far enough, you always end up sacrificing the other. And yet no matter how hard I push, I never find myself having to choose between the sentence that sounds best and the one that expresses an idea best. If I did, it would be frivolous to care how sentences sound. But in practice it feels the opposite of frivolous. Fixing sentences that sound bad seems to help get the ideas right. [1] </p><p>我从写作中知道这是真的。你无法同时优化两件毫无关联的事情；当你把其中一件事推到极致时，总会牺牲另一件。然而，无论我如何努力，我从未发现自己必须在“听起来最好的句子”和“表达思想最准确的句子”之间做选择。如果真是这样，纠结句子的音律就显得轻浮了。但实践中，这种感觉恰恰相反——<strong>修改听起来别扭的句子，似乎能帮助理清思想</strong>[1]</p><p>By right I mean more than just true. Getting the ideas right means developing them well — drawing the conclusions that matter most, and exploring each one to the right level of detail. So getting the ideas right is not just a matter of saying true things, but saying the right true things. </p><p>这里的“正确”不仅仅是“真实”。思想正确意味着充分发展它们——得出最重要的结论，并以恰当的细节层次展开。因此，思想正确不只是说真话，而是说出<strong>该说的真话</strong>。</p><p>How could trying to make sentences sound good help you do that? The clue to the answer is something I noticed 30 years ago when I was doing the layout for my first book. Sometimes when you’re laying out text you have bad luck. For example, you get a section that runs one line longer than the page. I don’t know what ordinary typesetters do in this situation, but what I did was rewrite the section to make it a line shorter. You’d expect such an arbitrary constraint to make the writing worse. But I found, to my surprise, that it never did. I always ended up with something I liked better. </p><p>为什么追求句子的音律能帮助做到这一点？答案的线索来自30年前我为第一本书排版时的发现。排版时偶尔会遇到厄运：比如某个章节比页面多出一行。我不知道普通排版师会怎么做，但我的解决方法是重写那段，让它缩短一行。这种武断的限制本该让文字变得更糟，但出乎意料的是，结果总是更好。</p><h3 id="二、文章的重力定律"><a href="#二、文章的重力定律" class="headerlink" title="二、文章的重力定律"></a>二、文章的重力定律</h3><p>I don’t think this was because my writing was especially careless. I think if you pointed to a random paragraph in anything written by anyone and told them to make it slightly shorter (or longer), they’d probably be able to come up with something better.</p><p>The best analogy for this phenomenon is when you shake a bin full of different objects. The shakes are arbitrary motions. Or more precisely, they’re not calculated to make any two specific objects fit more closely together. And yet repeated shaking inevitably makes the objects discover brilliantly clever ways of packing themselves. Gravity won’t let them become less tightly packed, so any change has to be a change for the better. [2] </p><p>我不认为这是因为我的写作特别粗心。我相信，如果随机指一段别人的文字并要求稍作删减（或扩充），他们很可能改得更好。</p><p>这种现象的最佳类比是摇晃装满杂物的箱子。摇晃是随机的动作，或者说，它并非为了让某两件物品更紧密贴合。然而，反复摇晃最终会让物品找到绝妙的排列方式。重力不允许它们松散，所以任何变化都只能是优化[2]。</p><p>So it is with writing. If you have to rewrite an awkward passage, you’ll never do it in a way that makes it less true. You couldn’t bear it, any more than gravity could bear things floating upward. So any change in the ideas has to be a change for the better. </p><p>写作也是如此。如果你必须重写一段拗口的文字，绝不会以牺牲真实性为代价。你无法忍受这种妥协，就像重力无法接受物体向上飘浮。因此，思想上的任何调整都只能是改进。</p><p>It’s obvious once you think about it. Writing that sounds good is more likely to be right for the same reason that a well-shaken bin is more likely to be tightly packed. But there’s something else going on as well. Sounding good isn’t just a random external force that leaves the ideas in an essay better off. It actually helps you to get them right. </p><p>细想之下，这显而易见。<strong>听起来好的文字更可能是正确的，就像摇晃充分的箱子更可能紧凑</strong>。但还有另一层原因：音律并非只是随机外力，被动地优化文章思想——它<strong>主动</strong>帮助你理清思路。</p><h3 id="三、好的文章是易读的"><a href="#三、好的文章是易读的" class="headerlink" title="三、好的文章是易读的"></a>三、好的文章是易读的</h3><p>The reason is that it makes the essay easier to read. It’s less work to read writing that flows well. How does that help the writer? Because the writer is the first reader. When I’m working on an essay, I spend far more time reading than writing. I’ll reread some parts 50 or 100 times, replaying the thoughts in them and asking myself, like someone sanding a piece of wood, does anything catch? Does anything feel wrong? And the easier the essay is to read, the easier it is to notice if something catches. </p><p>因为音律让文章更易读。流畅的文字减轻了阅读负担。这对作者有何帮助？因为<strong>作者是第一位读者</strong>。写文章时，我花在阅读上的时间远多于写作。某些段落我会重读50甚至100遍，反复咀嚼其中的思想，像打磨木头一样自问：是否有阻滞？是否有不对劲？文章越易读，越容易发现这些问题。</p><p>So yes, the two senses of good writing are connected in at least two ways. Trying to make writing sound good makes you fix mistakes unconsciously, and also helps you fix them consciously; it shakes the bin of ideas, and also makes mistakes easier to see. But now that we’ve dissolved one layer of preposterousness, I can’t resist adding another. Does sounding good do more than just help you get the ideas right? Is writing that sounds good inherently more likely to be right? Crazy as it may seem, I think that’s true too. </p><p>因此，好的写作的两个维度至少通过两种方式关联：追求音律能让你无意识地修正错误，也有助于有意识地改进；它既“摇晃思想的箱子”，又让错误更易察觉。但既然我们已经揭开了一层荒谬，我不妨再添一层：**音律的作用是否不止于辅助思想正确？听起来好的文字是否天生更可能是正确的？**尽管看似疯狂，我认为确实如此。</p><p>Obviously there’s a connection at the level of individual words. There are lots of words in English that sound like what they mean, often in wonderfully subtle ways. Glitter. Round. Scrape. Prim. Cavalcade. But the sound of good writing depends even more on the way you put words together, and there’s a connection at that level too. </p><p>显然，单个词汇层面就存在关联。英语中许多词的发音暗示其含义，且方式精妙至极。比如“glitter”（闪烁）、“round”（圆润）、“scrape”（刮擦）、“prim”（刻板）、“cavalcade”（队列）。但好文章的音律更多取决于词语组合方式，而这一层面同样存在联系。</p><h3 id="四、好的节奏产生好的文章"><a href="#四、好的节奏产生好的文章" class="headerlink" title="四、好的节奏产生好的文章"></a>四、好的节奏产生好的文章</h3><p>When writing sounds good, it’s mostly because it has good rhythm. But the rhythm of good writing is not the rhythm of music, or the meter of verse. It’s not so regular. If it were, it wouldn’t be good, because the rhythm of good writing has to match the ideas in it, and ideas have all kinds of different shapes. Sometimes they’re simple and you just state them. But other times they’re more subtle, and you need longer, more complicated sentences to tease out all the implications. </p><p>文章听起来好，主要因其节奏得当。但优秀写作的节奏并非音乐的韵律或诗歌的格律，它没那么规整。如果规整，反而不好，因为好文章的节奏必须匹配其中的思想，而思想的形态千差万别。有时它们简单直接，只需陈述；有时则微妙复杂，需要更长的句子梳理全部内涵。</p><p>An essay is a cleaned up train of thought, in the same way dialogue is cleaned up conversation, and a train of thought has a natural rhythm. So when an essay sounds good, it’s not merely because it has a pleasing rhythm, but because it has its natural one. Which means you can use getting the rhythm right as a heuristic for getting the ideas right. And not just in principle: good writers do both simultaneously as a matter of course. Often I don’t even distinguish between the two problems. I just think Ugh, this doesn’t sound right; what do I mean to say here? [3] </p><p>文章是整理过的思路轨迹，如同对白是加工过的对话，而思路自有其自然节奏。因此，文章音律好不仅因为节奏悦耳，更因为节奏<strong>自然</strong>。这意味着你可以把节奏正确作为思想正确的启发式标准。而且不仅是理论上的——优秀作者在实践中会同步解决这两个问题。我常甚至不区分它们，只是觉得“呃，这里听起来不对——我到底想说什么？”[3]</p><p>The sound of writing turns out to be more like the shape of a plane than the color of a car. If it looks good, as Kelly Johnson used to say, it will fly well. </p><p>最终，文字的音律更像飞机的气动外形，而非汽车的颜色。正如凯利·约翰逊所言：“如果它看起来对，飞起来就不会差。”</p><p>This is only true of writing that’s used to develop ideas, though. It doesn’t apply when you have ideas in some other way and then write about them afterward — for example, if you build something, or conduct an experiment, and then write a paper about it. In such cases the ideas often live more in the work than the writing, so the writing can be bad even though the ideas are good. The writing in textbooks and popular surveys can be bad for the same reason: the author isn’t developing the ideas, merely describing other people’s. It’s only when you’re writing to develop ideas that there’s such a close connection between the two senses of doing it well. </p><p>不过，这仅适用于<strong>用于发展思想的写作</strong>。如果你通过其他方式（比如建造某物或做实验）获得思想后再写成文章，音律与思想的关联就会减弱。这类情况下，思想更多存在于工作中而非文字里，因此文章可能糟糕但思想正确。教科书和科普读物的文字不佳也源于此——作者并非发展思想，只是转述他人。<strong>唯有当你通过写作探索思想时，两种“好”才会紧密相连。</strong></p><h3 id="内部一致与真实的重合"><a href="#内部一致与真实的重合" class="headerlink" title="内部一致与真实的重合"></a>内部一致与真实的重合</h3><p>Ok, many people will be thinking, this seems plausible so far, but what about liars? Is it not notoriously possible for a smooth-tongued liar to write something beautiful that’s completely false? </p><p>读到此处，许多人会想：目前为止还算合理，但骗子呢？巧舌如簧的骗子难道不能写出优美而完全虚假的文字吗？</p><p>It is, of course. But not without method acting. The way to write something beautiful and false is to begin by making yourself almost believe it. So just like someone writing something beautiful and true, you’re presenting a perfectly-formed train of thought. The difference is the point where it attaches to the world. You’re saying something that would be true if certain false premises were. If for some bizarre reason the number of jobs in a country were fixed, then immigrants really would be taking our jobs. </p><p>当然可以。但前提是<strong>方法派演技</strong>。写出美丽谎言的方法，是先让自己几乎相信它。因此，与写出美丽真理的人一样，你呈现的是一段完美成型的思路。区别在于它和现实的连接点——你描述的是一种在虚假前提下成立的真实。比如，如果某国工作岗位数量固定（尽管这荒诞），那么移民确实会“抢走我们的工作”。</p><p>So it’s not quite right to say that better sounding writing is more likely to be true. Better sounding writing is more likely to be internally consistent. If the writer is honest, internal consistency and truth converge. But while we can’t safely conclude that beautiful writing is true, it’s usually safe to conclude the converse: something that seems clumsily written will usually have gotten the ideas wrong too. </p><p>因此，“音律好的文字更可能真实”并不完全准确。更准确的说法是：<strong>音律好的文字更可能内部一致</strong>。如果作者诚实，内部一致与真实自会重合。</p><p>Indeed, the two senses of good writing are more like two ends of the same thing. The connection between them is not a rigid one; the goodness of good writing is not a rod but a rope, with multiple overlapping connections running through it. But it’s hard to move one end without moving the other. It’s hard to be right without sounding right.</p><p>虽然我们不能断言优美文字必然真实，但通常可以安全地反推：<strong>笨拙的文字往往思想也有问题</strong>。</p><p>事实上，好的写作的两个维度更像是同一事物的两端。它们的联系并非 rigid（僵硬的杆），而是 rope（柔韧的绳），内含多重交织的关联。但你很难只移动一端而不牵动另一端。<strong>很难正确而不听起来正确。</strong></p><p>Notes </p><p>[1] The closest thing to an exception is when you have to go back and insert a new point into the middle of something you’ve written. This often messes up the flow, sometimes in ways you can never quite repair. But I think the ultimate source of this problem is that ideas are tree-shaped and essays are linear. You inevitably run into difficulties when you try to cram the former into the latter. Frankly it’s surprising how much you can get away with. But even so you sometimes have to resort to an endnote. </p><p>[1] 最接近例外的情况是：当你需要在已写好的内容中插入新观点时，常会破坏行文流畅性，有时甚至无法完全修复。我认为根本原因在于思想是树状结构，而文章是线性的。将前者塞进后者时难免遇到困难。说实话，能勉强做到的程度已令人惊讶。但即便如此，有时你仍不得不借助尾注。</p><p>[2] Obviously if you shake the bin hard enough the objects in it can become less tightly packed. And similarly, if you imposed some huge external constraint on your writing, like using alternating one and two syllable words, the ideas would start to suffer. </p><p>[2] 显然，如果摇晃过于剧烈，箱内物品反而会变松散。同理，如果对写作施加某些极端限制（比如交替使用单双音节词），思想就会受损。</p><p>[3] Bizarrely enough, this happened in the writing of this very paragraph. An earlier version shared several phrases in common with the preceding paragraph, and the repetition bugged me each time I reread it. When I got annoyed enough to fix it, I discovered that the repetition reflected a problem in the underlying ideas, and I fixed both simultaneously.</p><p>[3] 诡异的是，这段文字的写作过程就印证了这一点。初稿与前一段有多个重复短语，每次重读都让我不适。当我终于忍无可忍去修改时，发现重复反映了底层思想的问题，于是同步修正了两者。</p>]]></content>
    
    
    <categories>
      
      <category>文章翻译</category>
      
    </categories>
    
    
    <tags>
      
      <tag>PAUL GRAHAM</tag>
      
    </tags>
    
  </entry>
  
  
  
  
</search>
