<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<search>
  
  
  
  <entry>
    <title>怎样正确的区分执着与固执</title>
    <link href="/2025/07/23/the-right-kind-of-stubborn/"/>
    <url>/2025/07/23/the-right-kind-of-stubborn/</url>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="THE-RIGHT-KIND-OF-STUBBORN"><a href="#THE-RIGHT-KIND-OF-STUBBORN" class="headerlink" title="THE RIGHT KIND OF STUBBORN"></a>THE RIGHT KIND OF STUBBORN</h2><p>原文链接: <a href="https://paulgraham.com/persistence.html">https://paulgraham.com/persistence.html</a></p><p>July 2024</p><p>Successful people tend to be persistent. New ideas often don’t work at first, but they’re not deterred. They keep trying and eventually find something that does. </p><p>成功人士往往具备执着的品质。新想法起初往往行不通，但他们不会因此却步，而是不断尝试，最终找到有效的方法。</p><p>Mere obstinacy, on the other hand, is a recipe for failure. Obstinate people are so annoying. They won’t listen. They beat their heads against a wall and get nowhere. </p><p>另一方面，单纯的固执则注定失败。固执的人很讨厌，他们不听劝，一味地撞南墙，却毫无进展。</p><p>But is there any real difference between these two cases? Are persistent and obstinate people actually behaving differently? Or are they doing the same thing, and we just label them later as persistent or obstinate depending on whether they turned out to be right or not? </p><p>但这两种情况真的有区别吗？执着的人和固执的人行为上是否真的不同？还是说他们做着同样的事，只是我们事后根据他们最终是否正确，才分别贴上 “执着” 或 “固执” 的标签？</p><p>If that’s the only difference then there’s nothing to be learned from the distinction. Telling someone to be persistent rather than obstinate would just be telling them to be right rather than wrong, and they already know that. Whereas if persistence and obstinacy are actually different kinds of behavior, it would be worthwhile to tease them apart. [1] </p><p>如果这是唯一的区别，那么这种区分就毫无借鉴意义。告诉别人要执着而非固执，无异于告诉他们要正确而非错误，而这一点他们早就知道了。然而，若执着与固执确实是两种不同的行为，那我们就有必要将它们区分开来。[1]</p><p>I’ve talked to a lot of determined people, and it seems to me that they’re different kinds of behavior. I’ve often walked away from a conversation thinking either “Wow, that guy is determined” or “Damn, that guy is stubborn,” and I don’t think I’m just talking about whether they seemed right or not. That’s part of it, but not all of it. </p><p>我和很多意志坚定的人聊过，在我看来，这两种行为确实不同。我常常在与人交谈后，要么想 “哇，这个人真执着”，要么想 “该死，这个人真固执”，而且我认为这不仅仅是因为他们看起来正确与否。这是一部分原因，但并非全部。</p><p>There’s something annoying about the obstinate that’s not simply due to being mistaken. They won’t listen. And that’s not true of all determined people. I can’t think of anyone more determined than the Collison brothers, and when you point out a problem to them, they not only listen, but listen with an almost predatory intensity. Is there a hole in the bottom of their boat? Probably not, but if there is, they want to know about it. </p><p>固执的人身上有种令人讨厌的特质，这不仅仅是因为他们犯错了。他们不听劝。但并非所有意志坚定的人都是如此。我想不出比科利森兄弟更执着的人了，当你向他们指出问题时，他们不仅会听，而且会带着近乎掠夺性的专注去听。他们的船底有洞吗？可能没有，但如果真有，他们一定想知道。</p><p>It’s the same with most successful people. They’re never more engaged than when you disagree with them. Whereas the obstinate don’t want to hear you. When you point out problems, their eyes glaze over, and their replies sound like ideologues talking about matters of doctrine. [2] </p><p>大多数成功人士都是如此。当你与他们意见相左时，他们会格外投入。而固执的人却不想听你说。当你指出问题时，他们眼神涣散，回答听起来就像理论家在谈论教条。[2]</p><p>The reason the persistent and the obstinate seem similar is that they’re both hard to stop. But they’re hard to stop in different senses. The persistent are like boats whose engines can’t be throttled back. The obstinate are like boats whose rudders can’t be turned. [3] </p><p>执着者和固执者看似相似，是因为他们都难以被阻止。但他们的 “难以被阻止” 意义不同。执着者就像引擎无法减速的船，而固执者就像舵无法转动的船。[3]</p><p>In the degenerate case they’re indistinguishable: when there’s only one way to solve a problem, your only choice is whether to give up or not, and persistence and obstinacy both say no. This is presumably why the two are so often conflated in popular culture. It assumes simple problems. But as problems get more complicated, we can see the difference between them. The persistent are much more attached to points high in the decision tree than to minor ones lower down, while the obstinate spray “don’t give up” indiscriminately over the whole tree. </p><p>在退化的情况下，两者难以区分：当解决问题只有一种方法时，你唯一的选择就是放弃或不放弃，而执着和固执都意味着不放弃。这大概就是为什么这两种特质在流行文化中常常被混为一谈。流行文化假设的是简单的问题。但随着问题变得越来越复杂，我们就能看出两者的区别了。执着的人更执着于决策树高层的要点，而对低层的次要要点则不那么在意，而固执的人则会不加区分地 “不放弃” 整个决策树。</p><p>The persistent are attached to the goal. The obstinate are attached to their ideas about how to reach it. </p><p>执着的人执着于目标，而固执的人执着于自己达成目标的想法。</p><p>Worse still, that means they’ll tend to be attached to their first ideas about how to solve a problem, even though these are the least informed by the experience of working on it. So the obstinate aren’t merely attached to details, but disproportionately likely to be attached to wrong ones.  </p><p>更糟糕的是，这意味着他们往往会执着于自己解决问题的最初想法，尽管这些想法是最缺乏实践经验支撑的。因此，固执的人不仅执着于细节，而且极有可能执着于错误的细节。</p><p>Why are they like this? Why are the obstinate obstinate? One possibility is that they’re overwhelmed. They’re not very capable. They take on a hard problem. They’re immediately in over their head. So they grab onto ideas the way someone on the deck of a rolling ship might grab onto the nearest handhold. </p><p>为什么他们会这样？固执的人为什么会固执？一种可能是他们不堪重负。他们能力不足，却承担了一个艰难的任务，很快就力不从心了。于是他们抓住一些想法不放，就像在摇晃的船上，有人会抓住最近的扶手一样。</p><p>That was my initial theory, but on examination it doesn’t hold up. If being obstinate were simply a consequence of being in over one’s head, you could make persistent people become obstinate by making them solve harder problems. But that’s not what happens. If you handed the Collisons an extremely hard problem to solve, they wouldn’t become obstinate. If anything they’d become less obstinate. They’d know they had to be open to anything. </p><p>这是我最初的想法，但仔细想想，这并不成立。如果固执仅仅是因为力不从心，那么通过让执着的人去解决更难的问题，就能让他们变得固执。但事实并非如此。如果你让科利森兄弟去解决一个极难的问题，他们不会变得固执。如果说有什么不同的话，他们会变得不那么固执。他们知道自己必须对一切持开放态度。</p><p>Similarly, if obstinacy were caused by the situation, the obstinate would stop being obstinate when solving easier problems. But they don’t. And if obstinacy isn’t caused by the situation, it must come from within. It must be a feature of one’s personality. </p><p>同样，如果固执是由环境造成的，那么当固执的人去解决更容易的问题时，他们就不会再固执了。但他们并没有。如果固执不是由环境造成的，那它一定源于内在，一定是个人性格的一种特征。</p><p>Obstinacy is a reflexive resistance to changing one’s ideas. This is not identical with stupidity, but they’re closely related. A reflexive resistance to changing one’s ideas becomes a sort of induced stupidity as contrary evidence mounts. And obstinacy is a form of not giving up that’s easily practiced by the stupid. You don’t have to consider complicated tradeoffs; you just dig in your heels. It even works, up to a point. </p><p>固执是一种对改变想法的本能抗拒。这与愚蠢并不完全相同，但两者密切相关。随着反对证据的增多，这种对改变想法的本能抗拒会演变成一种诱发的愚蠢。固执是一种不放弃的表现，愚蠢的人很容易做到这一点。你不必考虑复杂的权衡，只需固执己见。在某种程度上，这甚至是有效的。</p><p>The fact that obstinacy works for simple problems is an important clue. Persistence and obstinacy aren’t opposites. The relationship between them is more like the relationship between the two kinds of respiration we can do: aerobic respiration, and the anaerobic respiration we inherited from our most distant ancestors. Anaerobic respiration is a more primitive process, but it has its uses. When you leap suddenly away from a threat, that’s what you’re using. </p><p>固执在简单问题上能奏效，这是一个重要的线索。执着和固执并非对立面。它们之间的关系更像是我们能进行的两种呼吸方式：有氧呼吸和我们从远古祖先那里继承的无氧呼吸。无氧呼吸是一种更原始的过程，但它有其用途。当你突然跳起来躲避威胁时，你用的就是无氧呼吸。</p><p>The optimal amount of obstinacy is not zero. It can be good if your initial reaction to a setback is an unthinking “I won’t give up,” because this helps prevent panic. But unthinking only gets you so far. The further someone is toward the obstinate end of the continuum, the less likely they are to succeed in solving hard problems. [4]  </p><p>固执的最佳量并非零。如果面对挫折，你的第一反应是不假思索地 “我不会放弃”，这可能是好事，因为这有助于防止恐慌。但不假思索的作用有限。一个人越是倾向于固执，就越不可能成功解决难题。[4]</p><p>Obstinacy is a simple thing. Animals have it. But persistence turns out to have a fairly complicated internal structure. </p><p>固执是一种简单的东西，动物也有。但事实证明，执着有着相当复杂的内在结构。</p><p>One thing that distinguishes the persistent is their energy. At the risk of putting too much weight on words, they persist rather than merely resisting. They keep trying things. Which means the persistent must also be imaginative. To keep trying things, you have to keep thinking of things to try. Energy and imagination make a wonderful combination. Each gets the best out of the other. </p><p>执着者的一个特点是他们的精力。也许过分强调词语的含义不太好，但他们是 “坚持下去”，而不仅仅是 “抵抗”。他们不断尝试。这意味着执着的人还必须富有想象力。要不断尝试，你就必须不断想出新的点子。</p><p>Energy creates demand for the ideas produced by imagination, which thus produces more, and imagination gives energy somewhere to go. [5] </p><p>精力和想象力是一对绝妙的组合，彼此能让对方发挥出最佳水平。精力为想象力产生的想法创造需求，从而促使想象力产生更多想法，而想象力则为精力提供了方向。[5]</p><p>Merely having energy and imagination is quite rare. But to solve hard problems you need three more qualities: resilience, good judgement, and a focus on some kind of goal. </p><p>仅仅拥有精力和想象力是相当罕见的。但要解决难题，你还需要另外三种品质：韧性、良好的判断力和对某种目标的专注。</p><p>Resilience means not having one’s morale destroyed by setbacks. Setbacks are inevitable once problems reach a certain size, so if you can’t bounce back from them, you can only do good work on a small scale. But resilience is not the same as obstinacy. Resilience means setbacks can’t change your morale, not that they can’t change your mind. </p><p>韧性意味着不会因挫折而士气低落。一旦问题达到一定规模，挫折就不可避免，所以如果你不能从挫折中恢复过来，你就只能在小规模的事情上做出成绩。但韧性与固执不同。韧性意味着挫折不能改变你的士气，而不是说挫折不能改变你的想法。</p><p>Indeed, persistence often requires that one change one’s mind. That’s where good judgement comes in. The persistent are quite rational. They focus on expected value. It’s this, not recklessness, that lets them work on things that are unlikely to succeed. </p><p>事实上，执着往往需要人改变想法。这就需要良好的判断力了。执着的人非常理性，他们关注预期价值。正是这一点，而非鲁莽，让他们能够从事那些成功可能性不大的事情。</p><p>There is one point at which the persistent are often irrational though: at the very top of the decision tree. When they choose between two problems of roughly equal expected value, the choice usually comes down to personal preference. Indeed, they’ll often classify projects into deliberately wide bands of expected value in order to ensure that the one they want to work on still qualifies. </p><p>不过，在决策树的顶端，执着的人往往会不理性：当他们在两个预期价值大致相等的问题之间做出选择时，选择通常取决于个人偏好。事实上，他们往往会将项目故意划分为广泛的预期价值区间，以确保他们想做的项目仍然符合条件。</p><p>Empirically this doesn’t seem to be a problem. It’s ok to be irrational near the top of the decision tree. One reason is that we humans will work harder on a problem we love. But there’s another more subtle factor involved as well: our preferences among problems aren’t random. When we love a problem that other people don’t, it’s often because we’ve unconsciously noticed that it’s more important than they realize. </p><p>从经验来看，这似乎不是问题。在决策树的顶端不理性是可以接受的。一个原因是，我们人类会更努力地去解决自己喜欢的问题。但还有一个更微妙的因素：我们对那些别人不喜欢的问题的偏好，往往是因为我们下意识地注意到这些问题比别人意识到的更重要。</p><p>Which leads to our fifth quality: there needs to be some overall goal. If you’re like me you began, as a kid, merely with the desire to do something great. In theory that should be the most powerful motivator of all, since it includes everything that could possibly be done. But in practice it’s not much use, precisely because it includes too much. It doesn’t tell you what to do at this moment. </p><p>这就引出了第五种品质：需要有一个总体目标。如果你像我一样，小时候只是渴望做一些伟大的事情。理论上，这应该是最强大的动力，因为它包含了所有可能要做的事情。但实际上，它没什么用，正是因为它包含的太多了，它无法告诉你此刻该做什么。</p><p>So in practice your energy and imagination and resilience and good judgement have to be directed toward some fairly specific goal. Not too specific, or you might miss a great discovery adjacent to what you’re searching for, but not too general, or it won’t work to motivate you. [6] </p><p>所以，在实践中，你的精力、想象力、韧性和良好的判断力必须指向某个相当具体的目标。不能太具体，否则你可能会错过与你正在寻找的东西相关的重大发现，但也不能太笼统，否则就无法激励你。[6]</p><p>When you look at the internal structure of persistence, it doesn’t resemble obstinacy at all. It’s so much more complex. Five distinct qualities — energy, imagination, resilience, good judgement, and focus on a goal — combine to produce a phenomenon that seems a bit like obstinacy in the sense that it causes you not to give up. But the way you don’t give up is completely different. Instead of merely resisting change, you’re driven toward a goal by energy and resilience, through paths discovered by imagination and optimized by judgement. You’ll give way on any point low down in the decision tree, if its expected value drops sufficiently, but energy and resilience keep pushing you toward whatever you chose higher up. </p><p>当你审视执着的内在结构时，会发现它与固执一点也不像，它要复杂得多。五种不同的品质 —— 精力、想象力、韧性、良好的判断力和对目标的专注 —— 结合在一起，产生了一种看似有点像固执的现象，因为它让你不放弃。但你不放弃的方式完全不同。你不是仅仅抗拒改变，而是在精力和韧性的驱动下朝着目标前进，通过想象力发现路径，并通过判断力优化路径。如果决策树下层的某个要点的预期价值大幅下降，你会放弃它，但精力和韧性会推动你朝着你在决策树上层选择的目标前进。</p><p>Considering what it’s made of, it’s not surprising that the right kind of stubbornness is so much rarer than the wrong kind, or that it gets so much better results. Anyone can do obstinacy. Indeed, kids and drunks and fools are best at it. Whereas very few people have enough of all five of the qualities that produce the right kind of stubbornness, but when they do the results are magical.    </p><p>考虑到执着的构成，难怪正确的固执比错误的固执罕见得多，也难怪它能取得好得多的结果。任何人都可以固执，事实上，孩子、醉汉和傻瓜最擅长这个。而拥有产生正确固执的所有五种品质的人非常少，但当他们拥有这些品质时，结果是不可思议的。</p><p>Notes </p><p>[1] I’m going to use “persistent” for the good kind of stubborn and “obstinate” for the bad kind, but I can’t claim I’m simply following current usage. Conventional opinion barely distinguishes between good and bad kinds of stubbornness, and usage is correspondingly promiscuous. I could have invented a new word for the good kind, but it seemed better just to stretch “persistent.” </p><p>[1] 我将用 “执着（persistent）” 指代那种有益的固执，用 “固执（obstinate）” 指代有害的固执，但我并非完全遵循现有用法。传统观念几乎不区分固执的好坏，因此这两个词的使用也相应地混乱。我本可以为有益的固执创造一个新词，但似乎还是延伸 “执着” 的含义更好。</p><p>[2] There are some domains where one can succeed by being obstinate. Some political leaders have been notorious for it. But it won’t work in situations where you have to pass external tests. And indeed the political leaders who are famous for being obstinate are famous for getting power, not for using it well. </p><p>[2] 在某些领域，固执也能成功。有些政治领袖就因固执而出名。但在需要通过外部检验的情况下，固执行不通。事实上，那些因固执而闻名的政治领袖，出名的是他们获取权力的方式，而非运用权力的能力。</p><p>[3] There will be some resistance to turning the rudder of a persistent person, because there’s some cost to changing direction. </p><p>[3] 要改变执着者的方向（转动他们的 “舵”），多少会遇到一些阻力，因为改变方向总要付出代价。</p><p>[4] The obstinate do sometimes succeed in solving hard problems. One way is through luck: like the stopped clock that’s right twice a day, they seize onto some arbitrary idea, and it turns out to be right. Another is when their obstinacy cancels out some other form of error. For example, if a leader has overcautious subordinates, their estimates of the probability of success will always be off in the same direction. So if he mindlessly says “push ahead regardless” in every borderline case, he’ll usually turn out to be right. </p><p>[4] 固执的人有时也能解决难题。一种情况是靠运气：就像停摆的时钟每天也能准两次，他们抓住某个随意的想法，结果碰巧是对的。另一种情况是，他们的固执抵消了其他形式的错误。例如，若领导者的下属过于谨慎，他们对成功概率的估计总会偏向同一个错误方向。这时，若领导者在所有边缘案例中都盲目说 “无论如何都要推进”，往往最终会被证明是对的。</p><p>[5] If you stop there, at just energy and imagination, you get the conventional caricature of an artist or poet. </p><p>[5] 若仅停留在精力和想象力这两点，就会陷入人们对艺术家或诗人的固有刻板印象中。</p><p>[6] Start by erring on the small side. If you’re inexperienced you’ll inevitably err on one side or the other, and if you err on the side of making the goal too broad, you won’t get anywhere. Whereas if you err on the small side you’ll at least be moving forward. Then, once you’re moving, you expand the goal.</p><p>[6] 开始时，目标宁小勿大。缺乏经验时，你难免会在目标设定上有所偏差：若目标定得太宽泛，你会一事无成；若目标定得小一点，至少能向前推进。一旦开始行动，再逐步扩大目标范围。</p>]]></content>
    
    
    <categories>
      
      <category>文章翻译</category>
      
    </categories>
    
    
    <tags>
      
      <tag>PAUL GRAHAM</tag>
      
    </tags>
    
  </entry>
  
  
  
  <entry>
    <title>阅读的必要</title>
    <link href="/2025/07/23/the-need-to-read/"/>
    <url>/2025/07/23/the-need-to-read/</url>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="THE-NEED-TO-READ"><a href="#THE-NEED-TO-READ" class="headerlink" title="THE NEED TO READ"></a>THE NEED TO READ</h2><p>原文链接: <a href="https://paulgraham.com/read.html">https://paulgraham.com/read.html</a></p><p>November 2022</p><p>In the science fiction books I read as a kid, reading had often been replaced by some more efficient way of acquiring knowledge. Mysterious “tapes” would load it into one’s brain like a program being loaded into a computer. </p><p>在我小时候读的科幻小说里，阅读往往已被某种更高效的知识获取方式取代。神秘的 “磁带” 能将知识载入大脑，就像给电脑加载程序一样。</p><p>That sort of thing is unlikely to happen anytime soon. Not just because it would be hard to build a replacement for reading, but because even if one existed, it would be insufficient. Reading about x doesn’t just teach you about x; it also teaches you how to write. [1] </p><p>这类事情短期内不太可能发生。不仅因为构建阅读的替代品难度极大，更因为即便存在这样的替代品，它也无法满足需求。阅读关于某事物的内容，不仅能让你了解该事物，还能教会你如何写作。[1]</p><p>Would that matter? If we replaced reading, would anyone need to be good at writing? </p><p>这很重要吗？如果我们找到了取代阅读的方法，还需要有人擅长写作吗？</p><p>The reason it would matter is that writing is not just a way to convey ideas, but also a way to have them. </p><p>重要的原因在于，写作不仅是传达思想的方式，更是产生思想的方式。</p><p>A good writer doesn’t just think, and then write down what he thought, as a sort of transcript. A good writer will almost always discover new things in the process of writing. And there is, as far as I know, no substitute for this kind of discovery. Talking about your ideas with other people is a good way to develop them. But even after doing this, you’ll find you still discover new things when you sit down to write. There is a kind of thinking that can only be done by writing. </p><p>优秀的作家并非先思考，再把想法像抄本一样写下来。优秀的作家几乎总会在写作过程中发现新东西。而且据我所知，这种发现是无可替代的。与他人探讨想法是完善思想的好方法，但即便如此，当你坐下来写作时，仍会发现新的东西。有一种思考，只能通过写作完成。</p><p>There are of course kinds of thinking that can be done without writing. If you don’t need to go too deeply into a problem, you can solve it without writing. If you’re thinking about how two pieces of machinery should fit together, writing about it probably won’t help much. And when a problem can be described formally, you can sometimes solve it in your head. But if you need to solve a complicated, ill-defined problem, it will almost always help to write about it. Which in turn means that someone who’s not good at writing will almost always be at a disadvantage in solving such problems. </p><p>当然，有些思考无需写作也能进行。如果不需要深入钻研某个问题，你可以不写就能解决它。比如思考两台机器如何组装时，写作可能没多大帮助。当一个问题可以被形式化描述时，有时也能在脑中解决。但如果要解决一个复杂且定义模糊的问题，写作几乎总能起到帮助。这意味着，不擅长写作的人在解决这类问题时，几乎总会处于劣势。</p><p>You can’t think well without writing well, and you can’t write well without reading well. And I mean that last “well” in both senses. You have to be good at reading, and read good things. [2] </p><p>写不好，就无法思考透彻；读不好，就写不好。这里的 “好” 有两层含义：你既要擅长阅读，也要读优秀的作品。[2]</p><p>People who just want information may find other ways to get it. But people who want to have ideas can’t afford to.      </p><p>只想获取信息的人或许能找到其他途径。但想要产生思想的人，却不能放弃阅读。</p><p>Notes </p><p>[1] Audiobooks can give you examples of good writing, but having them read to you doesn’t teach you as much about writing as reading them yourself. </p><p>[1] 有声书能为你提供优秀写作的范例，但听别人读，不如自己读更能教会你写作。</p><p>[2] By “good at reading” I don’t mean good at the mechanics of reading. You don’t have to be good at extracting words from the page so much as extracting meaning from the words.</p><p>[2] 我说的 “擅长阅读”，并非指阅读的技巧。你不必擅长从书页中识别文字，而应擅长从文字中提炼意义。</p>]]></content>
    
    
    <categories>
      
      <category>文章翻译</category>
      
    </categories>
    
    
    <tags>
      
      <tag>PAUL GRAHAM</tag>
      
    </tags>
    
  </entry>
  
  
  
  <entry>
    <title>散文领域的格局</title>
    <link href="/2025/07/22/the-shape-of-the-essay-field/"/>
    <url>/2025/07/22/the-shape-of-the-essay-field/</url>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="THE-SHAPE-OF-THE-ESSAY-FIELD"><a href="#THE-SHAPE-OF-THE-ESSAY-FIELD" class="headerlink" title="THE SHAPE OF THE ESSAY FIELD"></a>THE SHAPE OF THE ESSAY FIELD</h2><p>原文链接: <a href="https://paulgraham.com/field.html">https://paulgraham.com/field.html</a></p><p>June 2025</p><p>An essay has to tell people something they don’t already know. But there are three different reasons people might not know something, and they yield three very different kinds of essays. </p><p>一篇散文必须告诉人们一些他们不知道的东西。但人们之所以不知道某件事，原因有三，而这三种原因催生出了三种截然不同的散文。</p><p>One reason people won’t know something is if it’s not important to know. That doesn’t mean it will make a bad essay. For example, you might write a good essay about a particular model of car. Readers would learn something from it. It would add to their picture of the world. For a handful of readers it might even spur some kind of epiphany. But unless this is a very unusual car it’s not critical for everyone to know about it. [1] </p><p>第一种原因是，这件事并不重要，不值得了解。但这并不意味着写这类内容就成不了好散文。比如，你可以写一篇关于某款特定车型的好散文。读者能从中学到东西，这会丰富他们对世界的认知。对少数读者来说，它甚至可能引发某种顿悟。但除非这是一款极不寻常的车，否则并非所有人都非了解它不可。[1]</p><p>If something isn’t important to know, there’s no answer to the question of why people don’t know it. Not knowing random facts is the default. But if you’re going to write about things that are important to know, you have to ask why your readers don’t already know them. Is it because they’re smart but inexperienced, or because they’re obtuse? </p><p>如果某件事不重要，那 “人们为什么不知道它” 这个问题就没有答案。不了解随机的琐事，本就是常态。但如果你要写的是值得了解的重要事物，就必须问自己：读者为什么偏偏不知道它？是因为他们聪明却缺乏经验，还是因为他们迟钝？</p><p>So the three reasons readers might not already know what you tell them are (a) that it’s not important, (b) that they’re obtuse, or (c) that they’re inexperienced. </p><p>所以，读者不知道你所要讲述的内容，原因有三：（a）内容不重要；（b）读者迟钝；（c）读者缺乏经验。</p><p>The reason I did this breakdown was to get at the following fact, which might have seemed controversial if I’d led with it, but should be obvious now. If you’re writing for smart people about important things, you’re writing for the young. </p><p>我做这种区分，是为了得出一个结论 —— 如果一开始就说，可能显得有争议，但现在看来应该很明显了：如果你要为聪明的人写重要的事，其实是在为年轻人写。</p><p>Or more precisely, that’s where you’ll have the most effect. Whatever you say should also be at least somewhat novel to you, however old you are. It’s not an essay otherwise, because an essay is something you write to figure something out. But whatever you figure out will presumably be more of a surprise to younger readers than it is to you. </p><p>更准确地说，这是你能产生最大影响的群体。无论你年龄多大，你所写的内容至少对自己来说也该有点新意。否则就不能称之为散文，因为散文本就是你为了弄明白某事而写的东西。但你弄明白的道理，对年轻读者来说，想必会比对你自己更令人惊讶。</p><p>There’s a continuum of surprise. At one extreme, something you read can change your whole way of thinking. The Selfish Gene did this to me. It was like suddenly seeing the other interpretation of an ambiguous image: you can treat genes rather than organisms as the protagonists, and evolution becomes easier to understand when you do. At the other extreme, writing merely puts into words something readers were already thinking — or thought they were. </p><p>惊喜是一个连续体。一端是，你读到的内容能彻底改变你的思维方式。《自私的基因》对我就是如此。这就像突然看懂了一幅模糊图像的另一种解读：你可以把基因而非生物体当作主角，这样一来，进化论就更容易理解了。另一端是，文字只是把读者已经在想（或者自以为在想）的东西表达出来而已。</p><p>The impact of an essay is how much it changes readers’ thinking multiplied by the importance of the topic. But it’s hard to do well at both. It’s hard to have big new ideas about important topics. So in practice there’s a tradeoff: you can change readers’ thinking a lot about moderately important things, or change it a little about very important ones. But with younger readers the tradeoff shifts. There’s more room to change their thinking, so there’s a bigger payoff for writing about important things. </p><p>一篇散文的影响力，等于它改变读者思维的程度乘以主题的重要性。但两者很难兼顾。对重要的主题产生重大的新见解，并非易事。所以实际上存在一种权衡：你可以在中等重要的事情上极大地改变读者的想法，或者在非常重要的事情上略微改变他们的想法。但对年轻读者而言，这种权衡会发生偏移。改变他们的思维有更大的空间，所以写重要的内容能带来更大的回报。</p><p>The tradeoff isn’t a conscious one, at least not for me. It’s more like a kind of gravitational field that writers work in. But every essayist works in it, whether they realize it or not. </p><p>这种权衡并非刻意为之，至少对我来说不是。它更像是作家身处的一种引力场。但每个散文作家，无论是否意识到，都身处其中。</p><p>This seems obvious once you state it, but it took me a long time to understand. I knew I wanted to write for smart people about important topics. I noticed empirically that I seemed to be writing for the young. But it took me years to understand that the latter was an automatic consequence of the former. In fact I only really figured it out as I was writing this essay. </p><p>说出来之后似乎显而易见，但我花了很久才明白这一点。我知道自己想为聪明的人写重要的事，也从经验中发现，自己似乎是在为年轻人写。但多年后我才明白，后者是前者的必然结果。事实上，直到写这篇散文时，我才真正想通。</p><p>Now that I know it, should I change anything? I don’t think so. In fact seeing the shape of the field that writers work in has reminded me that I’m not optimizing for returns in it. I’m not trying to surprise readers of any particular age; I’m trying to surprise myself. </p><p>既然明白了这一点，我应该做出改变吗？我觉得不必。事实上，看清作家所处领域的格局后，我反而意识到，自己并非在为追求回报而写作。我不是想给某个年龄段的读者带来惊喜，而是想给自己带来惊喜。</p><p>The way I usually decide what to write about is by following curiosity. I notice something new and dig into it. It would probably be a mistake to change that. But seeing the shape of the essay field has set me thinking. What would surprise young readers? Which important things do people tend to learn late? Interesting question. I should think about that.    </p><p>我通常通过追随好奇心来决定写什么。发现新事物，就深入挖掘。改变这种方式或许是个错误。但看清散文领域的格局后，我开始思考：什么能给年轻读者带来惊喜？哪些重要的东西，人们往往很晚才明白？这是个有趣的问题，我该好好想想。</p><p>Note </p><p>[1] It’s hard to write a really good essay about an unimportant topic, though, because a really good essayist will inevitably draw the topic into deeper waters. E. B. White could write an essay about how to boil potatoes that ended up being full of timeless wisdom. In which case, of course, it wouldn’t really be about how to boil potatoes; that would just have been the starting point. </p><p>[1] 不过，写一篇关于不重要话题的真正好散文并不容易，因为真正优秀的散文作家总会不可避免地将话题引向更深刻的层面。E.B. 怀特可以写一篇关于如何煮土豆的散文，最终却充满了永恒的智慧。当然，在这种情况下，文章其实并非真的在讲煮土豆，那只是一个起点而已。</p>]]></content>
    
    
    <categories>
      
      <category>文章翻译</category>
      
    </categories>
    
    
    <tags>
      
      <tag>PAUL GRAHAM</tag>
      
    </tags>
    
  </entry>
  
  
  
  <entry>
    <title>如何浪费时间与金钱</title>
    <link href="/2025/07/21/how-to-waste-time-and-money/"/>
    <url>/2025/07/21/how-to-waste-time-and-money/</url>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="HOW-TO-WASTE-TIME-AND-MONEY"><a href="#HOW-TO-WASTE-TIME-AND-MONEY" class="headerlink" title="HOW TO WASTE TIME AND MONEY"></a>HOW TO WASTE TIME AND MONEY</h2><p>原文链接: <a href="https://paulgraham.com/selfindulgence.html">https://paulgraham.com/selfindulgence.html</a></p><p>July 2010</p><h3 id="一、如何对金钱流失保持警觉"><a href="#一、如何对金钱流失保持警觉" class="headerlink" title="一、如何对金钱流失保持警觉"></a>一、如何对金钱流失保持警觉</h3><p>When we sold our startup in 1998 I suddenly got a lot of money. I now had to think about something I hadn’t had to think about before: how not to lose it. I knew it was possible to go from rich to poor, just as it was possible to go from poor to rich. But while I’d spent a lot of the past several years studying the paths from poor to rich, I knew practically nothing about the paths from rich to poor. Now, in order to avoid them, I had to learn where they were. </p><p>1998 年，当我们卖掉自己的初创公司时，我突然有了一大笔钱。这时，我不得不开始思考一个此前从未想过的问题：如何守住这笔钱。我知道，人可以从贫穷变富有，同样也可能从富有变贫穷。过去几年，我花了大量时间研究从穷到富的路径，但对于从富到穷的路径，我几乎一无所知。而现在，为了避开这些陷阱，我必须弄清楚它们到底在哪里。</p><p>So I started to pay attention to how fortunes are lost. If you’d asked me as a kid how rich people became poor, I’d have said by spending all their money. That’s how it happens in books and movies, because that’s the colorful way to do it. But in fact the way most fortunes are lost is not through excessive expenditure, but through bad investments. </p><p>于是，我开始留意财富是如何流失的。小时候如果有人问我，富人是怎么变穷的，我会说他们是把钱都花光了。书籍和电影里都是这么演的，因为这种方式更富有戏剧性。但事实上，大多数财富的流失并非源于过度消费，而是糟糕的投资。</p><p>It’s hard to spend a fortune without noticing. Someone with ordinary tastes would find it hard to blow through more than a few tens of thousands of dollars without thinking “wow, I’m spending a lot of money.” Whereas if you start trading derivatives, you can lose a million dollars (as much as you want, really) in the blink of an eye. </p><p>大把花钱却毫无察觉，这很难做到。一个品味普通的人，花掉几万美元后，总会想 “哇，我花了好多钱”。但如果你开始做衍生品交易，可能一眨眼的功夫就会输掉 100 万美元（说真的，想输多少就能输多少）。</p><p>In most people’s minds, spending money on luxuries sets off alarms that making investments doesn’t. Luxuries seem self-indulgent. And unless you got the money by inheriting it or winning a lottery, you’ve already been thoroughly trained that self-indulgence leads to trouble. Investing bypasses those alarms. You’re not spending the money; you’re just moving it from one asset to another. Which is why people trying to sell you expensive things say “it’s an investment.” </p><p>在大多数人看来，花钱买奢侈品会让人警觉，但投资却不会。奢侈品似乎是放纵自己的表现。而且，除非你的钱是继承来的或者中彩票得来的，否则你早就被反复告诫：放纵会招致麻烦。而投资则绕过了这些警报 —— 你不是在花钱，只是把钱从一种资产转移到另一种资产而已。这也是为什么那些推销昂贵东西的人会说 “这是一项投资”。</p><p>The solution is to develop new alarms. This can be a tricky business, because while the alarms that prevent you from overspending are so basic that they may even be in our DNA, the ones that prevent you from making bad investments have to be learned, and are sometimes fairly counterintuitive. </p><p>解决办法是建立新的警报机制。这可能有点棘手，因为防止过度消费的警报机制非常基础，甚至可能存在于我们的基因中，而防止糟糕投资的警报机制则需要学习，有时还相当违背直觉。</p><p>A few days ago I realized something surprising: the situation with time is much the same as with money. The most dangerous way to lose time is not to spend it having fun, but to spend it doing fake work. When you spend time having fun, you know you’re being self-indulgent. Alarms start to go off fairly quickly. If I woke up one morning and sat down on the sofa and watched TV all day, I’d feel like something was terribly wrong. Just thinking about it makes me wince. I’d start to feel uncomfortable after sitting on a sofa watching TV for 2 hours, let alone a whole day. </p><h3 id="二、浪费时间最危险的方式"><a href="#二、浪费时间最危险的方式" class="headerlink" title="二、浪费时间最危险的方式"></a>二、浪费时间最危险的方式</h3><p>几天前，我意识到一件令人惊讶的事：时间的情况和金钱非常相似。浪费时间最危险的方式，不是花时间享乐，而是做 “虚假工作”。当你花时间享乐时，你知道自己在放纵，警报很快就会响起。如果我早上醒来，坐在沙发上看一整天电视，我会觉得哪里不对劲。光是想想就让我畏缩 —— 坐沙发上看两个小时电视我就会不舒服，更别说一整天了。</p><p>And yet I’ve definitely had days when I might as well have sat in front of a TV all day — days at the end of which, if I asked myself what I got done that day, the answer would have been: basically, nothing. I feel bad after these days too, but nothing like as bad as I’d feel if I spent the whole day on the sofa watching TV. If I spent a whole day watching TV I’d feel like I was descending into perdition. But the same alarms don’t go off on the days when I get nothing done, because I’m doing stuff that seems, superficially, like real work. Dealing with email, for example. You do it sitting at a desk. It’s not fun. So it must be work. </p><p>但我确实有过这样的日子：一整天下来，要是问自己做了什么，答案基本是 “什么也没做”。这样的日子过后我也会难受，但远不如看一整天电视那么难受。如果看了一整天电视，我会觉得自己在堕落。但在那些一事无成的日子里，警报却不会响起，因为我在做的事情表面上看起来像正经工作。比如处理邮件 —— 你坐在办公桌前做这件事，而且并不觉得有趣，所以它肯定是工作。</p><p>With time, as with money, avoiding pleasure is no longer enough to protect you. It probably was enough to protect hunter-gatherers, and perhaps all pre-industrial societies. So nature and nurture combine to make us avoid self-indulgence. But the world has gotten more complicated: the most dangerous traps now are new behaviors that bypass our alarms about self-indulgence by mimicking more virtuous types. And the worst thing is, they’re not even fun.</p><p>对待时间和对待金钱一样，仅仅避免享乐已经不够了。对于狩猎采集者，或许对所有前工业社会的人来说，这可能就够了。所以，先天本能和后天教育共同让我们避免放纵。但世界变得更复杂了：最危险的陷阱是那些新行为 —— 它们通过模仿更有益的行为，绕过了我们对放纵的警报。最糟糕的是，这些行为甚至毫无乐趣可言。</p>]]></content>
    
    
    <categories>
      
      <category>文章翻译</category>
      
    </categories>
    
    
    <tags>
      
      <tag>PAUL GRAHAM</tag>
      
    </tags>
    
  </entry>
  
  
  
  <entry>
    <title>养娃</title>
    <link href="/2025/07/21/having-kids/"/>
    <url>/2025/07/21/having-kids/</url>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="HAVING-KIDS"><a href="#HAVING-KIDS" class="headerlink" title="HAVING KIDS"></a>HAVING KIDS</h2><p>原文链接: <a href="https://paulgraham.com/kids.html">https://paulgraham.com/kids.html</a></p><p>December 2019</p><h3 id="一、有小孩之前"><a href="#一、有小孩之前" class="headerlink" title="一、有小孩之前"></a>一、有小孩之前</h3><p>Before I had kids, I was afraid of having kids. Up to that point I felt about kids the way the young Augustine felt about living virtuously. I’d have been sad to think I’d never have children. But did I want them now? No. </p><p>在有孩子之前，我一直害怕要孩子。那时候，我对孩子的感觉，就像年轻时的奥古斯丁对 “过有德行的生活” 的感觉 —— 一想到自己永远不会有孩子，我会难过；但要说 “现在就想要”？不，我不想要。</p><p>If I had kids, I’d become a parent, and parents, as I’d known since I was a kid, were uncool. They were dull and responsible and had no fun. And while it’s not surprising that kids would believe that, to be honest I hadn’t seen much as an adult to change my mind. Whenever I’d noticed parents with kids, the kids seemed to be terrors, and the parents pathetic harried creatures, even when they prevailed. </p><p>如果有了孩子，我就会变成父母。而从我小时候起，父母在我眼里就是 “不酷” 的代名词：他们乏味、刻板，满脑子都是责任，完全无法享受生活。当然，孩子会这么想并不奇怪，但说实话，即便长大成人，我也没看到多少能改变这想法的事。每次看到带孩子的父母，孩子似乎都是些小恶魔，父母则是可怜兮兮、被折腾得焦头烂额的人 —— 哪怕他们最后 “镇住” 了孩子，也还是一副狼狈相。</p><p>When people had babies, I congratulated them enthusiastically, because that seemed to be what one did. But I didn’t feel it at all. “Better you than me,” I was thinking. </p><p>别人生孩子时，我会热情地祝贺，因为那似乎是 “该做的事”。但我心里毫无波澜，甚至在想：“还好是你，不是我。”</p><p>Now when people have babies I congratulate them enthusiastically and I mean it. Especially the first one. I feel like they just got the best gift in the world. </p><p>现在，别人生孩子时，我依然会热情祝贺，而且是发自内心的 —— 尤其是第一个孩子。我觉得他们像是收到了世界上最好的礼物。</p><p>What changed, of course, is that I had kids. Something I dreaded turned out to be wonderful. </p><p>当然，一切的转变都源于我自己有了孩子。曾经让我恐惧的事，最后竟成了美好的馈赠。</p><h3 id="二、有小孩之后"><a href="#二、有小孩之后" class="headerlink" title="二、有小孩之后"></a>二、有小孩之后</h3><p>Partly, and I won’t deny it, this is because of serious chemical changes that happened almost instantly when our first child was born. It was like someone flipped a switch. I suddenly felt protective not just toward our child, but toward all children. As I was driving my wife and new son home from the hospital, I approached a crosswalk full of pedestrians, and I found myself thinking “I have to be really careful of all these people. Every one of them is someone’s child!” </p><p>不得不承认，很大程度上是因为第一个孩子出生时，我体内瞬间发生了剧烈的化学变化。就像有人扳动了开关：我突然不仅想保护自己的孩子，还想保护所有孩子。记得开车载着妻子和刚出生的儿子从医院回家时，路过一个挤满行人的斑马线，我心里突然冒出一个念头：“我得对这些人万分小心。他们每一个，都是别人的孩子啊！”</p><p>So to some extent you can’t trust me when I say having kids is great. To some extent I’m like a religious cultist telling you that you’ll be happy if you join the cult too — but only because joining the cult will alter your mind in a way that will make you happy to be a cult member. </p><p>所以，当我说 “有孩子很棒” 时，你多少得打个折扣。某种程度上，我就像个邪教徒 —— 告诉你 “加入我们你就会快乐”，但真相是，只有加入后，你的大脑才会被改造，让你觉得作为教徒很快乐。</p><p>But not entirely. There were some things about having kids that I clearly got wrong before I had them. </p><p>但也不全是这样。有孩子这件事，我之前确实有很多明显的误解。</p><p>For example, there was a huge amount of selection bias in my observations of parents and children. Some parents may have noticed that I wrote “Whenever I’d noticed parents with kids.” Of course the times I noticed kids were when things were going wrong. I only noticed them when they made noise. And where was I when I noticed them? Ordinarily I never went to places with kids, so the only times I encountered them were in shared bottlenecks like airplanes. Which is not exactly a representative sample. Flying with a toddler is something very few parents enjoy. </p><p>比如，我对父母和孩子的观察存在严重的 “选择性偏差”。也许有父母注意到了，我写的是 “每次我‘注意到’带孩子的父母”。当然了，我会注意到孩子，往往是因为他们 “出状况” 的时候 —— 只有他们吵闹时，我才会留意到。而且，我是在什么场合注意到他们的呢？平时我根本不去有孩子的地方，唯一能碰到孩子的场合，都是像飞机这样的 “共用瓶颈” 场所。这显然不是有代表性的样本 —— 带学步的孩子坐飞机，没几个父母会觉得享受。</p><p>What I didn’t notice, because they tend to be much quieter, were all the great moments parents had with kids. People don’t talk about these much — the magic is hard to put into words, and all other parents know about them anyway — but one of the great things about having kids is that there are so many times when you feel there is nowhere else you’d rather be, and nothing else you’d rather be doing. You don’t have to be doing anything special. You could just be going somewhere together, or putting them to bed, or pushing them on the swings at the park. But you wouldn’t trade these moments for anything. One doesn’t tend to associate kids with peace, but that’s what you feel. You don’t need to look any further than where you are right now. </p><p>那些父母和孩子相处的美好时刻，我从来没注意到，因为它们大多安安静静的。人们很少谈论这些时刻 —— 那种魔力很难用语言描述，而且其他父母都懂 —— 但有孩子的一大好处是，你会频繁地觉得 “此刻就是最好的，做什么都不如现在”。不一定是做什么特别的事：可能只是一起出门，可能是哄他们睡觉，可能是在公园推他们荡秋千。但这些时刻，你无论如何都不愿交换。没人会把 “孩子” 和 “平静” 联系起来，但你真的会感到平静 —— 你会觉得，眼前的一切就足够了。</p><p>Before I had kids, I had moments of this kind of peace, but they were rarer. With kids it can happen several times a day. </p><p>有孩子之前，我也有过这种平静的时刻，但很少。有了孩子之后，一天能有好几次。</p><p>My other source of data about kids was my own childhood, and that was similarly misleading. I was pretty bad, and was always in trouble for something or other. So it seemed to me that parenthood was essentially law enforcement. I didn’t realize there were good times too. </p><p>我对孩子的另一个认知来源是自己的童年，这同样具有误导性。我小时候很调皮，总因为各种事被找麻烦。所以在我看来，为人父母本质上就是 “执法”—— 我从没想过，原来也有快乐的时候。</p><p>I remember my mother telling me once when I was about 30 that she’d really enjoyed having me and my sister. My god, I thought, this woman is a saint. She not only endured all the pain we subjected her to, but actually enjoyed it? Now I realize she was simply telling the truth. </p><p>记得 30 岁左右时，母亲曾对我说，她真的很享受养育我和妹妹的过程。当时我心想：天啊，这女人简直是圣人。她不仅忍受了我们带来的所有麻烦，竟然还觉得享受？现在我才明白，她只是在说真话。</p><p>She said that one reason she liked having us was that we’d been interesting to talk to. That took me by surprise when I had kids. You don’t just love them. They become your friends too. They’re really interesting. And while I admit small children are disastrously fond of repetition (anything worth doing once is worth doing fifty times) it’s often genuinely fun to play with them. That surprised me too. Playing with a 2 year old was fun when I was 2 and definitely not fun when I was 6. Why would it become fun again later? But it does. </p><p>她说喜欢养我们的一个原因是，和我们聊天很有意思。有了孩子后，这一点让我很意外：你不只是爱他们，他们还会成为你的朋友。他们真的很有趣。虽然我承认，小孩子对重复有种要命的执念（但凡值得做一次的事，就值得做五十次），但和他们玩常常是真的开心。这也让我意外：我两岁时和两岁的孩子玩很开心，六岁时就觉得无趣了，为什么长大后反而又觉得好玩了呢？但事实就是这样。</p><p>There are of course times that are pure drudgery. Or worse still, terror. Having kids is one of those intense types of experience that are hard to imagine unless you’ve had them. But it is not, as I implicitly believed before having kids, simply your DNA heading for the lifeboats. </p><p>当然，育儿也有纯粹枯燥的时候，甚至可怕的时刻。有孩子是一种极致的体验，没经历过的人很难想象。但它不像我之前默认的那样，只是 “DNA 在找救生艇”（指繁衍后代只是基因的本能）。</p><p>Some of my worries about having kids were right, though. They definitely make you less productive. I know having kids makes some people get their act together, but if your act was already together, you’re going to have less time to do it in. In particular, you’re going to have to work to a schedule. Kids have schedules. I’m not sure if it’s because that’s how kids are, or because it’s the only way to integrate their lives with adults’, but once you have kids, you tend to have to work on their schedule. </p><p>不过，我之前对有孩子的一些担忧是对的。他们确实会降低你的生产力。我知道有些人为了孩子会 “振作起来”，但如果你的生活本就有条理，那你能用来做事的时间会变少。尤其是，你得按时间表来。孩子有他们的作息 —— 不确定是因为孩子本身就这样，还是因为这是让他们的生活和成人生活融合的唯一方式 —— 但有了孩子后，你往往得按他们的时间表来。</p><p>You will have chunks of time to work. But you can’t let work spill promiscuously through your whole life, like I used to before I had kids. You’re going to have to work at the same time every day, whether inspiration is flowing or not, and there are going to be times when you have to stop, even if it is. </p><p>你还是会有整块的工作时间，但不能像以前那样，让工作随心所欲地填满生活。你得每天在固定时间工作，不管有没有灵感；也总会有不得不停下的时候，哪怕灵感正盛。</p><p>I’ve been able to adapt to working this way. Work, like love, finds a way. If there are only certain times it can happen, it happens at those times. So while I don’t get as much done as before I had kids, I get enough done. </p><p>我已经适应了这样的工作方式。工作和爱一样，总会找到出路。如果只有特定时间能做事，那就在那些时间做。所以虽然我做的事比没孩子时少，但也足够了。</p><p>I hate to say this, because being ambitious has always been a part of my identity, but having kids may make one less ambitious. It hurts to see that sentence written down. I squirm to avoid it. But if there weren’t something real there, why would I squirm? The fact is, once you have kids, you’re probably going to care more about them than you do about yourself. And attention is a zero-sum game. Only one idea at a time can be the top idea in your mind. Once you have kids, it will often be your kids, and that means it will less often be some project you’re working on. </p><p>这话我不想说，因为 “有野心” 一直是我身份的一部分，但有孩子可能会让人没那么有野心。写下这句话时，我都觉得别扭，想回避。但如果这不是事实，我何必回避呢？事实是，有了孩子后，你可能会更在乎他们，胜过在乎自己。而注意力是零和游戏 —— 脑子里一次只能有一个最重要的念头。有了孩子后，这个念头常常是他们，所以你放在工作项目上的心思就会少些。</p><p>I have some hacks for sailing close to this wind. For example, when I write essays, I think about what I’d want my kids to know. That drives me to get things right. And when I was writing Bel, I told my kids that once I finished it I’d take them to Africa. When you say that sort of thing to a little kid, they treat it as a promise. Which meant I had to finish or I’d be taking away their trip to Africa. Maybe if I’m really lucky such tricks could put me net ahead. But the wind is there, no question. </p><p>我有一些小技巧来应对这种情况。比如写文章时，我会想 “这是我想让孩子知道的事”，这会推动我把事情做好。写《贝尔》时，我跟孩子们说，写完就带他们去非洲。跟小孩子说这种话，他们会当真的 —— 这意味着我必须写完，不然就会剥夺他们的非洲之旅。也许运气好的话，这些技巧能让我总体上不输以前。但那种 “野心被稀释” 的趋势，确实存在。</p><p>On the other hand, what kind of wimpy ambition do you have if it won’t survive having kids? Do you have so little to spare? </p><p>但反过来想：如果你的野心连有孩子都承受不住，那它也太脆弱了吧？你就这么 “输不起” 吗？</p><p>And while having kids may be warping my present judgement, it hasn’t overwritten my memory. I remember perfectly well what life was like before. Well enough to miss some things a lot, like the ability to take off for some other country at a moment’s notice. That was so great. Why did I never do that? </p><p>虽然有孩子可能扭曲了我现在的判断，但它没抹去我的记忆。我清楚记得没孩子时的生活，清楚到会很想念一些事，比如随时能出发去别的国家。那多棒啊，我以前怎么没多做呢？</p><p>See what I did there? The fact is, most of the freedom I had before kids, I never used. I paid for it in loneliness, but I never used it. </p><p>发现了吗？事实是，没孩子时拥有的那些自由，我大多都没利用过。我为它付出了孤独的代价，却从未真正使用过。</p><p>I had plenty of happy times before I had kids. But if I count up happy moments, not just potential happiness but actual happy moments, there are more after kids than before. Now I practically have it on tap, almost any bedtime. </p><p>没孩子时，我有过很多快乐的时光。但如果数 “快乐的时刻”—— 不只是潜在的快乐，而是真实的快乐瞬间 —— 有孩子之后比之前多。现在，几乎每个哄睡的时刻，我都能感受到这种快乐，触手可及。</p><p>People’s experiences as parents vary a lot, and I know I’ve been lucky. But I think the worries I had before having kids must be pretty common, and judging by other parents’ faces when they see their kids, so must the happiness that kids bring.     </p><p>为人父母的体验因人而异，我知道自己很幸运。但我觉得，我之前对有孩子的担忧应该很普遍；而从其他父母看到孩子时的神情来看，孩子带来的快乐，大概也同样普遍。</p><p>Note </p><p>[1] Adults are sophisticated enough to see 2 year olds for the fascinatingly complex characters they are, whereas to most 6 year olds, 2 year olds are just defective 6 year olds.</p><p>[1] 成年人足够成熟，能发现两岁孩子身上那种迷人的复杂性，把他们看作独一无二的鲜活个体；而对大多数六岁孩子来说，两岁的小孩不过是 “发育不完全的六岁孩子” 罢了。</p>]]></content>
    
    
    <categories>
      
      <category>文章翻译</category>
      
    </categories>
    
    
    <tags>
      
      <tag>PAUL GRAHAM</tag>
      
    </tags>
    
  </entry>
  
  
  
  <entry>
    <title>如何取得杰出成就</title>
    <link href="/2025/07/19/how-to-do-great-work/"/>
    <url>/2025/07/19/how-to-do-great-work/</url>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="How-to-Do-Great-Work"><a href="#How-to-Do-Great-Work" class="headerlink" title="How to Do Great Work"></a>How to Do Great Work</h2><p>原文链接: <a href="https://paulgraham.com/greatwork.html">https://paulgraham.com/greatwork.html</a></p><p>译文链接 [赛博禅心]: <a href="https://mp.weixin.qq.com/s/31iL-Kbs4KrqpgrERVRNzQ">https://mp.weixin.qq.com/s/31iL-Kbs4KrqpgrERVRNzQ</a></p><h3 id="一、成就伟大事业的关键"><a href="#一、成就伟大事业的关键" class="headerlink" title="一、成就伟大事业的关键"></a>一、成就伟大事业的关键</h3><p>If you collected lists of techniques for doing great work in a lot of different fields, what would the intersection look like? I decided to find out by making it.</p><p>Partly my goal was to create a guide that could be used by someone working in any field. But I was also curious about the shape of the intersection. And one thing this exercise shows is that it does have a definite shape; it’s not just a point labelled “work hard.”</p><p>The following recipe assumes you’re very ambitious.</p><p>如果让你收集在不同领域成就伟大事业的技巧列表，它们的交集会是什么呢？我决定通过实践来找出答案。</p><p>我的目标有两个，其一是创建一个可以为所有领域的从业者所用的指南，其二是我也对交集的形态感到好奇 —— 实践表明，这个交集确实有一个「明确的形状」，它不仅仅是一个标有「努力工作」字样的点。</p><p><strong>以下指南的前提假设是你拥有雄心壮志。</strong></p><h4 id="第一步：决定要做什么"><a href="#第一步：决定要做什么" class="headerlink" title="第一步：决定要做什么"></a>第一步：决定要做什么</h4><p>The first step is to decide what to work on. The work you choose needs to have three qualities: </p><ul><li>it has to be something you have a natural aptitude for, </li><li>that you have a deep interest in, </li><li>and that offers scope to do great work.</li></ul><p>**第一步是决定要做什么。**你所选择的工作需要具有三个特质：</p><ol><li>你对这件事有天赋；</li><li>你对这件事有深深的兴趣；</li><li>这件事拥有取得杰出成就的空间。</li></ol><p>In practice you don’t have to worry much about the third criterion. Ambitious people are if anything already too conservative about it. So all you need to do is find something you have an aptitude for and great interest in. [1]</p><p>在实践中，我们不必过于担心第三点 —— 对于具有雄心壮志的人来说，可见的空间已然过于保守 —— 所以<strong>我们需要做的就是找到有天赋和极大兴趣的事情。</strong>[1]</p><p>That sounds straightforward, but it’s often quite difficult. When you’re young you don’t know what you’re good at or what different kinds of work are like. Some kinds of work you end up doing may not even exist yet. So while some people know what they want to do at 14, most have to figure it out.</p><p>这听起来很简单，但往往很困难。当我们年轻时，并不知道自己擅长什么，或者不同类型的工作是什么样的，甚至我们最终做的一些工作可能当前还不存在。所以，虽然有些人在十四岁的时候就知道他们想做什么，但大多数人还需要时间去弄清楚。</p><p>The way to figure out what to work on is by working. If you’re not sure what to work on, guess. But pick something and get going. You’ll probably guess wrong some of the time, but that’s fine. It’s good to know about multiple things; some of the biggest discoveries come from noticing connections between different fields.</p><p>找出要做什么的方法是通过工作。如果我们不确定要做什么，那就猜，但是要选择一件事情并开始做。我们可能会猜错，但没关系，了解多种事物是好的 —— <strong>一些最伟大的发现来自于注意到不同领域之间的联系</strong>。</p><p>Develop a habit of working on your own projects. Don’t let “work” mean something other people tell you to do. If you do manage to do great work one day, it will probably be on a project of your own. It may be within some bigger project, but you’ll be driving your part of it.</p><p><strong>养成自己发起并推动项目的习惯</strong>。不要让「工作」这个词等同于别人告诉我们要做什么事情。如果我们有一天真的取得了杰出成就，那可能会始于我们自己发起的一个项目 —— 它可能包含在某个更大的项目中，但你会推动其中的一部分。</p><p>What should your projects be? Whatever seems to you excitingly ambitious. As you grow older and your taste in projects evolves, exciting and important will converge. At 7 it may seem excitingly ambitious to build huge things out of Lego, then at 14 to teach yourself calculus, till at 21 you’re starting to explore unanswered questions in physics. But always preserve excitingness.</p><p>我们的项目应该是什么？任何令自己感到兴奋的且可以让自己踌躇满志的事。随着年龄的增长，我们对项目的品味会进化，兴奋程度和重要性会趋于正相关 —— 七岁时，用乐高搭建巨大的模型可能看起来令人兴奋且斗志满满；十四岁时，可能是自学微积分；二十一岁时，则可能是开始探索物理学中的未解问题 —— 但，无论是什么，它们始终是令人兴奋的。</p><p>There’s a kind of excited curiosity that’s both the engine and the rudder of great work. It will not only drive you, but if you let it have its way, will also show you what to work on.</p><p>伴随着兴奋的好奇心是杰出成就的引擎和舵，它不仅会驱动我们前进，如果我们能让它发挥更大的作用，它还会告诉我们要做什么。</p><p>What are you excessively curious about — curious to a degree that would bore most other people? That’s what you’re looking for.</p><p><strong>我们对什么有着「过分的」好奇心，「过分」到其他大多数人会觉得无聊的程度？那就是我们所要寻找的事。</strong></p><h4 id="第二步：学习足够多的知识"><a href="#第二步：学习足够多的知识" class="headerlink" title="第二步：学习足够多的知识"></a>第二步：学习足够多的知识</h4><p>Once you’ve found something you’re excessively interested in, the next step is to learn enough about it to get you to one of the frontiers of knowledge. Knowledge expands fractally, and from a distance its edges look smooth, but once you learn enough to get close to one, they turn out to be full of gaps.</p><p>一旦找到了「过分」感兴趣的事，下一步就是学习足够多的知识，让我们能够到达此领域的知识前沿。知识以分形的方式扩展，从远处看，它的边缘看起来很平滑，但一旦我们学习得足够多，接近其中的部分边缘，会发现它们充满了缺口。</p><h4 id="第三步：关注所属领域的”缺口”"><a href="#第三步：关注所属领域的”缺口”" class="headerlink" title="第三步：关注所属领域的”缺口”"></a>第三步：关注所属领域的”缺口”</h4><p>The next step is to notice them. This takes some skill, because your brain wants to ignore such gaps in order to make a simpler model of the world. Many discoveries have come from asking questions about things that everyone else took for granted. [2]</p><p>下一步是注意到这些缺口。这需要一些技巧，因为我们的大脑想要忽略这些缺口，以便构建一个更简单的世界模型。许多伟大的发现来自于对大家都视为理所当然的事提出问题。[2]</p><p>If the answers seem strange, so much the better. Great work often has a tincture of strangeness. You see this from painting to math. It would be affected to try to manufacture it, but if it appears, embrace it.</p><p>如果答案看起来很奇怪，那就更好了 —— 杰出成就往往带有奇特色彩 —— 从绘画到数学，我们都可以看到这一点。试图制造这种奇特的行为是做作的，但如果它出现了，就接受它。</p><h4 id="第四步：探索其中有前景的缺口"><a href="#第四步：探索其中有前景的缺口" class="headerlink" title="第四步：探索其中有前景的缺口"></a>第四步：探索其中有前景的缺口</h4><p>Boldly chase outlier ideas, even if other people aren’t interested in them — in fact, especially if they aren’t. If you’re excited about some possibility that everyone else ignores, and you have enough expertise to say precisely what they’re all overlooking, that’s as good a bet as you’ll find. [3]</p><p><strong>大胆地追求不合群的想法，即使其他人对它们不感兴趣</strong> —— 事实上，尤其是他们不感兴趣的时候。如果我们对大家都忽视的某种可能性感到兴奋，并且有足够的专业知识来精确地说出他们都忽视了什么，那就是我们能找到的最好的赌注。[3]</p><p>Four steps: </p><ul><li>choose a field, </li><li>learn enough to get to the frontier, </li><li>notice gaps, </li><li>explore promising ones.</li></ul><p>四个步骤：</p><ol><li>选择一个领域；</li><li>学习足够多的知识以到达领域前沿；</li><li>注意到领域缺口；</li><li>探索其中有前景的缺口。</li></ol><p>This is how practically everyone who’s done great work has done it, from painters to physicists.</p><p>—— 这就是几乎所有取得杰出成就的人都是如何做到的，从画家到物理学家。</p><p>Steps two and four will require hard work. It may not be possible to prove that you have to work hard to do great things, but the empirical evidence is on the scale of the evidence for mortality. That’s why it’s essential to work on something you’re deeply interested in. Interest will drive you to work harder than mere diligence ever could.</p><p>第二步和第四步需要努力。我可能无法用语言证明一个人必须努力才能取得伟大成就，但实证证据就像死亡的证据一样确凿。这就是为什么我们必须从事自己深感兴趣的事情 —— 兴趣会驱使我们比单纯的勤奋工作更加努力。</p><p>The three most powerful motives are curiosity, delight, and the desire to do something impressive. Sometimes they converge, and that combination is the most powerful of all.</p><p>The big prize is to discover a new fractal bud. You notice a crack in the surface of knowledge, pry it open, and there’s a whole world inside.</p><p><strong>三个最强大的内在动机是好奇心、快乐和做出令人印象深刻的事情的欲望，当它们会汇聚在一起时，会成为最强大的组合。</strong></p><p>最大的奖励是发现一个新的分形芽。我们注意到了知识表面的一个裂缝，撬开它，里面有一个完整的世界。</p><h3 id="二、找出自己要做的事"><a href="#二、找出自己要做的事" class="headerlink" title="二、找出自己要做的事"></a>二、找出自己要做的事</h3><p>Let’s talk a little more about the complicated business of figuring out what to work on. The main reason it’s hard is that you can’t tell what most kinds of work are like except by doing them. Which means the four steps overlap: you may have to work at something for years before you know how much you like it or how good you are at it. And in the meantime you’re not doing, and thus not learning about, most other kinds of work. So in the worst case you choose late based on very incomplete information. [4]</p><p>我们多讨论一些关于弄清楚要做什么这个复杂的问题。其中，主要困难在于，除了做过的工作，我们无法知道大多数类型的工作是什么样的，这意味着前面所说的四个步骤是重叠的：我们可能需要花几年的时间做某件事，才能知道自己有多喜欢它或者我们在这方面有多好；同时，我们没有在做大多数其他类型的工作，也就没有在学习。所以在最坏的情况下，我们会在不正确的时机且信息非常不完整的情况下做出选择。[4]</p><p>The nature of ambition exacerbates this problem. Ambition comes in two forms, one that precedes interest in the subject and one that grows out of it. Most people who do great work have a mix, and the more you have of the former, the harder it will be to decide what to do.</p><p>雄心壮志的性质加剧了这个问题。雄心壮志有两种形式：一种是在对工作感兴趣之前就有的，另一种是在工作过程中生长出来的。取得伟大成就的大多数人的雄心都是混合的，但前者越少，就会越难决定要做什么。</p><p>The educational systems in most countries pretend it’s easy. They expect you to commit to a field long before you could know what it’s really like. And as a result an ambitious person on an optimal trajectory will often read to the system as an instance of breakage.</p><p>大多数国家的教育系统都假装决定要做什么很容易，他们期望我们在知道某个领域真正是什么样子之前就做出决定。因此，<strong>沿着最佳轨迹来看，一个有雄心壮志的人往往会被系统视为异类。</strong></p><p>It would be better if they at least admitted it — if they admitted that the system not only can’t do much to help you figure out what to work on, but is designed on the assumption that you’ll somehow magically guess as a teenager. They don’t tell you, but I will: when it comes to figuring out what to work on, you’re on your own. Some people get lucky and do guess correctly, but the rest will find themselves scrambling diagonally across tracks laid down on the assumption that everyone does.</p><p>如果这些系统至少承认这一点就好了 —— 系统不仅不能帮助我们弄清楚要做什么，而且还是在假设我们可以在十几岁的时候神奇地猜出来的基础上设计的。它们不会说，但在这里我要强调：<strong>当涉及到弄清楚要做什么时，我们只能靠自己</strong>。有些人运气好，一下就猜对了，但其他人会发现自己在假设每个人都会在的轨道上歪斜着奔跑。</p><p>What should you do if you’re young and ambitious but don’t know what to work on? What you should not do is drift along passively, assuming the problem will solve itself. You need to take action. But there is no systematic procedure you can follow. When you read biographies of people who’ve done great work, it’s remarkable how much luck is involved. They discover what to work on as a result of a chance meeting, or by reading a book they happen to pick up. So you need to make yourself a big target for luck, and the way to do that is to be curious. Try lots of things, meet lots of people, read lots of books, ask lots of questions. [5]</p><p>如果我们年轻并且有雄心但不知道要做什么，我们应该做什么？我们知道自己不应该被动漂流，假设问题会自己解决，同时我们需要采取行动，但没有可以遵循的系统性程序。当我们阅读取得杰出成就的人的传记时，会发现运气的参与程度是那么高：他们通过偶然的会面，或者读到他们碰巧拿起的一本书，就发现了要做什么。<strong>所以我们需要让自己成为运气的显眼目标，做到这一点的方法是保持好奇 —— 尝试很多事，见很多人，读很多书，问很多问题。</strong>[5]</p><p>When in doubt, optimize for interestingness. Fields change as you learn more about them. What mathematicians do, for example, is very different from what you do in high school math classes. So you need to give different types of work a chance to show you what they’re like. But a field should become increasingly interesting as you learn more about it. If it doesn’t, it’s probably not for you.</p><p>当我们感到疑惑时，优先考虑有趣的事情。随着对它们了解得越多，我们对领域的认知就会发生变化，例如，数学家做的事情与我们在高中数学课上做的事情非常不同 —— 所以我们需要给不同类型的工作一个展示它们是什么样的机会 —— 但是，当我们对一个领域了解得越多，它应该变得越来越有趣，如果没有，那可能就不适合自己。</p><p>Don’t worry if you find you’re interested in different things than other people. The stranger your tastes in interestingness, the better. Strange tastes are often strong ones, and a strong taste for work means you’ll be productive. And you’re more likely to find new things if you’re looking where few have looked before.</p><p>如果我们发现自己对其他人不感兴趣的事情感兴趣，不要担心，我们的兴趣越奇特，越好 —— 奇特的往往是强烈的，对工作有强烈的感受意味着我们会有超高的生产力。而且，如果我们在很少有人到达过的地方探索，那就更有可能找到新的东西。</p><p>One sign that you’re suited for some kind of work is when you like even the parts that other people find tedious or frightening.</p><p><strong>当我们喜欢其他人感到乏味或恐惧的工作时，这是一个我们适合这份工作的标志。</strong></p><p>But fields aren’t people; you don’t owe them any loyalty. If in the course of working on one thing you discover another that’s more exciting, don’t be afraid to switch.</p><p>但，领域不是人，我们完全不需要对它们保持忠诚。如果在做一件事的过程中，我们发现了另一件更令人兴奋的事，不要害怕切换。</p><p>If you’re making something for people, make sure it’s something they actually want. The best way to do this is to make something you yourself want. Write the story you want to read; build the tool you want to use. Since your friends probably have similar interests, this will also get you your initial audience.</p><p>如果我们正在为人们做点东西，要确保它是人们真正想要的。做到这一点的最好方法是做自己想要的东西：写自己想读的故事，制作自己想使用的工具。由于我们的朋友可能有类似的兴趣，这也会为我们带来初始「观众」。</p><p>This should follow from the excitingness rule. Obviously the most exciting story to write will be the one you want to read. The reason I mention this case explicitly is that so many people get it wrong. Instead of making what they want, they try to make what some imaginary, more sophisticated audience wants. And once you go down that route, you’re lost. [6]</p><p>这也可以从令人兴奋的规则中得出的 —— 显然，最令人兴奋的故事就是我们自己想读的故事。我特别提到这个例子的原因是，<strong>有很多人在这方面做错了，他们不是制作他们想要的东西，而是试图制作一些想象中的、更成熟的观众想要的东西。一旦我们走上这条路，就迷失了。</strong>[6]</p><p>There are a lot of forces that will lead you astray when you’re trying to figure out what to work on. Pretentiousness, fashion, fear, money, politics, other people’s wishes, eminent frauds. But if you stick to what you find genuinely interesting, you’ll be proof against all of them. If you’re interested, you’re not astray.</p><p>当我们试图弄清楚要做什么时，有很多力量会使我们误入歧途：矫饰、趋势、恐惧、金钱、政治、他人的愿望、狡猾的骗子。但如果我们坚持自己真正感兴趣的事情，就能抵御所有这些，如果我们感兴趣，就没有误入歧途。</p><h3 id="三、关于制定计划"><a href="#三、关于制定计划" class="headerlink" title="三、关于制定计划"></a>三、关于制定计划</h3><p>Following your interests may sound like a rather passive strategy, but in practice it usually means following them past all sorts of obstacles. You usually have to risk rejection and failure. So it does take a good deal of boldness.</p><p>追随自己的兴趣可能听起来像是一种相当被动的策略，但在实践中，它通常意味着要跨越各种障碍，我们通常需要冒着被拒绝和失败的风险，所以这确实需要相当大的勇气。</p><p>But while you need boldness, you don’t usually need much planning. In most cases the recipe for doing great work is simply: work hard on excitingly ambitious projects, and something good will come of it. Instead of making a plan and then executing it, you just try to preserve certain invariants.</p><p>但是，我们虽然需要勇气，但通常不需要太多计划。大多数情况下，成就伟大事业的方式很简单：在令人兴奋的、能够激发我们雄心壮志的项目上努力工作，好的事情就会自然发生 —— <strong>我们不需要制定一个计划然后执行它，只需要维持某些不变量</strong>。</p><p>The trouble with planning is that it only works for achievements you can describe in advance. You can win a gold medal or get rich by deciding to as a child and then tenaciously pursuing that goal, but you can’t discover natural selection that way.</p><p>计划的问题在于，它只适用于可以提前描述的成就。我们可以决定赢得金牌或者变得富有，然后坚持追求这个目标，但不能以这种方式实现自然选择。</p><p>I think for most people who want to do great work, the right strategy is not to plan too much. At each stage do whatever seems most interesting and gives you the best options for the future. I call this approach “staying upwind.” This is how most people who’ve done great work seem to have done it.</p><p>我认为，对于大多数想要取得伟大成就的人来说，正确的策略是不要计划太多。在每个阶段，做任何看起来最有趣并为未来提供最好选择的事，我称这种方法为「保持上风」—— 这似乎就是大多数伟大成就如何达成的。</p><h3 id="四、工作推进的策略技巧"><a href="#四、工作推进的策略技巧" class="headerlink" title="四、工作推进的策略技巧"></a>四、工作推进的策略技巧</h3><p>Even when you’ve found something exciting to work on, working on it is not always straightforward. There will be times when some new idea makes you leap out of bed in the morning and get straight to work. But there will also be plenty of times when things aren’t like that.</p><p>即使我们找到了令人兴奋的工作，进行这项工作也并不总是简单的。有时候，一些新的想法会让我们早上从床上跳起来，直接开始工作，但也有很多时候，事情恰恰相反。</p><p>You don’t just put out your sail and get blown forward by inspiration. There are headwinds and currents and hidden shoals. So there’s a technique to working, just as there is to sailing.</p><p>我们不能只是张开帆，让灵感把自己推向前方，会有逆风、潮汐和隐藏的暗礁。所以，<strong>工作就像航行一样，是有技巧的</strong>。</p><p>For example, while you must work hard, it’s possible to work too hard, and if you do that you’ll find you get diminishing returns: fatigue will make you stupid, and eventually even damage your health. The point at which work yields diminishing returns depends on the type. Some of the hardest types you might only be able to do for four or five hours a day.</p><p>例如，我们虽然必须努力工作，但是也有可能工作过度，在这种状态下，我们会发现收益递减：疲劳会让我们变得愚蠢，最终甚至可能损害我们的健康。工作产生递减收益的点取决于工作的类型，一些最艰难的类型，我们可能一天只能做四五个小时。</p><p>Ideally those hours will be contiguous. To the extent you can, try to arrange your life so you have big blocks of time to work in. You’ll shy away from hard tasks if you know you might be interrupted.</p><p>理想情况下，这些工时应该是连续的。尽可能地，试着安排自己的生活，让自己有大块的时间来工作，如果知道可能会被打断，那就回避艰难的任务。</p><p>It will probably be harder to start working than to keep working. You’ll often have to trick yourself to get over that initial threshold. Don’t worry about this; it’s the nature of work, not a flaw in your character. Work has a sort of activation energy, both per day and per project. And since this threshold is fake in the sense that it’s higher than the energy required to keep going, it’s ok to tell yourself a lie of corresponding magnitude to get over it.</p><p>开始工作可能比继续工作更难，你经常需要欺骗自己，才能越过初始门槛。不要担心，这是工作的性质，不是你性格中的缺陷。工作需要一种「激活能量」，每天，以及每个项目都有，但因为它比继续前进所需的能量高，这个门槛可以被视作是假的，所以可以对自己适度撒个谎来越过它。</p><p>It’s usually a mistake to lie to yourself if you want to do great work, but this is one of the rare cases where it isn’t. When I’m reluctant to start work in the morning, I often trick myself by saying “I’ll just read over what I’ve got so far.” Five minutes later I’ve found something that seems mistaken or incomplete, and I’m off.</p><p>如果我们想取得伟大成就，对自己撒谎通常是错的，但有少数几个例外。每当早上不愿意开始工作时，我经常欺骗自己说：「我只是看看自己到目前为止做了什么。」五分钟后，我发现了一些看起来错误或不完整的东西，就开始工作了。</p><p>Similar techniques work for starting new projects. It’s ok to lie to yourself about how much work a project will entail, for example. Lots of great things began with someone saying “How hard could it be?”</p><p>类似的技巧适用于开始新的项目。在预估项目所需的工作量时，向自己撒谎是可以的，<strong>许多伟大事业都是从某人说「这有什么难的？」开始的</strong>。</p><p>This is one case where the young have an advantage. They’re more optimistic, and even though one of the sources of their optimism is ignorance, in this case ignorance can sometimes beat knowledge.</p><p>这是年轻人有优势的例子之一 —— 他们更乐观 —— 尽管他们乐观的部分来源是无知，但在这种情况下，无知有时可以打败渊博。</p><p>Try to finish what you start, though, even if it turns out to be more work than you expected. Finishing things is not just an exercise in tidiness or self-discipline. In many projects a lot of the best work happens in what was meant to be the final stage.</p><p>尽管如此，我们要尽量完成己经开始的事情，即使它比预期的工作量要多很多。完成一件事不仅是整洁或自律的练习，在许多项目中，最佳成就点处于本应是最后阶段的地方。</p><p>Another permissible lie is to exaggerate the importance of what you’re working on, at least in your own mind. If that helps you discover something new, it may turn out not to have been a lie after all. [7]</p><p>另一个可以撒谎的点是在自己心中夸大我们正在做的事情的重要性。如果这有助于我们发现新的东西，那么它可能最终并不是一个谎言。[7]</p><p>Since there are two senses of starting work — per day and per project — there are also two forms of procrastination. Per-project procrastination is far the more dangerous. You put off starting that ambitious project from year to year because the time isn’t quite right. When you’re procrastinating in units of years, you can get a lot not done. [8]</p><p>由于「开始工作」的有两种定义 —— 每天和每个项目 —— 所以也有两种形式的拖延，<strong>以项目为单位的拖延远比以天为单位的拖延更危险</strong> —— 我们把开始那个雄心勃勃的项目推迟了一年又一年，因为时间还不够 —— 当以年为单位计算时，我们可以做很多事情。[8]</p><p>One reason per-project procrastination is so dangerous is that it usually camouflages itself as work. You’re not just sitting around doing nothing; you’re working industriously on something else. So per-project procrastination doesn’t set off the alarms that per-day procrastination does. You’re too busy to notice it.</p><p>项目的拖延之所以如此危险，其中一个原因是它通常会伪装成「工作」。我们不是坐在那里什么都不做，而是在其他事情上勤奋地工作。所以，项目的拖延不会像日期的拖延一样，触发拖延的警报 —— 我们太忙了，注意不到它。</p><p>The way to beat it is to stop occasionally and ask yourself: Am I working on what I most want to work on? When you’re young it’s ok if the answer is sometimes no, but this gets increasingly dangerous as you get older. [9]</p><p>**打败项目拖延的方法是偶尔停下来问自己：「我正在做我最想做的事吗？」**年轻的时候，如果答案有时是「不」，那是可以的，但随着年龄的增长，这会变得越来越危险。[9]</p><p>Great work usually entails spending what would seem to most people an unreasonable amount of time on a problem. You can’t think of this time as a cost, or it will seem too high. You have to find the work sufficiently engaging as it’s happening.</p><p>**杰出的成就通常需要我们在一个问题上花费大多数人认为超出了合理范围的大量时间。**我们不能把这个时间看作是成本，否则它会显得太高，我们必须在工作过程中找到足够的吸引力。</p><p>There may be some jobs where you have to work diligently for years at things you hate before you get to the good part, but this is not how great work happens. Great work happens by focusing consistently on something you’re genuinely interested in. When you pause to take stock, you’re surprised how far you’ve come.</p><p>有一些工作，我们可能必须在自己讨厌的事情上努力工作数年，才能接近喜欢的部分，但这不是杰出成就产生的方式，杰出的成就是通过持续关注自己真正感兴趣的事情来实现的 —— 当我们停下来盘点时，会惊讶于自己已经走了多远。</p><p>The reason we’re surprised is that we underestimate the cumulative effect of work. Writing a page a day doesn’t sound like much, but if you do it every day you’ll write a book a year. That’s the key: consistency. People who do great things don’t get a lot done every day. They get something done, rather than nothing.</p><p>我们往往会低估工作的累积效应。每天写一页字不算什么，但如果我们每天都这样做，一年就能写一本书 —— <strong>这就是关键：一致性</strong> —— 取得杰出成就的人并不是每天都做很多事情，他们只做一些事情，而不是什么都不做。</p><p>If you do work that compounds, you’ll get exponential growth. Most people who do this do it unconsciously, but it’s worth stopping to think about. Learning, for example, is an instance of this phenomenon: the more you learn about something, the easier it is to learn more. Growing an audience is another: the more fans you have, the more new fans they’ll bring you.</p><p>**如果我们做的工作有叠加效应，那么我们就会收获指数增长，**大多数在做此类工作的人都是无意识的，但这值得我们停下来认真思考。例如，学习就是这种现象的一个例子：我们对某件事了解得越多，学习更多的事情就越容易。「观众」的增长也是如此：我们的粉丝越多，他们就会为我们带来更多的新粉丝。</p><p>The trouble with exponential growth is that the curve feels flat in the beginning. It isn’t; it’s still a wonderful exponential curve. But we can’t grasp that intuitively, so we underrate exponential growth in its early stages.</p><p>指数增长的问题在于，曲线在开始时给人的感觉很平。但它不是，它仍然是一个美妙的指数曲线，只是我们无法直观地理解这一点，所以我们低估了指数增长的早期阶段。</p><p>Something that grows exponentially can become so valuable that it’s worth making an extraordinary effort to get it started. But since we underrate exponential growth early on, this too is mostly done unconsciously: people push through the initial, unrewarding phase of learning something new because they know from experience that learning new things always takes an initial push, or they grow their audience one fan at a time because they have nothing better to do. If people consciously realized they could invest in exponential growth, many more would do it.</p><p>一件可以指数增长的事可以变得非常有价值，值得我们付出特别的努力去启动。但由于我们在早期低估了指数增长，这也主要是无意识地完成的：人们在学习新事物的初始且无回报的阶段中坚持下去，因为他们从经验中知道学习新事物总是需要一个初始的推动力，或者他们一个一个地增加他们的「观众」，因为他们没有更好的事可做 —— 如果人们意识到他们可以投资于指数增长，会有更多的人去做。</p><p>Work doesn’t just happen when you’re trying to. There’s a kind of undirected thinking you do when walking or taking a shower or lying in bed that can be very powerful. By letting your mind wander a little, you’ll often solve problems you were unable to solve by frontal attack.</p><p>工作不仅仅在我们努力时发生的。当我们散步、洗澡或躺在床上时，会进行一种无明确目标的思考，这种思考可能非常有力量。<strong>通过让思绪稍微漫游一下，我们经常能够解决那些无法通过正面攻击解决的问题</strong>。</p><p>You have to be working hard in the normal way to benefit from this phenomenon, though. You can’t just walk around daydreaming. The daydreaming has to be interleaved with deliberate work that feeds it questions. [10]</p><p>然而，我们必须是在以正确的方式努力工作前提下，才能从这种现象中获益。我们不能只是四处游荡做白日梦。这种漫无目的的思考必须与有意识的工作交替进行，工作会引导我们思考问题。[10]</p><p>Everyone knows to avoid distractions at work, but it’s also important to avoid them in the other half of the cycle. When you let your mind wander, it wanders to whatever you care about most at that moment. So avoid the kind of distraction that pushes your work out of the top spot, or you’ll waste this valuable type of thinking on the distraction instead. (Exception: Don’t avoid love.)</p><p>每个人都知道在工作时要避免分心，但在周期的另一半避免分心也很重要。每当我们的思绪发散时，它会漫游向我们那一刻最关心的事情上。所以，要避免让会将工作挤出首位的事分散自己的注意力，否则我们会把这种宝贵的思考方式用在分心上（例外情况：不要回避爱情！）。</p><p>Consciously cultivate your taste in the work done in your field. Until you know which is the best and what makes it so, you don’t know what you’re aiming for.</p><p>**有意识地培养对自己领域工作的品味。**除非我们知道什么是最好的，以及是什么使它成为最好的，否则我们并不知道自己在追求什么。</p><p>And that is what you’re aiming for, because if you don’t try to be the best, you won’t even be good. This observation has been made by so many people in so many different fields that it might be worth thinking about why it’s true. </p><ul><li><p>It could be because ambition is a phenomenon where almost all the error is in one direction — where almost all the shells that miss the target miss by falling short. </p></li><li><p>Or it could be because ambition to be the best is a qualitatively different thing from ambition to be good. </p></li><li><p>Or maybe being good is simply too vague a standard.</p></li></ul><p>Probably all three are true. [11]</p><p>这就是我们所应追求的，因为如果我们不努力成为最好的，我们甚至都做不好。这一观察已经被许多不同领域的人指出了，所以这可能值得我们思考一下为什么会这样：</p><ol><li>可能是因为实现雄心壮志的途中有这样一种现象，几乎所有的错误都偏向一方 —— <strong>几乎所有未击中目标的炮弹都是落得不够远；</strong></li><li>可能是因为追求做到最好的雄心壮志与追求做好的抱负有着质的不同；</li><li>可能与「最好」不同，「好」只是一个过于模糊的标准。</li></ol><p>—— 这三个可能都是真的。[11]</p><p>Fortunately there’s a kind of economy of scale here. Though it might seem like you’d be taking on a heavy burden by trying to be the best, in practice you often end up net ahead. It’s exciting, and also strangely liberating. It simplifies things. In some ways it’s easier to try to be the best than to try merely to be good.</p><p>幸运的是，这里也存在规模经济。虽然努力做到最好可能看起来会为我们增加很大的负担，但实际上我们经常会得到净收益。这是令人兴奋的，也是一种奇妙的解放，事情被简化了 —— 在某些方面，努力做到最好比仅仅努力做好更容易。</p><p>One way to aim high is to try to make something that people will care about in a hundred years. Not because their opinions matter more than your contemporaries’, but because something that still seems good in a hundred years is more likely to be genuinely good.</p><p>追求高目标的方法之一是试图创造一些人们在一百年后还会关心的东西。并不是因为他们的观点比我们同时代的人更重要，而是因为<strong>一百年后仍然看起来不错的东西更有可能是真正好的东西。</strong></p><h3 id="五、真诚的表达自己与面对问题"><a href="#五、真诚的表达自己与面对问题" class="headerlink" title="五、真诚的表达自己与面对问题"></a>五、真诚的表达自己与面对问题</h3><p>Don’t try to work in a distinctive style. Just try to do the best job you can; you won’t be able to help doing it in a distinctive way.</p><p><strong>不要刻意尝试标新立异的工作风格</strong>，当你专注于把工作做到最好的时候，你很自然的会发现一条与众不同的路。</p><p>Style is doing things in a distinctive way without trying to. Trying to is affectation.</p><p>风格是在不刻意为之的情况下以独特的方式做事，刻意为之则是矫饰。</p><p>Affectation is in effect to pretend that someone other than you is doing the work. You adopt an impressive but fake persona, and while you’re pleased with the impressiveness, the fakeness is what shows in the work. [12]</p><p>矫饰实际上是假装工作的人不是自己，我们采用了一个令人印象深刻但虚假的人格。虽然我们可能会为给他人留下深刻印象感到满足，但工作中表现出来的是一种假人格。[12]</p><p>The temptation to be someone else is greatest for the young. They often feel like nobodies. But you never need to worry about that problem, because it’s self-solving if you work on sufficiently ambitious projects. If you succeed at an ambitious project, you’re not a nobody; you’re the person who did it. So just do the work and your identity will take care of itself.</p><p>年轻人最容易受到「成为他人」的诱惑，他们经常自认为是无名小卒。但永远不需要担心这个问题，因为如果我们持续做足够有前景的项目，这个问题就会逐渐自我消解。如果成功地完成了一个伟大的项目，我们就不是无名小卒，而是完成它的人。所以，只要工作，我们的身份就会自己变好。</p><p>“Avoid affectation” is a useful rule so far as it goes, but how would you express this idea positively? How would you say what to be, instead of what not to be? The best answer is earnest. If you’re earnest you avoid not just affectation but a whole set of similar vices.</p><p>「避免矫饰」是个有用的规则，这需要长期坚持，但我们如何用积极的方式表达自己的想法呢？我们如何说出要成为什么，而不是不要成为什么呢？最好的答案是真诚。如果我们是真诚的，那就不仅可以避免矫饰，还可以避免一整套类似的恶习。</p><p>The core of being earnest is being intellectually honest. We’re taught as children to be honest as an unselfish virtue — as a kind of sacrifice. But in fact it’s a source of power too. To see new ideas, you need an exceptionally sharp eye for the truth. You’re trying to see more truth than others have seen so far. And how can you have a sharp eye for the truth if you’re intellectually dishonest?</p><p>真诚的核心是诚实。我们从小就被教导要诚实，作为一种无私的美德 —— 作为一种牺牲。但事实上，它是一种力量的来源，要看到新的想法，我们需要对真相异常敏锐。假设我们正在试图看到比其他人到目前为止看到的更多的真相，如果我们在智力上不诚实，又怎么能对真相有敏锐的眼光呢？</p><p>One way to avoid intellectual dishonesty is to maintain a slight positive pressure in the opposite direction. Be aggressively willing to admit that you’re mistaken. Once you’ve admitted you were mistaken about something, you’re free. Till then you have to carry it. [13]</p><p>保持智力诚实（Intellectual Honesty）的一种方法是保持轻微的正压。愿意积极承认自己的错误 —— 一旦我们承认自己在某件事上犯了错误，就自由了 —— 在这之前，我们必须承担它。[13]</p><p>Another more subtle component of earnestness is informality. Informality is much more important than its grammatically negative name implies. It’s not merely the absence of something. It means focusing on what matters instead of what doesn’t.</p><p>真诚的另一个更微妙的组成部分是不拘小节。「不拘小节」比它的语法层面所暗示的要重要得多，<strong>它不仅仅意味着少做某些事，还意味着关注重要的事情，而不是无关的事情。</strong></p><p>What formality and affectation have in common is that as well as doing the work, you’re trying to seem a certain way as you’re doing it. But any energy that goes into how you seem comes out of being good. That’s one reason nerds have an advantage in doing great work: they expend little effort on seeming anything. In fact that’s basically the definition of a nerd.</p><p>拘泥于形式和矫饰的共同点是，你在做工作的同时，也试图以某种方式伪装。但任何投入到「表面功夫」中能量都会被从做重要的事情中分走。这就是为什么书呆子在做伟大的工作上有优势的一个原因：他们在表面功夫上花费的努力很小。事实上，这基本上就是书呆子的定义。</p><p>Nerds have a kind of innocent boldness that’s exactly what you need in doing great work. It’s not learned; it’s preserved from childhood. So hold onto it. Be the one who puts things out there rather than the one who sits back and offers sophisticated-sounding criticisms of them. “It’s easy to criticize” is true in the most literal sense, and the route to great work is never easy.</p><p>书呆子有一种天真的大胆，这正是你在做伟大的工作时所需要的。它不是学来的；它是从童年保留下来的，所以要保持它。<strong>成为那个把事情做出来的人，而不是坐在背后提供复杂的批评的人。</strong>「批评很容易」在最字面的意义上是真的，而取得伟大成就的路永远不容易。</p><p>There may be some jobs where it’s an advantage to be cynical and pessimistic, but if you want to do great work it’s an advantage to be optimistic, even though that means you’ll risk looking like a fool sometimes. There’s an old tradition of doing the opposite. The Old Testament says it’s better to keep quiet lest you look like a fool. But that’s advice for seeming smart. If you actually want to discover new things, it’s better to take the risk of telling people your ideas.</p><p>可能有一些工作，悲观是一个优势，但如果我们想去的杰出成就，乐观是一个优势，即便这意味着我们有时会冒看起来像一个傻瓜的风险。旧传统指导我们做相反的事，《旧约圣经》说：最好保持安静，以免看起来像一个傻瓜 —— 但这是为了看起来聪明的建议，如果我们真的想发现新的东西，最好冒险告诉人们自己的想法。</p><p>Some people are naturally earnest, and with others it takes a conscious effort. Either kind of earnestness will suffice. But I doubt it would be possible to do great work without being earnest. It’s so hard to do even if you are. You don’t have enough margin for error to accommodate the distortions introduced by being affected, intellectually dishonest, orthodox, fashionable, or cool. [14]</p><p>有些人天生就是真诚的，有些人需要有意识的努力，任何一种真诚都足够。但我怀疑，**如果没有真诚，就不可能做出伟大的工作，而且即使我们是真诚的，也很难做到。**我们没有足够的误差边际来容纳被影响、智力上的不诚实、拘泥于形式、流行或酷带来的现实扭曲。[14]</p><p>Great work is consistent not only with who did it, but with itself. It’s usually all of a piece. So if you face a decision in the middle of working on something, ask which choice is more consistent.</p><p>优秀的作品不仅与创作者保持一致，也与作品本身保持一致。通常而言，优秀的作品都是成体系的 —— 所以，如果我们在工作中面临抉择，问问自己哪个选择更有一致性。</p><p>You may have to throw things away and redo them. You won’t necessarily have to, but you have to be willing to. And that can take some effort; when there’s something you need to redo, status quo bias and laziness will combine to keep you in denial about it. To beat this ask: If I’d already made the change, would I want to revert to what I have now?</p><p>我们可能不得不放弃一些事情并重新开始，我们不一定必须这样做，但我们必须愿意这样做，这可能需要一些努力。当我们需要重做一些事情时，对维持现状的倾向性和懒惰会联合起来让我们否认这个想法。为了克服这个问题，问问自己：如果我已经做了改变，我是否想要恢复现在的状态？</p><p>Have the confidence to cut. Don’t keep something that doesn’t fit just because you’re proud of it, or because it cost you a lot of effort.</p><p>**要有放弃的信心与决心。**不要仅仅因为自己为其感到骄傲，或者花费了很多努力，就保留不合适的东西。</p><p>Indeed, in some kinds of work it’s good to strip whatever you’re doing to its essence. The result will be more concentrated; you’ll understand it better; and you won’t be able to lie to yourself about whether there’s anything real there.</p><p>实际上，在某些类型的工作中，层层剥离并探究自己正在做的事情的本质是好的。结果会更加直接明了，我们会更好地理解它，也将无法对自己撒谎，需要直面其中是否有真正重要的东西。</p><p>Mathematical elegance may sound like a mere metaphor, drawn from the arts. That’s what I thought when I first heard the term “elegant” applied to a proof. But now I suspect it’s conceptually prior — that the main ingredient in artistic elegance is mathematical elegance. At any rate it’s a useful standard well beyond math.</p><p>数学优雅（Mathematical Elegance）可能听起来像是一个纯粹的隐喻，来自艺术 —— 当我第一次听到用「优雅」这个词用来形容一个证明时，我就是这么想的。但现在我倾向于它在概念上是先行的 —— 艺术优雅的主要成分是数学优雅 —— 无论如何，这都是一个超越数学的有用标准。</p><p>Elegance can be a long-term bet, though. Laborious solutions will often have more prestige in the short term. They cost a lot of effort and they’re hard to understand, both of which impress people, at least temporarily.</p><p>然而，**优雅是一个长期的投注。**费力的解决方案在短期内通常会有更高的声望，它们需要大量的努力，而且很难理解，这两点都会让人印象深刻，但也许是暂时的。</p><p>Whereas some of the very best work will seem like it took comparatively little effort, because it was in a sense already there. It didn’t have to be built, just seen. It’s a very good sign when it’s hard to say whether you’re creating something or discovering it.</p><p>相反，完成一些最好的作品看起来好像只花费了相对较少的努力，因为它在某种意义上已经存在了，它不需要被创造，只需要被看到。<strong>当我们很难说自己是在创造某物还是在发现它时，这是一个非常好的迹象。</strong></p><p>When you’re doing work that could be seen as either creation or discovery, err on the side of discovery. Try thinking of yourself as a mere conduit through which the ideas take their natural shape.</p><p>当我们正在做的工作可以被看作是创造或发现时，请偏向于发现。试着把自己想象成一个管道，通过它，想法可以自然地形成。</p><p>(Strangely enough, one exception is the problem of choosing a problem to work on. This is usually seen as search, but in the best case it’s more like creating something. In the best case you create the field in the process of exploring it.)</p><p>（奇怪的是，选择要解决的问题这件事是一个例外。这通常被视为搜索，但在最好的情况下，它更像是创造一些东西，我们在探索过程中创造了某个领域。）</p><p>Similarly, if you’re trying to build a powerful tool, make it gratuitously unrestrictive. A powerful tool almost by definition will be used in ways you didn’t expect, so err on the side of eliminating restrictions, even if you don’t know what the benefit will be.</p><p>同样，如果我们试图构建一个强大的工具，那要让它尽可能地无限制。一个强大的工具会以我们没有预料到的方式被使用 —— 这几乎可以算作强大工具的定义，所以要倾向于消除限制，即使你不知道这样做会有什么好处。</p><p>Great work will often be tool-like in the sense of being something others build on. So it’s a good sign if you’re creating ideas that others could use, or exposing questions that others could answer. The best ideas have implications in many different areas.</p><p>伟大的作品通常会像工具一样，其他人可以基于其再构建作品。所以，如果我们正在创造其他人可以使用的想法，或者揭示出其他人可以回答的问题，那么这是一个好的迹象 —— 最好的想法在许多不同的领域都有影响。</p><p>If you express your ideas in the most general form, they’ll be truer than you intended.</p><p><strong>如果我们以最通用的形式表达自己的想法，它们会比我们预期中的更真实。</strong></p><h3 id="六、打破常规者人恒敬之"><a href="#六、打破常规者人恒敬之" class="headerlink" title="六、打破常规者人恒敬之"></a>六、打破常规者人恒敬之</h3><p>True by itself is not enough, of course. Great ideas have to be true and new. And it takes a certain amount of ability to see new ideas even once you’ve learned enough to get to one of the frontiers of knowledge.</p><p>当然，仅仅真实是不够的，<strong>伟大的想法必须是真实且新颖的</strong>。并且，即使我们已经学到足够的知识来到达知识的前沿，看到新的想法也需要一定的能力。</p><p>In English we give this ability names like originality, creativity, and imagination. And it seems reasonable to give it a separate name, because it does seem to some extent a separate skill. It’s possible to have a great deal of ability in other respects — to have a great deal of what’s often called technical ability — and yet not have much of this.</p><p>在英语中，我们给这种能力取了如原创性、创造性和想象力等名字。给它一个单独的名字似乎是合理的，因为在某种程度上它似乎是一个单独的技能。我们可能在其他方面有很高的能力 —— 很高的「技术性能力」—— 但可能没有这么多看到新想法的能力。</p><p>I’ve never liked the term “creative process.” It seems misleading. Originality isn’t a process, but a habit of mind. Original thinkers throw off new ideas about whatever they focus on, like an angle grinder throwing off sparks. They can’t help it.</p><p>我从未喜欢过「创新过程」这个词，它似乎有些误导性。原创不是一个过程，而是一种思维习惯。原创的思想家，无论他们关注的是什么，都会产生新的想法，就像角磨机抛出火花一样，没有人可以控制这种现象的发生。</p><p>If the thing they’re focused on is something they don’t understand very well, these new ideas might not be good. One of the most original thinkers I know decided to focus on dating after he got divorced. He knew roughly as much about dating as the average 15 year old, and the results were spectacularly colorful. But to see originality separated from expertise like that made its nature all the more clear.</p><p>如果一个人关注的事情是自己不太理解的事情，这些新的想法可能并不好。我认识的最具原创性的思考者之一在离婚后决定专注于约会，他对约会的了解不甚深入，大约与一般 15 岁的孩子一样，结果好得令人惊讶 —— 看到原创性与专业知识是分离的，它的本质就变得更加清晰。</p><p>I don’t know if it’s possible to cultivate originality, but there are definitely ways to make the most of however much you have. For example, you’re much more likely to have original ideas when you’re working on something. Original ideas don’t come from trying to have original ideas. They come from trying to build or understand something slightly too difficult. [15]</p><p>我不知道原创性是否可以被培养出来，但肯定有方法可以最大限度地利用自己所拥有的。例如，当我们在工作时，更有可能产生原创想法。原创想法并不来自于刻意的尝试，而是来自于尝试构建或理解稍微困难的东西。[15]</p><p>Talking or writing about the things you’re interested in is a good way to generate new ideas. When you try to put ideas into words, a missing idea creates a sort of vacuum that draws it out of you. Indeed, there’s a kind of thinking that can only be done by writing.</p><p>讨论或写作我们感兴趣的事情是产生新想法的好途径。当我们试图把想法用词语表达出来时，缺失的想法会产生一种「吸引力」，把新想法从自己身上「吸引」出来。实际上，有一种思考只能通过写作来完成。</p><p>Changing your context can help. If you visit a new place, you’ll often find you have new ideas there. The journey itself often dislodges them. But you may not have to go far to get this benefit. Sometimes it’s enough just to go for a walk. [16]</p><p>改变我们所处的环境可能有所帮助。如果我们到访一个新地方*（这里地方的定义是模糊的，不特指物理坐标）*，会发现自己在那里会产生新想法，旅行本身通常会使灵感涌现。但是，我们可能不必走得很远就能体会到这种妙处 —— 有时候，只需要去散步就足够了。[16]</p><p>It also helps to travel in topic space. You’ll have more new ideas if you explore lots of different topics, partly because it gives the angle grinder more surface area to work on, and partly because analogies are an especially fruitful source of new ideas.</p><p>了解不同的专业领域也会有所帮助。如果我们探索了许多不同的领域，会有更多新想法，这就像是给了角磨机更大的工作表面，另一部分原因则是，类比是新想法的丰富的来源。</p><p>Don’t divide your attention evenly between many topics though, or you’ll spread yourself too thin. You want to distribute it according to something more like a power law. [17] Be professionally curious about a few topics and idly curious about many more.</p><p>不过，**不要把注意力平均分配到许多领域上，**否则会分散得太薄。我们应该根据幂律分布的规则来分配它 [17] —— <strong>对少数几个主题「专业地好奇」，对更多的主题「随便地好奇」。</strong></p><p>Curiosity and originality are closely related. Curiosity feeds originality by giving it new things to work on. But the relationship is closer than that. Curiosity is itself a kind of originality; it’s roughly to questions what originality is to answers. And since questions at their best are a big component of answers, curiosity at its best is a creative force.</p><p>好奇心和原创性密切相关。表面上看，好奇心通过给原创性提供新事物来喂养它，但两者之间的关系比这更紧密 —— 好奇心本身就是一种原创性，它大致可以被视为问题的原创性，和答案的原创性一样。而且，既然在最理想的情况下，问题在答案中的权重很高，那么同样在最理想的情况下，好奇心就是创造力的一种。</p><p>Having new ideas is a strange game, because it usually consists of seeing things that were right under your nose. Once you’ve seen a new idea, it tends to seem obvious. Why did no one think of this before?</p><p>拥有新想法是一种奇怪的游戏，因为通常它还包括看到那些就在我们眼前的东西。一旦我们看到一个新的想法，它往往显得很明显 —— 为什么之前没有人想到这个？</p><p>When an idea seems simultaneously novel and obvious, it’s probably a good one.</p><p><strong>当一个想法看起来既新颖又显而易见时，它可能是个好主意。</strong></p><p>Seeing something obvious sounds easy. And yet empirically having new ideas is hard. What’s the source of this apparent contradiction? It’s that seeing the new idea usually requires you to change the way you look at the world. We see the world through models that both help and constrain us. When you fix a broken model, new ideas become obvious. But noticing and fixing a broken model is hard. That’s how new ideas can be both obvious and yet hard to discover: they’re easy to see after you do something hard.</p><p>看到显而易见的东西听起来很容易，然而，从经验上看，产生新想法是困难的，这个明显矛盾的源头是什么呢？那就是看到新的想法通常需要我们改变看世界的方式。我们通过模型看世界，这些模型既帮助着我们，也限制着我们，在修复有问题的世界模型的过程中，新的想法会变得显而易见，但注意到并修复一个有问题的模型是困难的，这就是新的想法既明显又难以发现的原因。在你做了一些困难的事情之后，它们就容易被看到。</p><p>One way to discover broken models is to be stricter than other people. Broken models of the world leave a trail of clues where they bash against reality. Most people don’t want to see these clues. It would be an understatement to say that they’re attached to their current model; it’s what they think in; so they’ll tend to ignore the trail of clues left by its breakage, however conspicuous it may seem in retrospect.</p><p>发现有问题的世界模型的方法之一是比其他人更严谨。有问题的模型在与现实发生冲突时会留下一些迹象，但大多数人不想看到这些迹象。保守的说法是，人们倾向于依赖于他们当前的模型，这就是他们的思维方式，所以他们倾向于忽略模型出现问题时留下的线索，无论这在反思中看起来多么明显。</p><p>To find new ideas you have to seize on signs of breakage instead of looking away. That’s what Einstein did. He was able to see the wild implications of Maxwell’s equations not so much because he was looking for new ideas as because he was stricter.</p><p>要找到新的想法，我们必须抓住这些迹象，而不是避而不见。这就是爱因斯坦做的，他能看到麦克斯韦方程的伟大意义，不是因为他在寻找新的想法，而是因为他更严谨。</p><p>The other thing you need is a willingness to break rules. Paradoxical as it sounds, if you want to fix your model of the world, it helps to be the sort of person who’s comfortable breaking rules. From the point of view of the old model, which everyone including you initially shares, the new model usually breaks at least implicit rules.</p><p>**我们所要做的另一件事是愿意打破规则。**虽然这听起来矛盾，但如果我们想修正自己的世界模型，那么成为一个习惯于打破规则的人会有所帮助。从旧模型的观点来看，这个模型通常至少会违反隐含的规则，包括我们自己最初也是这么认为的。</p><p>Few understand the degree of rule-breaking required, because new ideas seem much more conservative once they succeed. They seem perfectly reasonable once you’re using the new model of the world they brought with them. But they didn’t at the time; it took the greater part of a century for the heliocentric model to be generally accepted, even among astronomers, because it felt so wrong.</p><p>很少有人了解打破规则所需的程度，因为新的想法在成功后看起来更保守。一旦我们使用了新的世界模型，它们会看起来完全合理，但开始的时候并不是这样的，地心模型在天文学家中被普遍接受甚至都花了近一个世纪，在这期间，所有人都觉得它错的离谱。</p><p>Indeed, if you think about it, a good new idea has to seem bad to most people, or someone would have already explored it. So what you’re looking for is ideas that seem crazy, but the right kind of crazy. How do you recognize these? You can’t with certainty. Often ideas that seem bad are bad. But ideas that are the right kind of crazy tend to be exciting; they’re rich in implications; whereas ideas that are merely bad tend to be depressing.</p><p>实际上，如果我们思考一下会发现，一个好的新想法必须对大多数人来说看起来是坏的，否则就已经有人探索过了。所以**我们在寻找的是那些看起来疯狂，但是正确类别的疯狂想法。**我们如何识别他们呢？不能确定。通常看起来不好的想法就是不好的，但是，正确类别的疯狂想法往往是令人兴奋的，它们富有意蕴，而单纯的坏想法往往会让人感到沮丧。</p><p>There are two ways to be comfortable breaking rules: to enjoy breaking them, and to be indifferent to them. I call these two cases being aggressively and passively independent-minded.</p><p><strong>有两种方式可以让我们自然而然地打破规则：享受打破规则本身，或干脆无视规则 —— 我将它们分别称为积极和被动独立思考。</strong></p><p>The aggressively independent-minded are the naughty ones. Rules don’t merely fail to stop them; breaking rules gives them additional energy. For this sort of person, delight at the sheer audacity of a project sometimes supplies enough activation energy to get it started.</p><p>积极独立思考的是那些叛逆的人。规则不仅无法阻止他们，打破规则还会给他们额外的能量。对这类人来说，一个项目的纯粹胆大有时就可以提供足够的「激活能量」让它启动。</p><p>The other way to break rules is not to care about them, or perhaps even to know they exist. This is why novices and outsiders often make new discoveries; their ignorance of a field’s assumptions acts as a source of temporary passive independent-mindedness. Aspies also seem to have a kind of immunity to conventional beliefs. Several I know say that this helps them to have new ideas.</p><p>打破规则的另一种方式是不关心甚至不知道它们的存在 —— 这就是为什么新手和外行人经常做出新发现，他们对所在领域既有假设的无知可以作为一种暂时的被动独立思考的来源。自闭症患者似乎也对常规信条有着免疫力，我认识的几个人说这帮助他们有新的想法。</p><p>Strictness plus rule-breaking sounds like a strange combination. In popular culture they’re opposed. But popular culture has a broken model in this respect. It implicitly assumes that issues are trivial ones, and in trivial matters strictness and rule-breaking are opposed. But in questions that really matter, only rule-breakers can be truly strict.</p><p>「严谨 + 打破规则」听起来像是一个奇怪的组合。在主流文化中，他们是对立的，但在这方面，主流文化的模型是有问题的，它默认假设问题都是琐碎的，而在琐碎的事情中，严谨和打破规则确实是对立的，但<strong>在真正重要的问题中，只有打破规则的人才是真正严谨的。</strong></p><p>An overlooked idea often doesn’t lose till the semifinals. You do see it, subconsciously, but then another part of your subconscious shoots it down because it would be too weird, too risky, too much work, too controversial. This suggests an exciting possibility: if you could turn off such filters, you could see more new ideas.</p><p>一个被主流文化忽视的想法通常直到半决赛才败下阵来。我们在潜意识中看到了它，然而潜意识的另一部分会击败它，因为它太奇怪、太冒险、太麻烦、太有争议。但这隐含了一个令人兴奋的可能性：我们如果能关闭这些过滤器，就能看到更多的新想法。</p><p>One way to do that is to ask what would be good ideas for someone else to explore. Then your subconscious won’t shoot them down to protect you.</p><p>做到这一点的方式之一是问自己：什么是别人认为的好想法？这样我们的潜意识就不会为了自我保护而否决他们。</p><p>You could also discover overlooked ideas by working in the other direction: by starting from what’s obscuring them. Every cherished but mistaken principle is surrounded by a dead zone of valuable ideas that are unexplored because they contradict it.</p><p>我们也可以从掩盖它们的事物着手，来发现被忽视的想法。每个被珍视的错误原则周围，都存在一片有价值但因为它们与原则相矛盾而未被探索的想法的栖息地。</p><p>Religions are collections of cherished but mistaken principles. So anything that can be described either literally or metaphorically as a religion will have valuable unexplored ideas in its shadow. Copernicus and Darwin both made discoveries of this type. [18]</p><p>宗教是被珍视但错误原则的集合。所以无论是字面意义上或隐喻地，任何被描述为宗教的东西的阴影之下都存在有价值的但未被探索的想法，哥白尼和达尔文都做出了此类发现。[18]</p><p>What are people in your field religious about, in the sense of being too attached to some principle that might not be as self-evident as they think? What becomes possible if you discard it?</p><p><strong>在我们所在的领域，人们对什么规则过分依赖，以至于它们可能不像公认的那般可以自证其是？如果我们抛弃这个原则，会有什么可能性？</strong></p><p>People show much more originality in solving problems than in deciding which problems to solve. Even the smartest can be surprisingly conservative when deciding what to work on. People who’d never dream of being fashionable in any other way get sucked into working on fashionable problems.</p><p>人们在解决问题上所表现出的原创性远超在决定要解决哪些问题上。即使是最聪明的人，在决定要做什么时也可能惊人地保守，那些在其他任何方面都不会想要赶时髦的人也会被吸入到处理「时兴问题」的漩涡中。</p><p>One reason people are more conservative when choosing problems than solutions is that problems are bigger bets. A problem could occupy you for years, while exploring a solution might only take days. But even so I think most people are too conservative. They’re not merely responding to risk, but to fashion as well. Unfashionable problems are undervalued.</p><p>问题需要我们下大赌注，这也是人们选择问题比解决问题更保守的原因之一。一个问题可能伴随我们好几年的时间，而探索一个解决方案可能只需要几天。但即便如此，我认为大多数人都过于保守，他们不仅仅是在回避风险，也在迎合潮流，不流行的问题被低估了。</p><p>One of the most interesting kinds of unfashionable problem is the problem that people think has been fully explored, but hasn’t. Great work often takes something that already exists and shows its latent potential. Durer and Watt both did this. So if you’re interested in a field that others think is tapped out, don’t let their skepticism deter you. People are often wrong about this.</p><p>最有趣的一类不流行问题是那些人们认为已经完全探索过，但实际上并没有的。**杰出的成就往往源于已经存在的东西，但问题发现者深入探索并展现了其更多潜力，**杜勒尔和瓦特都做到了这一点。所以，如果我们对别人认为已经被充分探索的领域感兴趣，不要让他们的怀疑阻挡我们，人们往往会在这方面犯错。</p><p>Working on an unfashionable problem can be very pleasing. There’s no hype or hurry. Opportunists and critics are both occupied elsewhere. The existing work often has an old-school solidity. And there’s a satisfying sense of economy in cultivating ideas that would otherwise be wasted.</p><p>解决不流行的问题可能会非常愉快，工作过程中没有炒作或忙慌。机会主义者和批评者都在别处忙碌，这时我们的工作往往有一种气定神闲的稳定，在努力「培育」这些「否则会被浪费」的想法时，有一种令人满足的经济感。</p><p>But the most common type of overlooked problem is not explicitly unfashionable in the sense of being out of fashion. It just doesn’t seem to matter as much as it actually does. How do you find these? By being self-indulgent — by letting your curiosity have its way, and tuning out, at least temporarily, the little voice in your head that says you should only be working on “important” problems.</p><p>但最常见的被忽视的问题并不是明确地不流行，而是它们并未过时，只是似乎没有它实际上那么重要。我们怎么找到这些呢？通过自我放纵 —— 通过让自己的好奇心有其自由发挥的空间，至少暂时地屏蔽自己脑中那个说我们只应该在「重要」问题上工作的小声音。</p><p>You do need to work on important problems, but almost everyone is too conservative about what counts as one. And if there’s an important but overlooked problem in your neighborhood, it’s probably already on your subconscious radar screen. So try asking yourself: if you were going to take a break from “serious” work to work on something just because it would be really interesting, what would you do? The answer is probably more important than it seems.</p><p>我们确实需要将精力放在重要的问题上，但几乎每个人在评价什么算重要问题时都过于保守。而且，如果我们周围有一个重要但被忽视的问题，它可能已经在我们的潜意识雷达中了。所以，试着问自己：**如果我要从「严肃」的工作中抽出时间，只是因为这会非常有趣，我会做什么？**答案可能比看起来更重要。</p><p>Originality in choosing problems seems to matter even more than originality in solving them. That’s what distinguishes the people who discover whole new fields. So what might seem to be merely the initial step — deciding what to work on — is in a sense the key to the whole game.</p><p>**选择问题的原创性似乎比解决问题的原创性更重要，这是区分那些发现全新领域的人的关键点。**所以，可能看起来只是初步步骤的东西 —— 决定要做什么 —— 在某种意义上是整个游戏的关键。</p><p>Few grasp this. One of the biggest misconceptions about new ideas is about the ratio of question to answer in their composition. People think big ideas are answers, but often the real insight was in the question.</p><p>很少有人能理解这一点。关于新想法的最大的误解之一是关于他们的组成中问题与答案的比例，人们认为重要的部分是答案，但往往真正的洞察在于问题。</p><p>Part of the reason we underrate questions is the way they’re used in schools. In schools they tend to exist only briefly before being answered, like unstable particles. But a really good question can be much more than that. A really good question is a partial discovery. How do new species arise? Is the force that makes objects fall to earth the same as the one that keeps planets in their orbits? By even asking such questions you were already in excitingly novel territory.</p><p>我们低估问题的一部分原因是学校的教育方式。在学校里，问题往往只在被解决之前存在一段很短的时间，就像不稳定粒子一样。但一个真正好的问题可以是更多的东西，一个真正好的问题是发现的一部分：新物种是如何产生的？让物体向地球坠落的力量和让行星保持在它们轨道上的力量是同一个吗？通过甚至提出这样的问题，我们已经进入了令人兴奋的新领域。</p><p>Unanswered questions can be uncomfortable things to carry around with you. But the more you’re carrying, the greater the chance of noticing a solution — or perhaps even more excitingly, noticing that two unanswered questions are the same.</p><p>未解决的问题与我们如影随形，会让我们感到负担。但我们带着的问题越多，发现解决方案的机会就越大 —— 或者可能更令人兴奋的是，发现两个未回答的问题是同一个。</p><p>Sometimes you carry a question for a long time. Great work often comes from returning to a question you first noticed years before — in your childhood, even — and couldn’t stop thinking about. People talk a lot about the importance of keeping your youthful dreams alive, but it’s just as important to keep your youthful questions alive. [19]</p><p>有时候一个问题会伴随我们很长时间。杰出的成就往往出自我们多年前 —— 甚至我们的童年同期 —— 首次注意到的，而且无法停止思考的问题。人们经常谈论保持自己年轻时梦想活跃的重要性，但保持年轻时问题的活跃同样重要。[19]</p><p>This is one of the places where actual expertise differs most from the popular picture of it. In the popular picture, experts are certain. But actually the more puzzled you are, the better, so long as (a) the things you’re puzzled about matter, and (b) no one else understands them either.</p><p>专业知识的实际形态与大众印象最大的区别之一是，**在大众印象中，专家们是胸有成竹的，但实际上，我们越是困惑，越好，**只要（a）我们困惑的事情是重要的，并且（b）没有其他人也理解它们。</p><p>Think about what’s happening at the moment just before a new idea is discovered. Often someone with sufficient expertise is puzzled about something. Which means that originality consists partly of puzzlement — of confusion! You have to be comfortable enough with the world being full of puzzles that you’re willing to see them, but not so comfortable that you don’t want to solve them. [20]</p><p>想想新想法被发现的那一刻之前所发生的事，通常情况下，是一个具有足够专业知识的人对某事感到困惑，这意味着困惑是原创性的一部分 —— 混乱！我们必须愿意看到世界充满谜团，对此感到舒适，但也不能那么舒适，以至于不想解决它们。[20]</p><p>It’s a great thing to be rich in unanswered questions. And this is one of those situations where the rich get richer, because the best way to acquire new questions is to try answering existing ones. Questions don’t just lead to answers, but also to more questions.</p><p>拥有很多未解答的问题是一件很棒的事。这也是那些富有的人会变得更富的原因之一，<strong>获得新问题的最好方法是尝试回答现有的问题，问题不仅导向答案，而且也导向更多的问题。</strong></p><p>The best questions grow in the answering. You notice a thread protruding from the current paradigm and try pulling on it, and it just gets longer and longer. So don’t require a question to be obviously big before you try answering it. You can rarely predict that. It’s hard enough even to notice the thread, let alone to predict how much will unravel if you pull on it.</p><p>**最好的问题会在被回答的过程中成长。**我们注意到当前范式中一条显眼的线索，并试图拉扯它，它就会变得越来越长。所以，我们在试图回答问题之前，不要苛求问题的「大」是明确的，我们很少能预测到这一点，仅仅注意到线索就已经很难了，更不用说预测如果我们拉扯它，会有多少东西随之而来。</p><p>It’s better to be promiscuously curious — to pull a little bit on a lot of threads, and see what happens. Big things start small. The initial versions of big things were often just experiments, or side projects, or talks, which then grew into something bigger. So start lots of small things.</p><p>最好的方法是保持广泛的好奇心 —— 在许多线索上都稍微拉一拉，看看会发生什么。大事物开始时都很小，它们的初始版本通常只是实验、副项目或者演讲，然后逐渐发展成更大的事物 —— 所以，我们应该开始着手做很多小事情。</p><p>Being prolific is underrated. The more different things you try, the greater the chance of discovering something new. Understand, though, that trying lots of things will mean trying lots of things that don’t work. You can’t have a lot of good ideas without also having a lot of bad ones. [21]</p><p>**高产的作用是被低估的。**我们尝试的事情越多，发现新事物的机会就越大。然而，要知道，尝试很多事也将意味着尝试很多无用的事，我们不能只有很多好主意而没有同样多的坏主意。[21]</p><p>Though it sounds more responsible to begin by studying everything that’s been done before, you’ll learn faster and have more fun by trying stuff. And you’ll understand previous work better when you do look at it. So err on the side of starting. Which is easier when starting means starting small; those two ideas fit together like two puzzle pieces.</p><p>当我们进入一个领域时，虽然从学习前人的工作成果开始听起来更负责任，但通过尝试，我们会学得更快，也会收获更多的乐趣，而当我们去看前人的工作时，也会更好地理解它们。所以，在初始阶段不要害怕犯错，与此同时，这也意味着我们从小事着手更加容易，这两个想法就像两片相邻的拼图片一般契合。</p><p>How do you get from starting small to doing something great? By making successive versions. Great things are almost always made in successive versions. You start with something small and evolve it, and the final version is both cleverer and more ambitious than anything you could have planned.</p><p>我们如何从小事开始做出伟大的事情？通过做有连续性的事。伟大的事业几乎总是在一系列连续的工作中被成就的。我们从一些小事开始，逐渐发展它，最后的版本既比我们可能计划的任何东西更好，也更有想象空间。</p><p>It’s particularly useful to make successive versions when you’re making something for people — to get an initial version in front of them quickly, and then evolve it based on their response.</p><p>当我们为人们做东西时，制作连续的版本特别有用 —— 快速地将初始版本呈现给他们，然后根据他们的反应进行演变。</p><p>Begin by trying the simplest thing that could possibly work. Surprisingly often, it does. If it doesn’t, this will at least get you started.</p><p><strong>试试可能行得通的最简单的东西。出乎意料地，它经常会是有用的，如果没有，至少这会让我们启程。</strong></p><p>Don’t try to cram too much new stuff into any one version. There are names for doing this with the first version (taking too long to ship) and the second (the second system effect), but these are both merely instances of a more general principle.</p><p>不要试图在任何一个版本中塞进太多的新东西。对此有一些对应的名称，对第一个版本来说是呈现（delivery）花费太长时间，对第二个版本来说是第二系统效应，但这些都只是更具一般性原则的例子。</p><p>An early version of a new project will sometimes be dismissed as a toy. It’s a good sign when people do this. That means it has everything a new idea needs except scale, and that tends to follow. [22]</p><p>新项目的早期版本有时会被贬低为玩具。当人们这么做时，这是个好兆头，这意味着它具备新思想所需要的一切，只是缺乏规模，而那往往会随之而来。[22]</p><p>The alternative to starting with something small and evolving it is to plan in advance what you’re going to do. And planning does usually seem the more responsible choice. It sounds more organized to say “we’re going to do x and then y and then z” than “we’re going to try x and see what happens.” And it is more organized; it just doesn’t work as well.</p><p>从小发展的另一种选择是事先计划我们要做的事情。计划通常看起来是更负责任的选择，说「我们要做 x，然后做 y，然后做 z」听起来比「我们要试试 x，看看会发生什么」似乎更有组织，它确实更有组织，只是效果不那么好。</p><p>Planning per se isn’t good. It’s sometimes necessary, but it’s a necessary evil — a response to unforgiving conditions. It’s something you have to do because you’re working with inflexible media, or because you need to coordinate the efforts of a lot of people. If you keep projects small and use flexible media, you don’t have to plan as much, and your designs can evolve instead.</p><p>计划本身并不好，但有时候它是必要的，只是是一种必要的恶 —— 对无情条件的反应。我们必须这么做，因为我们正在使用不灵活的媒介，或者因为我们需要协调很多人的努力，如果我们保持项目小而使用灵活的媒介，就不必计划那么多，我们的设计可以逐步演变。</p><p>Take as much risk as you can afford. In an efficient market, risk is proportionate to reward, so don’t look for certainty, but for a bet with high expected value. If you’re not failing occasionally, you’re probably being too conservative.</p><p>尽可能承担我们负担得起的风险。**在有效市场中，风险与回报成比例，所以不要寻求确定性，而要寻找高期望价值的赌注。**如果我们不失败，偶尔可能是因为过于保守。</p><p>Though conservatism is usually associated with the old, it’s the young who tend to make this mistake. Inexperience makes them fear risk, but it’s when you’re young that you can afford the most.</p><p>虽然保守主义通常是老年人的代名词，但年轻人更容易犯这个错误。无经验让他们害怕风险，但实际上，我们年轻的时候承受得起的风险最大。</p><p>Even a project that fails can be valuable. In the process of working on it, you’ll have crossed territory few others have seen, and encountered questions few others have asked. And there’s probably no better source of questions than the ones you encounter in trying to do something slightly too hard.</p><p>即使一个项目失败了，也可以是有价值的。因为在处理它的过程中，我们会穿过很少有人见过的领域，遇到很少有人提出的问题。<strong>试图做一些稍微难一点的事情，在这个过程中遇到的问题可能是全新问题的最好来源。</strong></p><p>Use the advantages of youth when you have them, and the advantages of age once you have those. The advantages of youth are energy, time, optimism, and freedom. The advantages of age are knowledge, efficiency, money, and power. With effort you can acquire some of the latter when young and keep some of the former when old.</p><p>在我们有年轻人的优势时，使用它们，一旦我们有了有经验的优势，就使用那些。<strong>年轻人的优势是精力、时间、乐观和自由，有经验的优势是知识、效率、金钱和权力 —— 努力工作，我们可以在年轻时获取一些后者，并在经验渐长时保持一些前者。</strong></p><p>The old also have the advantage of knowing which advantages they have. The young often have them without realizing it. The biggest is probably time. The young have no idea how rich they are in time. The best way to turn this time to advantage is to use it in slightly frivolous ways: to learn about something you don’t need to know about, just out of curiosity, or to try building something just because it would be cool, or to become freakishly good at something.</p><p>有经验的人的另一个优势是知道自己有哪些优势。年轻人经常意识不到自己所拥有的优势 —— 最大的可能性来自时间，而年轻人对他们在时间上的富足没有任何概念。利用这个时间的最佳方式是以「略微任性」的方式来使用它：只是出于好奇心而去学习我们不需要知道的东西，或者只是因为一件事很酷而试图去建造一些东西，或者让自己变得非常擅长某事。</p><p>That “slightly” is an important qualification. Spend time lavishly when you’re young, but don’t simply waste it. There’s a big difference between doing something you worry might be a waste of time and doing something you know for sure will be. The former is at least a bet, and possibly a better one than you think. [23]</p><p>「略微」是一个重要的修饰词。当我们年轻的时候，可以挥霍时间，但不要简单地浪费它。做一些我们「担心可能是」浪费时间的事情和「确定会」浪费时间的事情之间有很大的区别 —— 前者至少是一次赌注，结果可能比我们认为的更好。[23]</p><p>The most subtle advantage of youth, or more precisely of inexperience, is that you’re seeing everything with fresh eyes. When your brain embraces an idea for the first time, sometimes the two don’t fit together perfectly. Usually the problem is with your brain, but occasionally it’s with the idea. A piece of it sticks out awkwardly and jabs you when you think about it. People who are used to the idea have learned to ignore it, but you have the opportunity not to. [24]</p><p><strong>年轻，或者说无经验的最微妙的优势，就是我们用全新的眼光看待一切</strong>。当我们的大脑第一次接受一个想法时，有时两者并不完全匹配，但通常问题出在我们的大脑上，偶尔在想法上。想法中的一部分突兀地冒出来，在我们思考时刺痛自己，习惯了这个感觉的人已经学会忽视它，但我们有机会不这样做。[24]</p><p>So when you’re learning about something for the first time, pay attention to things that seem wrong or missing. You’ll be tempted to ignore them, since there’s a 99% chance the problem is with you. And you may have to set aside your misgivings temporarily to keep progressing. But don’t forget about them. When you’ve gotten further into the subject, come back and check if they’re still there. If they’re still viable in the light of your present knowledge, they probably represent an undiscovered idea.</p><p>所以，当我们第一次学习某件事时，要注意那些似乎错误或缺失的东西。我们会被诱惑忽视它们，认为有 99% 的可能性问题在自己身上，并且我们可能必须暂时放下自己的疑虑以继续前进，但不要忘记它们 —— 当我们深入到领域中，再回来检查它们是否依然存在，如果在我们现在的知识水平下，它们仍然是可行的，那么它们可能代表着一个未被发现的想法。</p><p>One of the most valuable kinds of knowledge you get from experience is to know what you don’t have to worry about. The young know all the things that could matter, but not their relative importance. So they worry equally about everything, when they should worry much more about a few things and hardly at all about the rest.</p><p>**经验给我们带来的最有价值的知识之一是知道我们不必担心什么。**年轻人知道所有可能的事，但不知道它们的相对重要性，所以他们对所有事情都一样担忧，而我们应该只对几件事情担忧，对其他的事情几乎不需要担忧。</p><p>But what you don’t know is only half the problem with inexperience. The other half is what you do know that ain’t so. You arrive at adulthood with your head full of nonsense — bad habits you’ve acquired and false things you’ve been taught — and you won’t be able to do great work till you clear away at least the nonsense in the way of whatever type of work you want to do.</p><p>但我们的无知只是缺乏经验问题的其中一半，另一半是我们所熟知的那些错误的东西。我们带着满脑子毫无意义的东西进入成年期 —— 已经养成的坏习惯和被教导的错误观念 —— 在清除了至少是在自己想做的工作的路上的噪声前，我们无法取得杰出成就。</p><p>Much of the nonsense left in your head is left there by schools. We’re so used to schools that we unconsciously treat going to school as identical with learning, but in fact schools have all sorts of strange qualities that warp our ideas about learning and thinking.</p><p>我们头脑中许多无意义的噪声都是学校留下的。我们习惯于学校，以至于我们无意识地将「去学校」当作「学习」，但实际上学校有各种奇怪的价值观，扭曲了我们对学习和思考的观念。</p><p>For example, schools induce passivity. Since you were a small child, there was an authority at the front of the class telling all of you what you had to learn and then measuring whether you did. But neither classes nor tests are intrinsic to learning; they’re just artifacts of the way schools are usually designed.</p><p>例如，学校会引导我们进行被动学习。当我们还是小孩子的时候，课堂便利用其权威告诉我们所有人必须学习什么，然后测试我们是否做到了，但是课堂和考试并不是学习的本质，他们只是学校通常设计的产物。</p><p>The sooner you overcome this passivity, the better. If you’re still in school, try thinking of your education as your project, and your teachers as working for you rather than vice versa. That may seem a stretch, but it’s not merely some weird thought experiment. It’s the truth economically, and in the best case it’s the truth intellectually as well. The best teachers don’t want to be your bosses. They’d prefer it if you pushed ahead, using them as a source of advice, rather than being pulled by them through the material.</p><p>尽快克服这种被动性越好。如果还在学校，那就试着把教育当作自己的项目，老师是在为自己工作，而不是反过来。这可能看起来有些牵强，但这不仅仅是一种特别的思维实验，从经济上说，这是真的，在最好的情况下，从知识上说也是真的，最好的老师不想做我们的老板。他们宁愿我们推进，用他们作为一个建议的来源，而不是被他们通过材料拉动。</p><p>Schools also give you a misleading impression of what work is like. In school they tell you what the problems are, and they’re almost always soluble using no more than you’ve been taught so far. In real life you have to figure out what the problems are, and you often don’t know if they’re soluble at all.</p><p>学校也给我们工作是什么样的误导性印象。在学校里，他们告诉我们问题是什么，而且几乎总是可以使用我们到目前为止学到的东西来解决。在现实生活中，我们必须找出问题是什么，而且往往不知道它们是否可以解决。</p><p>But perhaps the worst thing schools do to you is train you to win by hacking the test. You can’t do great work by doing that. You can’t trick God. So stop looking for that kind of shortcut. The way to beat the system is to focus on problems and solutions that others have overlooked, not to skimp on the work itself.</p><p>但是学校教导我们最糟糕的事情可能就是训练我们通过成为「小镇做题家（hacking the test）」来胜出比赛。我们不能通过这样做取得杰出成就，所以要停止寻找此类捷径，击败系统的方法是专注于其他人忽视的问题和解决方案，而不是偷工减料。</p><p>Don’t think of yourself as dependent on some gatekeeper giving you a “big break.” Even if this were true, the best way to get it would be to focus on doing good work rather than chasing influential people.</p><p><strong>不要依赖某个「看门人」给自己一个「大机会」，即使这是真的，得到它的最好方式是专注于做好工作，而不是追逐有影响力的人。</strong></p><p>And don’t take rejection by committees to heart. The qualities that impress admissions officers and prize committees are quite different from those required to do great work. The decisions of selection committees are only meaningful to the extent that they’re part of a feedback loop, and very few are.</p><p>也不要把「委员会」的拒绝放在心上。让招生官员和管理委员会印象深刻的品质与做出伟大工作所需的品质完全不同。选择管理层的决定只有在它们是反馈循环的一部分时才有意义，而很少有决定是这样的</p><p>People new to a field will often copy existing work. There’s nothing inherently bad about that. There’s no better way to learn how something works than by trying to reproduce it. Nor does copying necessarily make your work unoriginal. Originality is the presence of new ideas, not the absence of old ones.</p><p>在一个领域里，新手经常会复制已有的工作。这本身并没有什么错，试图复制一件事是学习它是如何运作的最好方式，复制并不一定会使我们的工作失去原创性，<strong>原创性在于新想法的产生，而不是旧想法的缺失。</strong></p><p>There’s a good way to copy and a bad way. If you’re going to copy something, do it openly instead of furtively, or worse still, unconsciously. This is what’s meant by the famously misattributed phrase “Great artists steal.” The really dangerous kind of copying, the kind that gives copying a bad name, is the kind that’s done without realizing it, because you’re nothing more than a train running on tracks laid down by someone else. But at the other extreme, copying can be a sign of superiority rather than subordination. [25]</p><p>有好的复制方式，也有坏的。如果我们要复制一些东西，那么公开地去做，而不是偷偷摸摸，或者更糟糕，无意识地去做，这就是那句被误传的名言「伟大的艺术家都是窃贼」的含义。真正危险的复制类型，即给复制带来坏名声的那种，就是我们在不知不觉中做的复制，在这种情况下，我们只不过是在别人铺设的轨道上行驶的列车，但在另一个极端，<strong>复制可以是一种超越的标志，而不是从属关系。</strong>[25]</p><p>In many fields it’s almost inevitable that your early work will be in some sense based on other people’s. Projects rarely arise in a vacuum. They’re usually a reaction to previous work. When you’re first starting out, you don’t have any previous work; if you’re going to react to something, it has to be someone else’s. Once you’re established, you can react to your own. But while the former gets called derivative and the latter doesn’t, structurally the two cases are more similar than they seem.</p><p>在很多领域里，我们早期的工作几乎不可避免地在某种程度上是基于他人的。项目很少是凭空产生的，它们通常是对已有工作的反应：刚开始的时候，我们自己没有任何已有工作，如果我们要对某事有反应，那必然是别人的工作，一旦我们有了稳定的地位，就可以对自己的工作有所反应。尽管前者被认为派生的，后者不被认为派生的，但从结构上看，两种情况比看起来更相似。</p><p>Oddly enough, the very novelty of the most novel ideas sometimes makes them seem at first to be more derivative than they are. New discoveries often have to be conceived initially as variations of existing things, even by their discoverers, because there isn’t yet the conceptual vocabulary to express them.</p><p>有时候，足够新颖的、最新奇的想法一开始看起来更加像派生出来的。在最初构想阶段，新的发现通常需要被视为现有事物的变形，甚至他们的发现者也是这样做的，因为还没有对应的概念以及词汇来描述它们。</p><p>There are definitely some dangers to copying, though. One is that you’ll tend to copy old things — things that were in their day at the frontier of knowledge, but no longer are.</p><p>复制确实有些危险，其中之一是倾向于复制旧东西 —— 那些在过去是知识前沿，但现在已经不再是的东西。</p><p>And when you do copy something, don’t copy every feature of it. Some will make you ridiculous if you do. Don’t copy the manner of an eminent 50 year old professor if you’re 18, for example, or the idiom of a Renaissance poem hundreds of years later.</p><p>当我们复制某件事时，不要复制它的所有特性。如果我们复制某些部分的话，会看起来很荒谬。例如，我们 18 岁时不能复制一位 50 岁杰出教授的举止，或者几百年前文艺复兴时期诗歌的习语。</p><p>Some of the features of things you admire are flaws they succeeded despite. Indeed, the features that are easiest to imitate are the most likely to be the flaws.</p><p>我们所崇拜事物的一些特性是「尽管他们存在缺陷但依然取得成功的」。但事实上，最容易模仿的特性最有可能是缺陷。</p><p>This is particularly true for behavior. Some talented people are jerks, and this sometimes makes it seem to the inexperienced that being a jerk is part of being talented. It isn’t; being talented is merely how they get away with it.</p><p>对于行为尤其如此。一些有才华的人是混蛋，这有时使得无经验的人认为做混蛋是才华的一部分，并不是，才华只是他们得以逃脱的方式。</p><p>One of the most powerful kinds of copying is to copy something from one field into another. History is so full of chance discoveries of this type that it’s probably worth giving chance a hand by deliberately learning about other kinds of work. You can take ideas from quite distant fields if you let them be metaphors.</p><p>最有力的复制类型之一是从一个领域复制到另一个领域。历史上充满了这种类型的偶然发现，所以我们值得有意地去学习其他类型的工作，从而为这类偶然性提供帮助。我们可以从毫不相干的领域中获取想法，如果我们能够让它们成为灵感来源的话。</p><p>Negative examples can be as inspiring as positive ones. In fact you can sometimes learn more from things done badly than from things done well; sometimes it only becomes clear what’s needed when it’s missing.</p><p>负面的例子可能和积极的例子一样启发人。事实上，**我们有时可以从做得糟糕的事情中学到比从做得好的事情中更多的东西，**有时只有当它缺失时，才能清楚地看出完满需要什么。</p><p>If a lot of the best people in your field are collected in one place, it’s usually a good idea to visit for a while. It will increase your ambition, and also, by showing you that these people are human, increase your self-confidence. [26]</p><p>**如果我们所在领域的许多最好的人都集中在一个地方，那去那里待一段时间通常是个好主意。**这会增加我们的斗志，同时，通过向我们展示这些优秀的人都是人，增加我们的自信心。[26]</p><p>If you’re earnest you’ll probably get a warmer welcome than you might expect. Most people who are very good at something are happy to talk about it with anyone who’s genuinely interested. If they’re really good at their work, then they probably have a hobbyist’s interest in it, and hobbyists always want to talk about their hobbies.</p><p>如果我们是真诚的，可能会受到比自己期望的更热烈的欢迎。大多数在某件事上非常出色的人都很乐意和任何真正有兴趣的人谈论它 —— 如果他们真的很擅长自己的工作，那么他们可能对它存在一种类似业余爱好者般的心理，业余爱好者总是想谈论他们的爱好。</p><p>It may take some effort to find the people who are really good, though. Doing great work has such prestige that in some places, particularly universities, there’s a polite fiction that everyone is engaged in it. And that is far from true. People within universities can’t say so openly, but the quality of the work being done in different departments varies immensely. Some departments have people doing great work; others have in the past; others never have.</p><p>然而，找到那些真正优秀的人可能需要一些努力。取得杰出成就会带来巨大的威望，以至于在一些地方，特别是大学，大家都有一个礼貌的假设，那就是每个人都在从事它。而这并非事实，人们不能公开说明这点，但在大学内部，不同部门所做的工作的质量差距巨大 —— 一些部门有人做出了伟大的工作，其他的在过去有过，其他的从来没有过。</p><p>Seek out the best colleagues. There are a lot of projects that can’t be done alone, and even if you’re working on one that can be, it’s good to have other people to encourage you and to bounce ideas off.</p><p>**寻找最能够共事的人。**很多项目是无法独自完成的，即使我们正在从事可以独自完成的项目，也好有其他人来鼓励自己，和我们交流想法。</p><p>Colleagues don’t just affect your work, though; they also affect you. So work with people you want to become like, because you will.</p><p>然而，同事不仅会影响我们的工作，他们也会影响我们本身。所以，<strong>与我们想成为的人一起工作，因为我们将会变得像他们。</strong></p><p>Quality is more important than quantity in colleagues. It’s better to have one or two great ones than a building full of pretty good ones. In fact it’s not merely better, but necessary, judging from history: the degree to which great work happens in clusters suggests that one’s colleagues often make the difference between doing great work and not.</p><p>在同事方面，质量比数量更重要 —— 拥有一两个优秀的同事比拥有一个楼的还算不错的同事更好。实际上，不仅是更好，而且是必需的，从历史来看，在集群中取得杰出成就的案例表明，同事通常决定了我们是否能取得伟大成就。</p><p>How do you know when you have sufficiently good colleagues? In my experience, when you do, you know. Which means if you’re unsure, you probably don’t. But it may be possible to give a more concrete answer than that. Here’s an attempt: sufficiently good colleagues offer surprising insights. They can see and do things that you can’t. So if you have a handful of colleagues good enough to keep you on your toes in this sense, you’re probably over the threshold.</p><p>我们如何知道自己有足够好的同事呢？根据我的经验，当我们有的时候，你就知道了 —— 这意味着，如果我们不确定，那可能没有。可能有更具体的答案，但这里是一个尝试：**足够好的同事会提供令人惊讶的见解，他们能看到并做我们不能做的事。**所以，如果我们有一小撮足够好的同事，让我们在这个意义上保持警觉，他们可能就已经越过了「不错」的阈值。</p><p>Most of us can benefit from collaborating with colleagues, but some projects require people on a larger scale, and starting one of those is not for everyone. If you want to run a project like that, you’ll have to become a manager, and managing well takes aptitude and interest like any other kind of work. If you don’t have them, there is no middle path: you must either force yourself to learn management as a second language, or avoid such projects. [27]</p><p>我们大多数人都可以从与同事的合作中获益，但一些项目需要更大规模的人，并不是每个人都适合发起这样的项目。如果我们想参与这样的项目，将必须成为一个管理者，好的管理需要才能和兴趣，这和其他任何类型的工作一样，如果我们没有它们，就没有妥协的方案：我们必须强迫自己学习管理并将其作为第二技能，或者避免参与这样的项目。[27]</p><p>Husband your morale. It’s the basis of everything when you’re working on ambitious projects. You have to nurture and protect it like a living organism.</p><p>**珍惜自己的士气 —— 当我们从事雄心勃勃的项目时，这是一切的基础。**我们必须像呵护生命一样来培养和保护它。</p><p>Morale starts with your view of life. You’re more likely to do great work if you’re an optimist, and more likely to if you think of yourself as lucky than if you think of yourself as a victim.</p><p>士气从我们的人生观开始。如果我们是一个乐观主义者，则更有可能取得伟大成就，我们需要把自己看作是幸运的，而不是受害者。</p><p>Indeed, work can to some extent protect you from your problems. If you choose work that’s pure, its very difficulties will serve as a refuge from the difficulties of everyday life. If this is escapism, it’s a very productive form of it, and one that has been used by some of the greatest minds in history.</p><p>事实上，工作可以在某种程度上保护我们免受自己的问题的影响。如果我们选择的工作是纯洁的，那么其本身就会成为我们从日常生活的困难中寻求庇护的地方，这种逃避是非常有生产力的，一些历史上最伟大的思想家都利用过这种行为。</p><p>Morale compounds via work: high morale helps you do good work, which increases your morale and helps you do even better work. But this cycle also operates in the other direction: if you’re not doing good work, that can demoralize you and make it even harder to. Since it matters so much for this cycle to be running in the right direction, it can be a good idea to switch to easier work when you’re stuck, just so you start to get something done.</p><p>士气通过工作复合增长：高昂的士气帮助我们做好工作，这又增加了我们的士气，帮助我们做得更好。但这个周期也在反方向奏效：如果我们没有做好工作，那可能会让自己士气低落，使得做事更难。由于这个周期在正确的方向运行如此重要，当我们陷入困境时，切换到更简单的工作可能是个好主意，只要我们一直做事就好。</p><p>One of the biggest mistakes ambitious people make is to allow setbacks to destroy their morale all at once, like a balloon bursting. You can inoculate yourself against this by explicitly considering setbacks a part of your process. Solving hard problems always involves some backtracking.</p><p>雄心勃勃的人最大的错误之一就是让挫折一次性毁掉他们的士气，就像气球爆炸一样。我们可以通过明确挫折是我们过程的一部分来预防这一点，解决难题总是涉及到走回头路。</p><p>Doing great work is a depth-first search whose root node is the desire to. So “If at first you don’t succeed, try, try again” isn’t quite right. It should be: If at first you don’t succeed, either try again, or backtrack and then try again.</p><p>**取得杰出成就是一种深度优先搜索，其根节点是我们想成功的欲望。**所以，「如果一开始没有成功，再试一次」这句话并不完全正确，它应该是「如果一开始没有成功，要么再试一次，要么退回去，然后再试一次」。</p><p>“Never give up” is also not quite right. Obviously there are times when it’s the right choice to eject. A more precise version would be: Never let setbacks panic you into backtracking more than you need to. Corollary: Never abandon the root node.</p><p>「永不放弃」也不完全正确，显然，有时候选择退出是正确的选择。更准确的说法应该是：永远不要让挫折让我们慌乱地走比自己需要的更多的回头路 —— 推论：永远不要放弃根节点。</p><p>It’s not necessarily a bad sign if work is a struggle, any more than it’s a bad sign to be out of breath while running. It depends how fast you’re running. So learn to distinguish good pain from bad. Good pain is a sign of effort; bad pain is a sign of damage.</p><p>工作如果令人痛苦挣扎，不一定是坏的迹象，就像在跑步时呼吸困难不一定是坏的迹象一样，这取决于我们跑得多快。所以学会区分好的痛苦和坏的痛苦 —— 好的痛苦是努力的标志，坏的痛苦是损害的标志。</p><p>An audience is a critical component of morale. If you’re a scholar, your audience may be your peers; in the arts, it may be an audience in the traditional sense. Either way it doesn’t need to be big. The value of an audience doesn’t grow anything like linearly with its size. Which is bad news if you’re famous, but good news if you’re just starting out, because it means a small but dedicated audience can be enough to sustain you. If a handful of people genuinely love what you’re doing, that’s enough.</p><p>**「观众」是士气的关键组成部分。**学者的观众可能是他们的同行，在艺术领域，可能是传统意义上的观众 —— 无论哪种方式，观众的数量不需要很大，观众的价值并不像其大小那样成线性增长。这对于那些著名的人来说是个坏消息，但对于刚刚起步的人来说是个好消息，因为这意味着一小组专注的观众足以支持我们，如果有少数人真正喜欢我们在做的事，那就够了。</p><p>To the extent you can, avoid letting intermediaries come between you and your audience. In some types of work this is inevitable, but it’s so liberating to escape it that you might be better off switching to an adjacent type if that will let you go direct. [28]</p><p>尽可能避免让中间人介入我们和自己的观众之间。在某些类型的工作中，这种情况不可避免，但我们有极大的自由度摆脱这种情况，因此，如果能让我们直接面对自己的观众，那我们最好转而从事类似的工作。[28]</p><p>The people you spend time with will also have a big effect on your morale. You’ll find there are some who increase your energy and others who decrease it, and the effect someone has is not always what you’d expect. Seek out the people who increase your energy and avoid those who decrease it. Though of course if there’s someone you need to take care of, that takes precedence.</p><p>我们花时间在一起的人也会对我们的士气产生很大影响。我们会发现有些人增加了自己的能量，而有些人减少了我们的能量，而一个人对你产生的影响并不总是你期望的。寻找那些能增加我们能量的人，避开那些减少我们能量的人 —— 当然，如果有人需要我们照顾，那就优先考虑。</p><p>Don’t marry someone who doesn’t understand that you need to work, or sees your work as competition for your attention. If you’re ambitious, you need to work; it’s almost like a medical condition; so someone who won’t let you work either doesn’t understand you, or does and doesn’t care.</p><p>不要与一个不明白我们需要工作，或者与我们的工作竞争注意力的人结婚。如果我们有雄心壮志，我们需要工作，这无须多言，所以，如果一个人不让我们工作，要么就是不理解我们，要么就是理解但不在乎。</p><p>Ultimately morale is physical. You think with your body, so it’s important to take care of it. That means exercising regularly, eating and sleeping well, and avoiding the more dangerous kinds of drugs. Running and walking are particularly good forms of exercise because they’re good for thinking. [29]</p><p>最后，**士气其实也是物理的，我们用身体思考，所以照顾好它很重要。**这意味着定期运动、饮食以及保持良好睡眠，避免使用危险类型的药物。跑步和步行是特别好的锻炼方式，因为它们有利于思考。[29]</p><p>People who do great work are not necessarily happier than everyone else, but they’re happier than they’d be if they didn’t. In fact, if you’re smart and ambitious, it’s dangerous not to be productive. People who are smart and ambitious but don’t achieve much tend to become bitter.</p><p>取得杰出成就的人并不一定比其他人更快乐，但他们比不成功时更快乐。实际上，如果我们聪明而有雄心，不工作是危险的，那些聪明而有雄心，但没有成就很多的人往往会变得很痛苦。</p><p>It’s ok to want to impress other people, but choose the right people. The opinion of people you respect is signal. Fame, which is the opinion of a much larger group you might or might not respect, just adds noise.</p><p><strong>想要给别人留下印象是可以的，但要选择正确的人，我们所尊重的人的观点是信号；名声，也就是我们可能尊重或可能不尊重的更广泛群体的观点，只是噪音。</strong></p><p>The prestige of a type of work is at best a trailing indicator and sometimes completely mistaken. If you do anything well enough, you’ll make it prestigious. So the question to ask about a type of work is not how much prestige it has, but how well it could be done.</p><p>一种工作的声望最好的情况下是一个落后的指标，有时则是完全错误的标志。如果我们把任何事情做得足够好，我们就会使它有声望。所以，面对一种工作，我们的问题不应该是它有多大的声望，而是它可以被做到多好。</p><p>Competition can be an effective motivator, but don’t let it choose the problem for you; don’t let yourself get drawn into chasing something just because others are. In fact, don’t let competitors make you do anything much more specific than work harder.</p><p>竞争可以是一个有效的动力，但不要让它指导我们选择问题，不要仅仅因为别人在追求某件事就让自己被扯进去。事实上，不要让竞争者指导我们做任何比较具体的事，比如更加努力工作。</p><p>Curiosity is the best guide. Your curiosity never lies, and it knows more than you do about what’s worth paying attention to.</p><p><strong>好奇心是最好的指导者，好奇心永远不会撒谎，它比我们自己更了解什么值得关注。</strong></p><p>Notice how often that word has come up. If you asked an oracle the secret to doing great work and the oracle replied with a single word, my bet would be on “curiosity.”</p><p>注意这个词出现的频率。<strong>如果我们问一个预言家取得杰出成就的秘密，预言家用一个词回答，我赌就是「好奇心」。</strong></p><p>That doesn’t translate directly to advice. It’s not enough just to be curious, and you can’t command curiosity anyway. But you can nurture it and let it drive you.</p><p>这并不能直接被解释为建议。仅仅是好奇是不够的，我们也不能左右好奇，但是我们可以培养它，让它驱动我们。</p><p>Curiosity is the key to all four steps in doing great work: it will choose the field for you, get you to the frontier, cause you to notice the gaps in it, and drive you to explore them. The whole process is a kind of dance with curiosity.</p><p>好奇心是做伟大工作的所有四个步骤的关键：它会为我们选择领域，带我们到达领域边界，让我们注意到其中的空白，并驱使我们去探索它们 —— 整个过程都在与好奇心共舞。</p><p>Believe it or not, I tried to make this essay as short as I could. But its length at least means it acts as a filter. If you made it this far, you must be interested in doing great work. And if so you’re already further along than you might realize, because the set of people willing to want to is small.</p><p>信不信由你，我试图让这篇论文尽可能地短。但是它的长度至少意味着它起到了一个过滤器的作用 —— 如果你看到了这里，你一定对做伟大的工作感兴趣。如果是这样，你已经比你可能意识到的要进一步了，因为愿意去想的人的集合是很小的。</p><p>The factors in doing great work are factors in the literal, mathematical sense, and they are: ability, interest, effort, and luck. Luck by definition you can’t do anything about, so we can ignore that. And we can assume effort, if you do in fact want to do great work. So the problem boils down to ability and interest. Can you find a kind of work where your ability and interest will combine to yield an explosion of new ideas?</p><p>取得伟大成就的因素在字面上，数学上是因素，它们是：**能力、兴趣、努力和运气。**运气是我们无法左右的，所以可以忽略它；并且，如果确实想要取得伟大成就，我们可以假设每个人都很努力；<strong>所以问题归结为能力和兴趣 —— 我们能否找到一种工作，将自己的能力和兴趣结合起来，让新想法迸发？</strong></p><p>Here there are grounds for optimism. There are so many different ways to do great work, and even more that are still undiscovered. Out of all those different types of work, the one you’re most suited for is probably a pretty close match. Probably a comically close match. It’s just a question of finding it, and how far into it your ability and interest can take you. And you can only answer that by trying.</p><p>我们有乐观的理由。有很多不同的方式来取得伟大成就，与此同时，还有更多的方式还未被发现。在所有这些不同类型的工作中，我们最适合的那一种可能是非常接近的匹配，可能是一个滑稽的接近的匹配 —— 这其中只有一个问题，我们要找到它，以及我们的能力和兴趣能带自己走多远 —— 我们只能通过尝试来回答这个问题。</p><p>Many more people could try to do great work than do. What holds them back is a combination of modesty and fear. It seems presumptuous to try to be Newton or Shakespeare. It also seems hard; surely if you tried something like that, you’d fail. Presumably the calculation is rarely explicit. Few people consciously decide not to try to do great work. But that’s what’s going on subconsciously; they shy away from the question.</p><p>可以尝试取得伟大成就的人比实际做到的人多得多，但阻止他们的是一种由谦逊和恐惧组成的混合物，例如，「试图成为牛顿或莎士比亚似乎有点狂妄，这看起来也很难」，「如果试了这样的事情，一定会失败」，「经过推算，这样的概率很小，不做是明智的」等等。很少有人有意识地决定不去尝试取得伟大成就，但这就是潜意识里正在发生的事 —— 他们回避这个问题。</p><p>So I’m going to pull a sneaky trick on you. Do you want to do great work, or not? Now you have to decide consciously. Sorry about that. I wouldn’t have done it to a general audience. But we already know you’re interested.</p><p>现在我要与你玩个游戏了。你想取得伟大的成就，还是不想呢？现在你必须有意识地下决定 —— 对不起，对此我感到抱歉，我一般不会对读者这么做，但看到这里，我已经知道你感兴趣了。</p><p>Don’t worry about being presumptuous. You don’t have to tell anyone. And if it’s too hard and you fail, so what? Lots of people have worse problems than that. In fact you’ll be lucky if it’s the worst problem you have.</p><p>不要担心过于自大，你不需要讲这个决定告诉任何人。如果太难，失败了，那又怎样呢？很多人需要解决这更糟糕的问题 —— 实际上，如果这是你最糟糕的问题，那么你真的非常幸运。</p><p>Yes, you’ll have to work hard. But again, lots of people have to work hard. And if you’re working on something you find very interesting, which you necessarily will if you’re on the right path, the work will probably feel less burdensome than a lot of your peers’.</p><p>是的，我们必须努力工作。但再次，很多人必须努力工作。并且，如果我们在做自己觉得非常有趣的事情，我们必然会在正确的道路上，工作可能会感觉比我们很多同伴的轻松。</p><p>The discoveries are out there, waiting to be made. Why not by you?</p><p><strong>发现正在等待被发现，为什么不是由我们自己呢？</strong></p><p>Notes</p><p>[1] I don’t think you could give a precise definition of what counts as great work. Doing great work means doing something important so well that you expand people’s ideas of what’s possible. But there’s no threshold for importance. It’s a matter of degree, and often hard to judge at the time anyway. So I’d rather people focused on developing their interests rather than worrying about whether they’re important or not. Just try to do something amazing, and leave it to future generations to say if you succeeded.</p><p>[1] 我不认为我们可以给杰出成就一个精确的定义。取得杰出成就意味着做了某件很重要事情，做得很好，以至于扩大了人们对可能性的认识，但是，对于重要性并没有一个阈值，这是一个程度的问题，而且往往很难在当时进行判断。所以，我宁愿让人们专注于发展他们的兴趣，而不是担心它们是否重要 —— 只要试图做一些令人惊奇的事情，子孙后代会判断你是否成功。</p><p>[2] A lot of standup comedy is based on noticing anomalies in everyday life. “Did you ever notice…?” New ideas come from doing this about nontrivial things. Which may help explain why people’s reaction to a new idea is often the first half of laughing: Ha!</p><p>[2] 很多的单口喜剧都是基于在日常生活中发现的不寻常现象。「你有没有注意到…？」新的想法来自于关于非琐碎事情的这类观察，这可能有助于解释为什么人们对一个新想法的反应往往是笑：哈！</p><p>[3] That second qualifier is critical. If you’re excited about something most authorities discount, but you can’t give a more precise explanation than “they don’t get it,” then you’re starting to drift into the territory of cranks.</p><p>[3] 「有足够的专业知识来精确地说出他们都忽视了什么」这个限定是关键。如果我们对大部分权威都不认可的事情感到兴奋，但不能给出比「他们不懂」更精确的解释，那么我们自己就开始向怪人那一端发展了。</p><p>[4] Finding something to work on is not simply a matter of finding a match between the current version of you and a list of known problems. You’ll often have to coevolve with the problem. That’s why it can sometimes be so hard to figure out what to work on. The search space is huge. It’s the cartesian product of all possible types of work, both known and yet to be discovered, and all possible future versions of you.</p><p>[4] 找到一些事情来做并不仅仅是在当前版本和已知问题之间找到匹配的问题，我们往往必须要与问题共同发展，这就是为什么有时找出该做什么事会很困难。我们所能搜索的空间是巨大的，它是所有可能的工作类型（已知的和尚未发现的）和所有可能的未来版本的笛卡尔乘积。</p><p>There’s no way you could search this whole space, so you have to rely on heuristics to generate promising paths through it and hope the best matches will be clustered. Which they will not always be; different types of work have been collected together as much by accidents of history as by the intrinsic similarities between them.</p><p>我们没有办法搜索整个空间，所以必须依赖启发式方法在空间中生成有希望的路径，并希望最佳匹配会聚集在一起 —— 但是，它们并不总是会聚集在一起 —— 不同类型的工作被聚集在一起，多半是由于历史的偶然性，而非它们的内在相似性。</p><p>[5] There are many reasons curious people are more likely to do great work, but one of the more subtle is that, by casting a wide net, they’re more likely to find the right thing to work on in the first place.</p><p>[5] 好奇的人更有可能取得杰出成就有很多原因，但其中的一个微妙原因是，通过撒了一个宽广的网，他们更有可能在一开始就找到正确的事情来做。</p><p>[6] It can also be dangerous to make things for an audience you feel is less sophisticated than you, if that causes you to talk down to them. You can make a lot of money doing that, if you do it in a sufficiently cynical way, but it’s not the route to great work. Not that anyone using this m.o. would care.</p><p>[6] 如果我们感觉受众不如自己精明，我们可能会对他们居高临下，那么为他们制作出的东西可能也是糟糕的。如果我们抱着藐视一切的态度做产品，可以赚很多钱，但这不是通往杰出成就的路 —— 不过使用这种手段的人可能不会在意。</p><p>[7] This idea I learned from Hardy’s A Mathematician’s Apology, which I recommend to anyone ambitious to do great work, in any field.</p><p>[7] 这个想法我从哈代的《一个数学家的辩白》中学到的，我推荐任何有抱负，要取得伟大成就的人去阅读读，无论是在什么领域。</p><p>[8] Just as we overestimate what we can do in a day and underestimate what we can do over several years, we overestimate the damage done by procrastinating for a day and underestimate the damage done by procrastinating for several years.</p><p>[8] 就像我们高估了我们在一天内可以做什么，低估了我们在几年内可以做什么，我们高估了拖延一天造成的损害，低估了拖延几年造成的损害。</p><p>[9] You can’t usually get paid for doing exactly what you want, especially early on. There are two options: get paid for doing work close to what you want and hope to push it closer, or get paid for doing something else entirely and do your own projects on the side. Both can work, but both have drawbacks: in the first approach your work is compromised by default, and in the second you have to fight to get time to do it.</p><p>[9] 我们通常不能完全按照自己的意愿去做事，特别是在早期。有两个选择：做接近我们想做的工作并希望二者越来越接近，或者做完全不同的事情并在业余时间做自己的项目。两者都可行，但两者都有缺点：在第一种方法中，我们的工作默认被妥协了，在第二种我们必须努力找到时间去做。</p><p>[10] If you set your life up right, it will deliver the focus-relax cycle automatically. The perfect setup is an office you work in and that you walk to and from.</p><p>[10] 如果我们的生活安排得当，它会自动提供「专注 - 放松」的周期。完美的设置是我们在这个循环中工作，并且拥有可以步行往返的办公室。</p><p>[11] There may be some very unworldly people who do great work without consciously trying to. If you want to expand this rule to cover that case, it becomes: Don’t try to be anything except the best.</p><p>[11] 也许有一些非常超凡的人，他们可以取得杰出成就，而不需要有意识地去尝试。如果我们想拓展这个规则以取得同样的成功，它会变成：除了做最好的，别尝试做其他任何事情。</p><p>[12] This gets more complicated in work like acting, where the goal is to adopt a fake persona. But even here it’s possible to be affected. Perhaps the rule in such fields should be to avoid unintentional affectation.</p><p>[12] 在诸如表演之类的工作中，目标是展现一个假的人格，这就更复杂了。但是即使在这种情况下，也有可能被矫饰影响 —— 也许在这样的领域中的规则应该是避免无意的矫饰。</p><p>[13] It’s safe to have beliefs that you treat as unquestionable if and only if they’re also unfalsifiable. For example, it’s safe to have the principle that everyone should be treated equally under the law, because a sentence with a “should” in it isn’t really a statement about the world and is therefore hard to disprove. And if there’s no evidence that could disprove one of your principles, there can’t be any facts you’d need to ignore in order to preserve it.</p><p>[13] 如果我们有一个原则，如何判断它是否可以被视为是无可质疑的？只有在它是无法证伪的情况下才是安全的。例如，每个人都应该在法律面前平等，这是安全的原则，因为一个带有「应该」的句子实际上并不是关于世界观的陈述，因此很难被证明是错误的。如果我们不需要掩盖任何事实以维护它，那就没有证据可以证伪我们的某个原则。</p><p>[14] Affectation is easier to cure than intellectual dishonesty. Affectation is often a shortcoming of the young that burns off in time, while intellectual dishonesty is more of a character flaw.</p><p>[14] 矫饰比智力不诚实更容易治愈。矫饰往往是年轻人的缺点，随着时间的推移会消失，而智力不诚实更像是一个性格上的缺点。</p><p>[15] Obviously you don’t have to be working at the exact moment you have the idea, but you’ll probably have been working fairly recently.</p><p>[15] 显然，我们不必在有想法的那一刻就投入这项工作，但我们需要工作。</p><p>[16] Some say psychoactive drugs have a similar effect. I’m skeptical, but also almost totally ignorant of their effects.</p><p>[16] 有些人说精神活性药物有类似的效果。我持怀疑态度，但也对它们的影响几乎一无所知。</p><p>[17] For example you might give the nth most important topic (m-1)&#x2F;m^n of your attention, for some m &gt; 1. You couldn’t allocate your attention so precisely, of course, but this at least gives an idea of a reasonable distribution.</p><p>[17] 例如，我们可能会给第 n 个最重要的主题 (m-1)&#x2F;m^n 的注意力，m &gt; 1。当然，我们不能那么精确地分配自己的注意力，但这至少给出了一个合理分配的想法。</p><p>[18] The principles defining a religion have to be mistaken. Otherwise anyone might adopt them, and there would be nothing to distinguish the adherents of the religion from everyone else.</p><p>[18] 定义一个宗教的原则必须是错误的。否则，任何人都可能采用它们，那么就没有什么可以区分宗教信徒和其他人的了。</p><p>[19] It might be a good exercise to try writing down a list of questions you wondered about in your youth. You might find you’re now in a position to do something about some of them.</p><p>[19] 试着写下我们过去好奇的问题的列表可能是一个好的练习。我们可能会发现自己现在有能力去解决其中的一些问题。</p><p>[20] The connection between originality and uncertainty causes a strange phenomenon: because the conventional-minded are more certain than the independent-minded, this tends to give them the upper hand in disputes, even though they’re generally stupider.<br>The best lack all conviction, while the worst<br>Are full of passionate intensity.</p><p>[20] 原创性和不确定性之间的联系导致了一种奇特的现象：因为有传统思维的人比独立思维的人更确定，这往往给他们在争论中占上风，即使他们通常更愚蠢。最好的人都缺乏信念，而最差的人充满了顽固气息。</p><p>[21] Derived from Linus Pauling’s “If you want to have good ideas, you must have many ideas.”</p><p>[21] 来自 Linus Pauling 的「如果你想有好主意，你必须有很多主意。」</p><p>[22] Attacking a project as a “toy” is similar to attacking a statement as “inappropriate.” It means that no more substantial criticism can be made to stick.</p><p>[22] 称一个项目为「玩具」类似于称一个声明为「不适当」，这意味着没有更实质的批评可以给出。</p><p>[23] One way to tell whether you’re wasting time is to ask if you’re producing or consuming. Writing computer games is less likely to be a waste of time than playing them, and playing games where you create something is less likely to be a waste of time than playing games where you don’t.</p><p>[23] 判断我们是否在浪费时间的一个方法是问自己是否在生产还是在消费。写电脑游戏可能比玩它们浪费时间的可能性要小，而玩我们可以创造东西的游戏可能比玩不能创造东西的游戏浪费时间的可能性要小。</p><p>[24] Another related advantage is that if you haven’t said anything publicly yet, you won’t be biased toward evidence that supports your earlier conclusions. With sufficient integrity you could achieve eternal youth in this respect, but few manage to. For most people, having previously published opinions has an effect similar to ideology, just in quantity 1.</p><p>[24] 另一个相关的优点是，如果我们还没有公开地说过什么，就不会偏向于相信支持我们之前的结论的证据。以足够的中立态度，我们可以在这方面实现永恒青春，但很少有人能做到。对大多数人来说，以前公开过的意见有一种类似于意识形态的效果，只是在数量上为 1。</p><p>[25] In the early 1630s Daniel Mytens made a painting of Henrietta Maria handing a laurel wreath to Charles I. Van Dyck then painted his own version to show how much better he was.</p><p>[25] 1630 年代初，Daniel Mytens 画了一幅画，描绘了 Henrietta Maria 把月桂冠递给 Charles I 的场景，然后 Van Dyck 画了他自己的版本，以显示他有多么优秀。</p><p>[26] I’m being deliberately vague about what a place is. As of this writing, being in the same physical place has advantages that are hard to duplicate, but that could change.</p><p>[26] 我在这里故意模糊了什么是地方的定义。截至写这篇文章，身处同一物理地点具有难以复制的优势，但这可能会改变。</p><p>[27] This is false when the work the other people have to do is very constrained, as with SETI@home or Bitcoin. It may be possible to expand the area in which it’s false by defining similarly restricted protocols with more freedom of action in the nodes.</p><p>[27] 当其他人必须做的工作非常受限时，这是错误的，例如 SETI@home 或比特币。通过定义类似的受限协议，让节点有更大的行动自由，可能会使错误扩大。</p><p>[28] Corollary: Building something that enables people to go around intermediaries and engage directly with their audience is probably a good idea.</p><p>[28] 推论：构建能让人们绕过中介并直接与受众接触的东西可能是个好主意。</p><p>[29] It may be helpful always to walk or run the same route, because that frees attention for thinking. It feels that way to me, and there is some historical evidence for it.</p><p>[29] 一直走或跑同样的路线可能有所帮助，因为这给思考留出更多注意力。我有这种感觉，也有一些历史证据支持。</p>]]></content>
    
    
    <categories>
      
      <category>文章翻译</category>
      
    </categories>
    
    
    <tags>
      
      <tag>PAUL GRAHAM</tag>
      
    </tags>
    
  </entry>
  
  
  
  <entry>
    <title>平凡而惊奇</title>
    <link href="/2025/07/17/general-and-surprising/"/>
    <url>/2025/07/17/general-and-surprising/</url>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="GENERAL-AND-SURPRISING"><a href="#GENERAL-AND-SURPRISING" class="headerlink" title="GENERAL AND SURPRISING"></a>GENERAL AND SURPRISING</h2><p>原文链接: <a href="https://paulgraham.com/sun.html">https://paulgraham.com/sun.html</a></p><h3 id="一、最具价值的见解"><a href="#一、最具价值的见解" class="headerlink" title="一、最具价值的见解"></a>一、最具价值的见解</h3><p>The most valuable insights are both general and surprising. F &#x3D; ma for example. But general and surprising is a hard combination to achieve. That territory tends to be picked clean, precisely because those insights are so valuable. </p><p>最有价值的见解兼具普遍性和惊喜感。例如 F&#x3D;ma（牛顿第二运动定律）。但兼具普遍性和惊喜感是很难实现的，这类见解所在的领域往往已被挖掘殆尽，原因恰恰在于它们极具价值。</p><p>Ordinarily, the best that people can do is one without the other: either surprising without being general (e.g. gossip), or general without being surprising (e.g. platitudes). </p><p>通常情况下，鱼和熊掌不可兼得：要么有惊喜感却缺乏普遍性（比如八卦），要么有普遍性却毫无惊喜（比如陈词滥调）。</p><p>Where things get interesting is the moderately valuable insights. You get those from small additions of whichever quality was missing. The more common case is a small addition of generality: a piece of gossip that’s more than just gossip, because it teaches something interesting about the world. But another less common approach is to focus on the most general ideas and see if you can find something new to say about them. Because these start out so general, you only need a small delta of novelty to produce a useful insight. </p><p>真正有趣的是那些中等价值的见解。要获得这类见解，只需在缺失的特质上稍作补充。更常见的情况是补充少量普遍性：一条八卦之所以不只是八卦，是因为它能让人了解到关于世界的有趣之事。但另一种不太常见的方式是，聚焦于最具普遍性的观点，看看能否就它们说出些新东西。由于这些观点本身已经极具普遍性，因此只需一点新颖性的补充，就能产生有独到之处的见解。</p><h3 id="二、微小创意也能够带来巨大的不同"><a href="#二、微小创意也能够带来巨大的不同" class="headerlink" title="二、微小创意也能够带来巨大的不同"></a>二、微小创意也能够带来巨大的不同</h3><p>A small delta of novelty is all you’ll be able to get most of the time. Which means if you take this route, your ideas will seem a lot like ones that already exist. Sometimes you’ll find you’ve merely rediscovered an idea that did already exist. But don’t be discouraged. Remember the huge multiplier that kicks in when you do manage to think of something even a little new. </p><p>大多数时候，你能获得的只是少量的新颖性。这意味着如果你选择这条路径，你的观点看起来会和已有的观点十分相似。有时你会发现，自己只是重新发现了一个早已存在的观点。但不必气馁。记住，当你确实想到哪怕一点点新东西时，随之而来的乘法效应是巨大的。</p><p>Corollary: the more general the ideas you’re talking about, the less you should worry about repeating yourself. If you write enough, it’s inevitable you will. Your brain is much the same from year to year and so are the stimuli that hit it. I feel slightly bad when I find I’ve said something close to what I’ve said before, as if I were plagiarizing myself. But rationally one shouldn’t. You won’t say something exactly the same way the second time, and that variation increases the chance you’ll get that tiny but critical delta of novelty. </p><p>推论：你谈论的观点越具普遍性，就越不必担心重复自己。如果你写得足够多，重复是不可避免的。你的大脑年复一年变化不大，冲击它的刺激也大致相同。当我发现自己说的话和以前说过的很接近时，会略感不适，仿佛在抄袭自己。但理性而言，不必如此。你第二次不会用完全相同的方式表达，而这种差异会增加你获得那微小却关键的新颖性增量的机会。</p><h3 id="三、持续探索的勇气"><a href="#三、持续探索的勇气" class="headerlink" title="三、持续探索的勇气"></a>三、持续探索的勇气</h3><p>And of course, ideas beget ideas. (That sounds familiar.) An idea with a small amount of novelty could lead to one with more. But only if you keep going. So it’s doubly important not to let yourself be discouraged by people who say there’s not much new about something you’ve discovered. “Not much new” is a real achievement when you’re talking about the most general ideas. </p><p>当然，观点会催生新观点。（这话听着耳熟。）一个带有少量新颖性的观点可能会引出更具新颖性的观点，但前提是你要坚持下去。因此，当有人说你发现的东西没什么新意时，千万不要气馁，这一点尤为重要。当你谈论的是最具普遍性的观点时，“没太多新意” 其实是一项实实在在的成就。</p><p>It’s not true that there’s nothing new under the sun. There are some domains where there’s almost nothing new. But there’s a big difference between nothing and almost nothing, when it’s multiplied by the area under the sun.</p><p>“日光之下并无新事” 这句话并不正确。有些领域几乎没有新东西，但 “完全没有新东西” 和 “几乎没有新东西” 之间存在巨大差异，尤其是当它乘以 “日光之下的广阔领域” 时。</p>]]></content>
    
    
    <categories>
      
      <category>文章翻译</category>
      
    </categories>
    
    
    <tags>
      
      <tag>PAUL GRAHAM</tag>
      
    </tags>
    
  </entry>
  
  
  
  <entry>
    <title>何时去追寻你所热爱</title>
    <link href="/2025/07/16/follow-your-passion/"/>
    <url>/2025/07/16/follow-your-passion/</url>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="WHEN-TO-DO-WHAT-YOU-LOVE"><a href="#WHEN-TO-DO-WHAT-YOU-LOVE" class="headerlink" title="WHEN TO DO WHAT YOU LOVE"></a>WHEN TO DO WHAT YOU LOVE</h2><p>原文链接: <a href="https://paulgraham.com/when.html">https://paulgraham.com/when.html</a></p><h3 id="一、关于“追随热情”的争论"><a href="#一、关于“追随热情”的争论" class="headerlink" title="一、关于“追随热情”的争论"></a>一、关于“追随热情”的争论</h3><p>There’s some debate about whether it’s a good idea to “follow your passion.” In fact the question is impossible to answer with a simple yes or no. Sometimes you should and sometimes you shouldn’t, but the border between should and shouldn’t is very complicated. The only way to give a general answer is to trace it. </p><p>关于 “追随激情” 是否是个好主意，存在一些争议。事实上，这个问题无法用简单的 “是” 或 “否” 来回答。有时应该，有时不应该，但 “应该” 与 “不应该” 之间的界限非常复杂。给出一个一般性答案的唯一方法，是追溯其背后的逻辑。</p><p>When people talk about this question, there’s always an implicit “instead of.” All other things being equal, why wouldn’t you work on what interests you the most? So even raising the question implies that all other things aren’t equal, and that you have to choose between working on what interests you the most and something else, like what pays the best. </p><p>人们讨论这个问题时，总会隐含一个 “取而代之” 的前提。在其他条件相同的情况下，为什么不做自己最感兴趣的事呢？因此，即便提出这个问题，也意味着其他条件并不相同 —— 你必须在 “做最感兴趣的事” 和 “其他事”（比如薪资最高的事）之间做出选择。</p><p>And indeed if your main goal is to make money, you can’t usually afford to work on what interests you the most. People pay you for doing what they want, not what you want. But there’s an obvious exception: when you both want the same thing. For example, if you love football, and you’re good enough at it, you can get paid a lot to play it. </p><p>的确，若你的主要目标是赚钱，通常就没法只顾着做最感兴趣的事。人们付钱给你，是为了让你做他们想让你做的事，而非你自己想做的事。但有个明显的例外：当你和他们的需求一致时。比如，如果你热爱足球，且足够擅长，就能靠踢球赚很多钱。</p><p>Of course the odds are against you in a case like football, because so many other people like playing it too. This is not to say you shouldn’t try though. It depends how much ability you have and how hard you’re willing to work. </p><p>当然，在足球这类领域，成功的概率对你不利，因为太多人也喜欢踢球。但这并非说你不该尝试 —— 这取决于你的能力有多强，以及你愿意付出多少努力。</p><p>The odds are better when you have strange tastes: when you like something that pays well and that few other people like. For example, it’s clear that Bill Gates truly loved running a software company. He didn’t just love programming, which a lot of people do. He loved writing software for customers. That is a very strange taste indeed, but if you have it, you can make a lot by indulging it. </p><p>当你的喜好比较特别时，成功的概率会更高：比如你喜欢的事既能赚钱，又没多少人感兴趣。显然，比尔・盖茨是真的热爱经营软件公司。他不只是热爱编程（很多人都热爱编程），而是热爱为客户写软件。这确实是一种非常特别的喜好，但如果你有这种喜好，沉浸其中就能赚很多钱。</p><p>There are even some people who have a genuine intellectual interest in making money. This is distinct from mere greed. They just can’t help noticing when something is mispriced, and can’t help doing something about it. It’s like a puzzle for them. [1] </p><p>甚至有一些人，对赚钱有着真正的智力层面的兴趣。这和单纯的贪婪不同。他们总会不由自主地发现定价不合理的东西，也总会忍不住去做点什么。对他们来说，这就像一道谜题。[1]</p><h3 id="二、目标与兴趣的平衡"><a href="#二、目标与兴趣的平衡" class="headerlink" title="二、目标与兴趣的平衡"></a>二、目标与兴趣的平衡</h3><p>In fact there’s an edge case here so spectacular that it turns all the preceding advice on its head. If you want to make a really huge amount of money — hundreds of millions or even billions of dollars — it turns out to be very useful to work on what interests you the most. The reason is not the extra motivation you get from doing this, but that the way to make a really large amount of money is to start a startup, and working on what interests you is an excellent way to discover startup ideas. </p><p>事实上，这里有一个极端案例，它的影响之大，足以颠覆前面所有的建议。如果你想赚一大笔钱 —— 数亿甚至数十亿美元 —— 那么，做自己最感兴趣的事其实非常有用。原因并非做这些事能带来额外的动力，而是赚大钱的方式往往是创办初创公司，而做自己感兴趣的事，是发现初创公司创意的绝佳途径。</p><p>Many if not most of the biggest startups began as projects the founders were doing for fun. Apple, Google, and Facebook all began that way. Why is this pattern so common? Because the best ideas tend to be such outliers that you’d overlook them if you were consciously looking for ways to make money. Whereas if you’re young and good at technology, your unconscious instincts about what would be interesting to work on are very well aligned with what needs to be built. </p><p>即便不是大多数，也有很多顶尖的初创公司，最初都是创始人出于乐趣而做的项目。苹果、谷歌、脸书都是如此。为什么这种模式如此常见？因为最棒的创意往往太出格，如果你刻意追求赚钱，很可能会忽略它们。而如果你年轻且擅长技术，你对 “做什么事有趣” 的直觉，往往和 “该创造什么” 高度契合。</p><p>So there’s something like a midwit peak for making money. If you don’t need to make much, you can work on whatever you’re most interested in; if you want to become moderately rich, you can’t usually afford to; but if you want to become super rich, and you’re young and good at technology, working on what you’re most interested in becomes a good idea again. </p><p>所以，在赚钱这件事上，存在一种 “中等智慧峰值”：如果你不需要赚太多钱，就能做自己最感兴趣的事；如果你想变得小康，通常就不能只顾兴趣；但如果你想变得超级富有，且年轻又擅长技术，那么做自己最感兴趣的事又会成为一个好主意。</p><h3 id="三、何时做出抉择"><a href="#三、何时做出抉择" class="headerlink" title="三、何时做出抉择"></a>三、何时做出抉择</h3><p>What if you’re not sure what you want? What if you’re attracted to the idea of making money and more attracted to some kinds of work than others, but neither attraction predominates? How do you break ties? </p><p>如果你不确定自己想要什么呢？如果你既被赚钱的想法吸引，又对某些工作更感兴趣，但两者都没有绝对优势，该如何抉择？</p><p>The key here is to understand that such ties are only apparent. When you have trouble choosing between following your interests and making money, it’s never because you have complete knowledge of yourself and of the types of work you’re choosing between, and the options are perfectly balanced. When you can’t decide which path to take, it’s almost always due to ignorance. In fact you’re usually suffering from three kinds of ignorance simultaneously: you don’t know what makes you happy, what the various kinds of work are really like, or how well you could do them. [2] </p><p>关键在于，这种 “难以抉择” 往往只是表面现象。当你在 “追随兴趣” 和 “赚钱” 之间犹豫时，绝非因为你完全了解自己、了解可选的工作，且选项完美平衡。你无法决定，几乎总是因为信息不足 —— 你不知道什么能让自己快乐，不知道各种工作的真实情况，也不知道自己能把这些工作做得多好。[2]</p><p>In a way this ignorance is excusable. It’s often hard to predict these things, and no one even tells you that you need to. If you’re ambitious you’re told you should go to college, and this is good advice so far as it goes, but that’s where it usually ends. No one tells you how to figure out what to work on, or how hard this can be. </p><p>在某种程度上，这种信息不足是可以理解的。预测这些事往往很难，而且没人告诉你需要去弄清楚这些。如果你有野心，别人会告诉你应该上大学，这在某种程度上是个好建议，但通常也就到此为止了。没人告诉你该如何确定自己要做什么，也没人告诉你这件事有多难。</p><p>What do you do in the face of uncertainty? Get more certainty. And probably the best way to do that is to try working on things you’re interested in. That will get you more information about how interested you are in them, how good you are at them, and how much scope they offer for ambition. </p><p>面对不确定性该怎么办？去获取更多确定性。最好的方法可能就是尝试做自己感兴趣的事。这会让你更清楚自己对这件事的兴趣有多深、自己有多擅长，以及这件事能给你多大的发展空间。</p><p>Don’t wait. Don’t wait till the end of college to figure out what to work on. Don’t even wait for internships during college. You don’t necessarily need a job doing x in order to work on x; often you can just start doing it in some form yourself. And since figuring out what to work on is a problem that could take years to solve, the sooner you start, the better. </p><p>别等。别等到大学毕业才确定自己要做什么，甚至别等到大学期间的实习。你不一定非要找到一份做某件事的工作才能去做它 —— 通常你自己就能以某种形式开始。既然确定自己要做什么可能需要好几年，那么越早开始越好。</p><h3 id="四、时势造英雄"><a href="#四、时势造英雄" class="headerlink" title="四、时势造英雄"></a>四、时势造英雄</h3><p>One useful trick for judging different kinds of work is to look at who your colleagues will be. You’ll become like whoever you work with. Do you want to become like these people? </p><p>判断不同工作的一个有用技巧，是看看你未来的同事会是什么样的人。你会变得和他们越来越像。你想变成他们那样吗？</p><p>Indeed, the difference in character between different kinds of work is magnified by the fact that everyone else is facing the same decisions as you. If you choose a kind of work mainly for how well it pays, you’ll be surrounded by other people who chose it for the same reason, and that will make it even more soul-sucking than it seems from the outside. Whereas if you choose work you’re genuinely interested in, you’ll be surrounded mostly by other people who are genuinely interested in it, and that will make it extra inspiring. [3] </p><p>事实上，不同工作在 “人的特质” 上的差异，会因 “每个人都在做类似选择” 而被放大。如果你选一份工作主要是因为薪水高，身边就会围绕着同样为钱而来的人，这会让这份工作比表面看起来更让人身心俱疲。而如果你选择自己真正感兴趣的工作，身边大多会是同样感兴趣的人，这会让工作额外鼓舞人心。[3]</p><p>The other thing you do in the face of uncertainty is to make choices that are uncertainty-proof. The less sure you are about what to do, the more important it is to choose options that give you more options in the future. I call this “staying upwind.” If you’re unsure whether to major in math or economics, for example, choose math; math is upwind of economics in the sense that it will be easier to switch later from math to economics than from economics to math. </p><p>面对不确定性时，另一件要做的事是做 “抗不确定性” 的选择。你越不确定该做什么，就越要选那些能给未来留更多选项的事。我称之为 “保持在上风处”。比如，如果你不确定该选数学还是经济学专业，就选数学 —— 数学相对于经济学处于 “上风”，因为日后从数学转经济学比从经济学转数学更容易。</p><p>There’s one case, though, where it’s easy to say whether you should work on what interests you the most: if you want to do great work. This is not a sufficient condition for doing great work, but it is a necessary one. </p><p>不过，有一种情况，“是否该做自己最感兴趣的事” 的答案很明确：如果你想做出伟大的成就。这不是做出伟大成就的充分条件，但却是必要条件。</p><p>There’s a lot of selection bias in advice about whether to “follow your passion,” and this is the reason. Most such advice comes from people who are famously successful, and if you ask someone who’s famously successful how to do what they did, most will tell you that you have to work on what you’re most interested in. And this is in fact true. </p><p>关于 “是否该追随激情” 的建议，存在很强的选择性偏差，这就是原因所在。大多数这类建议来自那些非常成功的人，如果你问一个极其成功的人如何取得成就，大多数人会告诉你，必须做自己最感兴趣的事。而这其实是事实。</p><p>That doesn’t mean it’s the right advice for everyone. Not everyone can do great work, or wants to. But if you do want to, the complicated question of whether or not to work on what interests you the most becomes simple. The answer is yes. The root of great work is a sort of ambitious curiosity, and you can’t manufacture that.     </p><p>但这并不意味着这对每个人都是正确的建议。不是每个人都能或都想做出伟大的成就。但如果你想，那么 “是否该做自己最感兴趣的事” 这个复杂的问题就会变得简单 —— 答案是 “是”。伟大成就的根源，是一种充满野心的好奇心，而这种好奇心是无法刻意制造的。</p><p>Notes </p><p>[1] These examples show why it’s a mistake to assume that economic inequality must be evidence of some kind of brokenness or unfairness. It’s obvious that different people have different interests, and that some interests yield far more money than others, so how can it not be obvious that some people will end up much richer than others? In a world where some people like to write enterprise software and others like to make studio pottery, economic inequality is the natural outcome. </p><p>[1] 这些例子说明，认为 “经济不平等一定是某种缺陷或不公的证据” 是错误的。显然，不同的人有不同的兴趣，有些兴趣能带来多得多的钱，那么有些人比其他人富有得多，这不也是显而易见的吗？在一个有人喜欢写企业软件、有人喜欢做工作室陶艺的世界里，经济不平等是自然的结果。</p><p>[2] Difficulty choosing between interests is a different matter. That’s not always due to ignorance. It’s often intrinsically difficult. I still have trouble doing it. </p><p>[2] 在不同兴趣之间难以抉择则是另一回事。这并不总是因为信息不足，往往本质上就很难。我至今也很难做到。</p><p>[3] You can’t always take people at their word on this. Since it’s more prestigious to work on things you’re interested in than to be driven by money, people who are driven mainly by money will often claim to be more interested in their work than they actually are. One way to test such claims is by doing the following thought experiment: if their work didn’t pay well, would they take day jobs doing something else in order to do it in their spare time? Lots of mathematicians and scientists and engineers would. Historically lots have. But I don’t think as many investment bankers would.</p><p>[3] 在这一点上，你不能总是轻信别人的话。因为 “为兴趣工作” 比 “为钱工作” 更体面，所以那些主要为钱工作的人，往往会宣称自己对工作的兴趣比实际更深。检验这种说法的一个方法是做这样一个思想实验：如果他们的工作薪水不高，他们会做一份其他的日常工作，以便在业余时间继续做这份工作吗？很多数学家、科学家和工程师会这么做。历史上很多人都是如此。但我觉得，投资银行家里这么做的人不会太多。</p>]]></content>
    
    
    <categories>
      
      <category>文章翻译</category>
      
    </categories>
    
    
    <tags>
      
      <tag>PAUL GRAHAM</tag>
      
    </tags>
    
  </entry>
  
  
  
  <entry>
    <title>好的写作</title>
    <link href="/2025/07/14/good-wrting/"/>
    <url>/2025/07/14/good-wrting/</url>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="GOOD-WRITING"><a href="#GOOD-WRITING" class="headerlink" title="GOOD WRITING"></a>GOOD WRITING</h2><p>原文链接: <a href="https://paulgraham.com/goodwriting.html">https://paulgraham.com/goodwriting.html</a></p><h3 id="一、听起来好-与-观点正确"><a href="#一、听起来好-与-观点正确" class="headerlink" title="一、听起来好 与 观点正确"></a>一、听起来好 与 观点正确</h3><p>There are two senses in which writing can be good: it can sound good, and the ideas can be right. It can have nice, flowing sentences, and it can draw correct conclusions about important things. It might seem as if these two kinds of good would be unrelated, like the speed of a car and the color it’s painted. And yet I don’t think they are. I think writing that sounds good is more likely to be right. </p><p>好的写作可以体现在两个方面：一是<strong>听起来好</strong>，二是<strong>思想正确</strong>。它可以拥有流畅优美的句子，也可以对重要事物得出正确的结论。乍看之下，这两种“好”似乎毫无关联，就像汽车的速度和它的颜色一样互不相干。然而，我认为它们并非如此。<strong>我认为听起来好的文字，更可能是正确的。</strong></p><p>So here we have the most exciting kind of idea: one that seems both preposterous and true. Let’s examine it. How can this possibly be true? </p><p>于是，我们遇到了最令人兴奋的那种观点：一个看似荒谬却又真实的想法。让我们仔细审视它——这怎么可能成立？</p><p>I know it’s true from writing. You can’t simultaneously optimize two unrelated things; when you push one far enough, you always end up sacrificing the other. And yet no matter how hard I push, I never find myself having to choose between the sentence that sounds best and the one that expresses an idea best. If I did, it would be frivolous to care how sentences sound. But in practice it feels the opposite of frivolous. Fixing sentences that sound bad seems to help get the ideas right. [1] </p><p>我从写作中知道这是真的。你无法同时优化两件毫无关联的事情；当你把其中一件事推到极致时，总会牺牲另一件。然而，无论我如何努力，我从未发现自己必须在“听起来最好的句子”和“表达思想最准确的句子”之间做选择。如果真是这样，纠结句子的音律就显得轻浮了。但实践中，这种感觉恰恰相反——<strong>修改听起来别扭的句子，似乎能帮助理清思想</strong>[1]</p><p>By right I mean more than just true. Getting the ideas right means developing them well — drawing the conclusions that matter most, and exploring each one to the right level of detail. So getting the ideas right is not just a matter of saying true things, but saying the right true things. </p><p>这里的“正确”不仅仅是“真实”。思想正确意味着充分发展它们——得出最重要的结论，并以恰当的细节层次展开。因此，思想正确不只是说真话，而是说出<strong>该说的真话</strong>。</p><p>How could trying to make sentences sound good help you do that? The clue to the answer is something I noticed 30 years ago when I was doing the layout for my first book. Sometimes when you’re laying out text you have bad luck. For example, you get a section that runs one line longer than the page. I don’t know what ordinary typesetters do in this situation, but what I did was rewrite the section to make it a line shorter. You’d expect such an arbitrary constraint to make the writing worse. But I found, to my surprise, that it never did. I always ended up with something I liked better. </p><p>为什么追求句子的音律能帮助做到这一点？答案的线索来自30年前我为第一本书排版时的发现。排版时偶尔会遇到厄运：比如某个章节比页面多出一行。我不知道普通排版师会怎么做，但我的解决方法是重写那段，让它缩短一行。这种武断的限制本该让文字变得更糟，但出乎意料的是，结果总是更好。</p><h3 id="二、文章的重力定律"><a href="#二、文章的重力定律" class="headerlink" title="二、文章的重力定律"></a>二、文章的重力定律</h3><p>I don’t think this was because my writing was especially careless. I think if you pointed to a random paragraph in anything written by anyone and told them to make it slightly shorter (or longer), they’d probably be able to come up with something better.</p><p>The best analogy for this phenomenon is when you shake a bin full of different objects. The shakes are arbitrary motions. Or more precisely, they’re not calculated to make any two specific objects fit more closely together. And yet repeated shaking inevitably makes the objects discover brilliantly clever ways of packing themselves. Gravity won’t let them become less tightly packed, so any change has to be a change for the better. [2] </p><p>我不认为这是因为我的写作特别粗心。我相信，如果随机指一段别人的文字并要求稍作删减（或扩充），他们很可能改得更好。</p><p>这种现象的最佳类比是摇晃装满杂物的箱子。摇晃是随机的动作，或者说，它并非为了让某两件物品更紧密贴合。然而，反复摇晃最终会让物品找到绝妙的排列方式。重力不允许它们松散，所以任何变化都只能是优化[2]。</p><p>So it is with writing. If you have to rewrite an awkward passage, you’ll never do it in a way that makes it less true. You couldn’t bear it, any more than gravity could bear things floating upward. So any change in the ideas has to be a change for the better. </p><p>写作也是如此。如果你必须重写一段拗口的文字，绝不会以牺牲真实性为代价。你无法忍受这种妥协，就像重力无法接受物体向上飘浮。因此，思想上的任何调整都只能是改进。</p><p>It’s obvious once you think about it. Writing that sounds good is more likely to be right for the same reason that a well-shaken bin is more likely to be tightly packed. But there’s something else going on as well. Sounding good isn’t just a random external force that leaves the ideas in an essay better off. It actually helps you to get them right. </p><p>细想之下，这显而易见。<strong>听起来好的文字更可能是正确的，就像摇晃充分的箱子更可能紧凑</strong>。但还有另一层原因：音律并非只是随机外力，被动地优化文章思想——它<strong>主动</strong>帮助你理清思路。</p><h3 id="三、好的文章是易读的"><a href="#三、好的文章是易读的" class="headerlink" title="三、好的文章是易读的"></a>三、好的文章是易读的</h3><p>The reason is that it makes the essay easier to read. It’s less work to read writing that flows well. How does that help the writer? Because the writer is the first reader. When I’m working on an essay, I spend far more time reading than writing. I’ll reread some parts 50 or 100 times, replaying the thoughts in them and asking myself, like someone sanding a piece of wood, does anything catch? Does anything feel wrong? And the easier the essay is to read, the easier it is to notice if something catches. </p><p>因为音律让文章更易读。流畅的文字减轻了阅读负担。这对作者有何帮助？因为<strong>作者是第一位读者</strong>。写文章时，我花在阅读上的时间远多于写作。某些段落我会重读50甚至100遍，反复咀嚼其中的思想，像打磨木头一样自问：是否有阻滞？是否有不对劲？文章越易读，越容易发现这些问题。</p><p>So yes, the two senses of good writing are connected in at least two ways. Trying to make writing sound good makes you fix mistakes unconsciously, and also helps you fix them consciously; it shakes the bin of ideas, and also makes mistakes easier to see. But now that we’ve dissolved one layer of preposterousness, I can’t resist adding another. Does sounding good do more than just help you get the ideas right? Is writing that sounds good inherently more likely to be right? Crazy as it may seem, I think that’s true too. </p><p>因此，好的写作的两个维度至少通过两种方式关联：追求音律能让你无意识地修正错误，也有助于有意识地改进；它既“摇晃思想的箱子”，又让错误更易察觉。但既然我们已经揭开了一层荒谬，我不妨再添一层：**音律的作用是否不止于辅助思想正确？听起来好的文字是否天生更可能是正确的？**尽管看似疯狂，我认为确实如此。</p><p>Obviously there’s a connection at the level of individual words. There are lots of words in English that sound like what they mean, often in wonderfully subtle ways. Glitter. Round. Scrape. Prim. Cavalcade. But the sound of good writing depends even more on the way you put words together, and there’s a connection at that level too. </p><p>显然，单个词汇层面就存在关联。英语中许多词的发音暗示其含义，且方式精妙至极。比如“glitter”（闪烁）、“round”（圆润）、“scrape”（刮擦）、“prim”（刻板）、“cavalcade”（队列）。但好文章的音律更多取决于词语组合方式，而这一层面同样存在联系。</p><h3 id="四、好的节奏产生好的文章"><a href="#四、好的节奏产生好的文章" class="headerlink" title="四、好的节奏产生好的文章"></a>四、好的节奏产生好的文章</h3><p>When writing sounds good, it’s mostly because it has good rhythm. But the rhythm of good writing is not the rhythm of music, or the meter of verse. It’s not so regular. If it were, it wouldn’t be good, because the rhythm of good writing has to match the ideas in it, and ideas have all kinds of different shapes. Sometimes they’re simple and you just state them. But other times they’re more subtle, and you need longer, more complicated sentences to tease out all the implications. </p><p>文章听起来好，主要因其节奏得当。但优秀写作的节奏并非音乐的韵律或诗歌的格律，它没那么规整。如果规整，反而不好，因为好文章的节奏必须匹配其中的思想，而思想的形态千差万别。有时它们简单直接，只需陈述；有时则微妙复杂，需要更长的句子梳理全部内涵。</p><p>An essay is a cleaned up train of thought, in the same way dialogue is cleaned up conversation, and a train of thought has a natural rhythm. So when an essay sounds good, it’s not merely because it has a pleasing rhythm, but because it has its natural one. Which means you can use getting the rhythm right as a heuristic for getting the ideas right. And not just in principle: good writers do both simultaneously as a matter of course. Often I don’t even distinguish between the two problems. I just think Ugh, this doesn’t sound right; what do I mean to say here? [3] </p><p>文章是整理过的思路轨迹，如同对白是加工过的对话，而思路自有其自然节奏。因此，文章音律好不仅因为节奏悦耳，更因为节奏<strong>自然</strong>。这意味着你可以把节奏正确作为思想正确的启发式标准。而且不仅是理论上的——优秀作者在实践中会同步解决这两个问题。我常甚至不区分它们，只是觉得“呃，这里听起来不对——我到底想说什么？”[3]</p><p>The sound of writing turns out to be more like the shape of a plane than the color of a car. If it looks good, as Kelly Johnson used to say, it will fly well. </p><p>最终，文字的音律更像飞机的气动外形，而非汽车的颜色。正如凯利·约翰逊所言：“如果它看起来对，飞起来就不会差。”</p><p>This is only true of writing that’s used to develop ideas, though. It doesn’t apply when you have ideas in some other way and then write about them afterward — for example, if you build something, or conduct an experiment, and then write a paper about it. In such cases the ideas often live more in the work than the writing, so the writing can be bad even though the ideas are good. The writing in textbooks and popular surveys can be bad for the same reason: the author isn’t developing the ideas, merely describing other people’s. It’s only when you’re writing to develop ideas that there’s such a close connection between the two senses of doing it well. </p><p>不过，这仅适用于<strong>用于发展思想的写作</strong>。如果你通过其他方式（比如建造某物或做实验）获得思想后再写成文章，音律与思想的关联就会减弱。这类情况下，思想更多存在于工作中而非文字里，因此文章可能糟糕但思想正确。教科书和科普读物的文字不佳也源于此——作者并非发展思想，只是转述他人。<strong>唯有当你通过写作探索思想时，两种“好”才会紧密相连。</strong></p><h3 id="五、内部一致与真实的重合"><a href="#五、内部一致与真实的重合" class="headerlink" title="五、内部一致与真实的重合"></a>五、内部一致与真实的重合</h3><p>Ok, many people will be thinking, this seems plausible so far, but what about liars? Is it not notoriously possible for a smooth-tongued liar to write something beautiful that’s completely false? </p><p>读到此处，许多人会想：目前为止还算合理，但骗子呢？巧舌如簧的骗子难道不能写出优美而完全虚假的文字吗？</p><p>It is, of course. But not without method acting. The way to write something beautiful and false is to begin by making yourself almost believe it. So just like someone writing something beautiful and true, you’re presenting a perfectly-formed train of thought. The difference is the point where it attaches to the world. You’re saying something that would be true if certain false premises were. If for some bizarre reason the number of jobs in a country were fixed, then immigrants really would be taking our jobs. </p><p>当然可以。但前提是<strong>方法派演技</strong>。写出美丽谎言的方法，是先让自己几乎相信它。因此，与写出美丽真理的人一样，你呈现的是一段完美成型的思路。区别在于它和现实的连接点——你描述的是一种在虚假前提下成立的真实。比如，如果某国工作岗位数量固定（尽管这荒诞），那么移民确实会“抢走我们的工作”。</p><p>So it’s not quite right to say that better sounding writing is more likely to be true. Better sounding writing is more likely to be internally consistent. If the writer is honest, internal consistency and truth converge. But while we can’t safely conclude that beautiful writing is true, it’s usually safe to conclude the converse: something that seems clumsily written will usually have gotten the ideas wrong too. </p><p>因此，“音律好的文字更可能真实”并不完全准确。更准确的说法是：<strong>音律好的文字更可能内部一致</strong>。如果作者诚实，内部一致与真实自会重合。</p><p>Indeed, the two senses of good writing are more like two ends of the same thing. The connection between them is not a rigid one; the goodness of good writing is not a rod but a rope, with multiple overlapping connections running through it. But it’s hard to move one end without moving the other. It’s hard to be right without sounding right.</p><p>虽然我们不能断言优美文字必然真实，但通常可以安全地反推：<strong>笨拙的文字往往思想也有问题</strong>。</p><p>事实上，好的写作的两个维度更像是同一事物的两端。它们的联系并非 rigid（僵硬的杆），而是 rope（柔韧的绳），内含多重交织的关联。但你很难只移动一端而不牵动另一端。<strong>很难正确而不听起来正确。</strong></p><p>Notes </p><p>[1] The closest thing to an exception is when you have to go back and insert a new point into the middle of something you’ve written. This often messes up the flow, sometimes in ways you can never quite repair. But I think the ultimate source of this problem is that ideas are tree-shaped and essays are linear. You inevitably run into difficulties when you try to cram the former into the latter. Frankly it’s surprising how much you can get away with. But even so you sometimes have to resort to an endnote. </p><p>[1] 最接近例外的情况是：当你需要在已写好的内容中插入新观点时，常会破坏行文流畅性，有时甚至无法完全修复。我认为根本原因在于思想是树状结构，而文章是线性的。将前者塞进后者时难免遇到困难。说实话，能勉强做到的程度已令人惊讶。但即便如此，有时你仍不得不借助尾注。</p><p>[2] Obviously if you shake the bin hard enough the objects in it can become less tightly packed. And similarly, if you imposed some huge external constraint on your writing, like using alternating one and two syllable words, the ideas would start to suffer. </p><p>[2] 显然，如果摇晃过于剧烈，箱内物品反而会变松散。同理，如果对写作施加某些极端限制（比如交替使用单双音节词），思想就会受损。</p><p>[3] Bizarrely enough, this happened in the writing of this very paragraph. An earlier version shared several phrases in common with the preceding paragraph, and the repetition bugged me each time I reread it. When I got annoyed enough to fix it, I discovered that the repetition reflected a problem in the underlying ideas, and I fixed both simultaneously.</p><p>[3] 诡异的是，这段文字的写作过程就印证了这一点。初稿与前一段有多个重复短语，每次重读都让我不适。当我终于忍无可忍去修改时，发现重复反映了底层思想的问题，于是同步修正了两者。</p>]]></content>
    
    
    <categories>
      
      <category>文章翻译</category>
      
    </categories>
    
    
    <tags>
      
      <tag>PAUL GRAHAM</tag>
      
    </tags>
    
  </entry>
  
  
  
  
</search>
